<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298511-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298511</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10198824</doc-number>
<date>20020718</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>950</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  115</main-classification>
<further-classification>358  113</further-classification>
<further-classification>347  5</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Document print history</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6411970</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Aitken et al.</name>
<date>20020600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>707205</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6918082</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Gross et al.</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>715511</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0051166</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Tomita</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>358  113</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00004">
<othercit>Michael Larson, Using Microsoft Word 2000 1999, Special ed., pp. 1-4.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>21</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>15</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  115</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  113</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  118</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  11</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  116</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358  117</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358468</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>358407</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347  5</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>347  2</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>399  1</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040021708</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20040205</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lay</last-name>
<first-name>Daniel Travis</first-name>
<address>
<city>Meridian</city>
<state>ID</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Parry</last-name>
<first-name>Travis J.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Boise</city>
<state>ID</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hewlett-Packard Development Company, L.P.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Houston</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Popovici</last-name>
<first-name>Dov</first-name>
<department>2625</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present disclosure relates to generating print history information regarding an electronic document and recording the information into a print history property within the electronic document. Print history information includes details of each print instance, such as the date and time a document is printed, the printer used, and the computer device providing the print job. Advantages of the disclosed system and methods for creating a document print history include an ability to determine particular users who print restricted-access documents and an ability to maintain document databases.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="132.00mm" wi="86.36mm" file="US07298511-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="260.01mm" wi="164.68mm" file="US07298511-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="197.53mm" wi="154.60mm" file="US07298511-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="251.12mm" wi="90.59mm" file="US07298511-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="143.51mm" wi="85.34mm" file="US07298511-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present disclosure relates to printing, and more particularly, to recording and updating various print history information into an electronic document as part of the electronic document's properties.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Various application programs generate information about electronic files/documents as the electronic files/documents are created within the application programs. Information is typically saved within an electronic document under various properties of the document. These properties are viewable by users through a document properties tab accessible through a pull-down menu within an application. Although the information can vary from application to application, it is typically related to the document's creation. The information might therefore be categorized in properties such as an origination property that includes the document's author, creation date, revision number, who last saved the document and the date they saved it. Another property might be a statistical property containing information such as the number of pages, paragraphs, lines, words, and characters the document contains.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Although such information may be useful to the author of a document, it does not help in understanding what happens to the document after the document has been completed. Information regarding how a document is used after it has been created may be useful for various purposes. For example, print history information including when, where, and by whom a document has been printed may be a useful tool to help track the use of the document. Such information may be of particular benefit for tracking secure documents that have restricted access. Such print history information might also be useful in maintaining document databases and for metrics reporting purposes. For example, documents that have little or no print history over a given time period may be deemed to be of no use and therefore removed from a database, while those with recently active print histories might be retained in the database as still being useful.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Accordingly, the need exists for a way to accumulate print history information for individual electronic documents, maintain associations between individual electronic documents and their corresponding accumulated print history information, and present accumulated print history information to users regarding individual electronic documents.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">During the printing process of an electronic document, a print driver is configured to record print history information about the printing process into the electronic document.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In a particular embodiment, a print driver receives an electronic document from an application program executing on a client computer. The driver formats the document into a printer-friendly format and sends the document to a printer to be rendered as hardcopy output. During this process, the driver records information into the electronic document regarding the print process. Print history information for each print instance of an electronic document is made available to a user through a print history option in the electronic document's properties.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The same reference numbers are used throughout the drawings to reference like components and features.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a system environment suitable for creating a print history of an electronic document.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating in greater detail, an exemplary embodiment of an input device and a printing device that are suitable for implementation in the system environment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an example of a document properties dialog box illustrating a print history property.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a flow diagram illustrating an example method of creating a print history of an electronic document.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a flow diagram illustrating an alternate example method of creating a print history of an electronic document.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a flow diagram illustrating an alternate example method of creating a print history of an electronic document.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The present disclosure relates to generating print history information regarding an electronic document and recording the information into a print history property within the electronic document. Print history information includes details of each print instance, such as the date and time a document is printed, the printer used, and the computer device providing the print job. Advantages of the disclosed system and methods for creating a document print history include an ability to determine particular users who print restricted-access documents and an ability to maintain document databases.</p>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">Exemplary System Environment for Creating a Document Print History</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates an example of a system environment <b>100</b> suitable for creating a print history of an electronic document. The system <b>100</b> includes input device(s) <b>102</b>, printing device(s) <b>104</b>, and a communication network <b>106</b> operatively coupling input device(s) <b>102</b> to printing device(s) <b>104</b>. The communication network <b>106</b> can include both local and remote connections depending on the particular system configuration. Thus, network connection <b>106</b> may include, for example, a printer cable, a LAN (local area network), a WAN (wide area network), an intranet, the Internet, and other such suitable communications links. Network connection <b>106</b> can also include wireless communications links such as IR (infrared) or RF (radio frequency) links.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Input device(s) <b>102</b> can be implemented as a variety of general purpose computing devices including, for example, a personal computer (PC), a laptop computer, a Macintosh, a workstation computer, and other devices configured to communicate with printing device(s) <b>104</b>. An input device <b>102</b> typically provides a user with the ability to manipulate or otherwise prepare in electronic form, an image or document to be rendered as an image that is printed or otherwise formed onto a print medium by a printer <b>104</b> after transmission over network <b>106</b>. In general, input device <b>102</b> outputs data to printer <b>104</b> in a suitable PDL (page description language) driver format, such as PCL or PostScript. In addition, input device <b>102</b> is configured to record print history information into electronic documents/files as discussed more fully below with respect to particular embodiments.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">This disclosure is applicable to various types of printing devices <b>104</b> capable of rendering PDL data in printed form on a print medium, such as printing pixels on paper. Therefore, printing devices <b>104</b> can include devices such as laser-based printers, ink-based printers, dot matrix printers, dry medium printers, plotters and the like. In addition, printing devices <b>104</b> might also include various multi-function peripheral (MFP) devices that combine a printing function with other functions such as facsimile transmission, scanning, copying and the like. In general, a printer <b>104</b> receives input data as a print job in a suitable PDL format transmitted by input device <b>102</b> over network <b>106</b>. Printer <b>104</b> is configured to render the print job as a hard copy image document formed on various print media, such as paper or transparencies.</p>
<p id="h-0007" num="0000">Exemplary System Embodiment for Creating a Document Print History</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram illustrating in greater detail, an exemplary embodiment of an input device <b>102</b> and a printer <b>104</b> suitable for implementation in the system environment <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Input device <b>102</b> is embodied as a client computer <b>102</b> operatively coupled to printer <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Client computer <b>102</b> typically includes a processor <b>200</b>, a volatile memory <b>202</b> (i.e., RAM), and a nonvolatile memory <b>204</b> (e.g., ROM, hard disk, floppy disk, CD-ROM, etc.). Nonvolatile memory <b>204</b> generally provides storage of computer/processor-readable instructions, data structures, program modules and other data for client computer <b>102</b>. Client computer <b>102</b> may implement various application programs <b>206</b> stored in memory <b>204</b> and executable on processor <b>200</b> to create or otherwise form an electronic document or image (e.g., text and/or graphics) such as electronic document <b>208</b> on a computer display screen <b>210</b>. Such documents/images are transferable over network connection <b>106</b> to printer <b>104</b> for creating hard copies of the documents/images. Applications <b>206</b> typically include software programs implementing, for example, word processors, spread sheets, network browsers, multimedia players, illustrators, computer-aided design tools and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Client computer <b>102</b> may also implement one or more software-based device drivers such as printer driver <b>212</b> that are stored in memory <b>204</b> and executable on processor <b>200</b>. Device drivers might also be implemented on the specific devices they are “driving” such as printer <b>104</b>. In general, printer driver <b>212</b> formats document information into a page description language (PDL) such as PostScript or Printer Control Language (PCL) or another appropriate format which is output to printer <b>104</b>. In the current embodiment, printer driver <b>212</b> additionally includes a print history module <b>214</b> generally configured to generate print history information <b>216</b> and record it into electronic document files <b>208</b> as discussed more fully herein below.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Printer <b>104</b> of the <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> embodiment includes controller <b>212</b> that, in general, processes data from client computer <b>102</b> to control the output of printer <b>104</b> through printer device engine <b>226</b>. The controller <b>212</b> typically includes a data processing unit or CPU <b>220</b>, a volatile memory <b>222</b> (i.e., RAM), and a nonvolatile memory <b>224</b>. Nonvolatile memory <b>224</b> can include various computer storage media such as ROM, flash memory, a hard disk, a removable floppy disk, a removable optical disk and the like. Nonvolatile memory <b>224</b> generally provides storage of computer/processor-readable instructions, data structures, program modules and the like for printer <b>104</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">As mentioned above, client computer <b>102</b> implements printer driver <b>212</b>, which includes print history module <b>214</b>. Print history module <b>214</b> is configured to record print history information <b>216</b> into an electronic document <b>208</b> during a print process for the electronic document <b>208</b>. Typically a print process is initiated from within an application program <b>206</b> by a user selecting a print command. The print command initiates a print process for an electronic document <b>208</b> that has been created or otherwise accessed by an application program <b>206</b>. For example, a user working in a word-processing application such as Microsoft® Word®, may finish writing a document and select the print command from within the application, which initiates a print process through printer driver <b>212</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Generally, during the creation of an electronic document <b>208</b> within an application program <b>206</b>, information related to the creation of the electronic document <b>208</b> is generated by the application program <b>206</b> and stored in the electronic document <b>208</b> as a property of the electronic document <b>208</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates an example of such document properties for a document entitled “Unicode.doc”. The document properties are illustrated in a screen shot <b>300</b> on a display screen <b>210</b> of a computer such as client computer <b>102</b>. The information provided in the document properties of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> includes statistical information <b>302</b> such as the number of pages, words, characters, lines, and paragraphs in the document. An “origin” property <b>304</b> is also illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> and contains information including the document's author, the last person or computer to save the document, the document's revision number, the document's creation date, and the document's last saved date.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Print history module <b>214</b> functions in a similar manner to gather or generate information related to the process of printing an electronic document <b>208</b>, and to record or save that information as print history information <b>216</b> into the electronic document <b>208</b>. Thus, the document properties of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> include a print history <b>306</b> property tab. Within the print history <b>306</b> property tab are print instance tabs (e.g., <b>308</b>, <b>322</b>) that contain print history information related to the electronic document <b>208</b>. Each time the electronic document <b>208</b> is printed, a print instance (e.g., <b>308</b>, <b>322</b>) is generated and stored in the electronic document <b>208</b>. Each print instance contains print history information that corresponds with the particular print process implemented for that print instance. For example, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, print instance #<b>1</b> <b>308</b> contains print history information that indicates the print process was initiated on a computer <b>102</b>, “D3×n4×01” <b>310</b>, and that the printing was implemented on a printer <b>104</b>, “HP LJ 8150 PCL6 (Copy 3)” <b>312</b>. Print instance #<b>1</b> <b>308</b> also contains print history information that indicates the printer driver <b>212</b>, <b>314</b> that was used, the date <b>316</b> and time <b>318</b> of the print process, and the number of copies <b>320</b> generated during the print process. It is noted that the print history information illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is only an example of the sort of information that might be recorded into an electronic document <b>208</b>. Various other print history information might also be recorded into an electronic document <b>208</b>.</p>
<p id="h-0008" num="0000">Exemplary Methods for Creating a Document Print History</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Example methods for creating a print history of an electronic document will now be described with primary reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4</figref>, <b>5</b> and <b>6</b>. The methods apply generally to the exemplary embodiments discussed above with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>2</b> and <b>3</b>. The elements of the described methods may be performed by any appropriate means, such as by the execution of processor-readable instructions defined on processor-readable media, such as a disk, a ROM or other such memory device.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Referring to the method illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, at block <b>400</b>, a print process is implemented for printing an electronic document. The print process typically begins when a user selects a print command from within an application program. The print process activates a print driver which processes the electronic document for printing. At block <b>402</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, print history information is recorded into the electronic document that relates to the print process. The information typically includes identification information for the computer <b>102</b> from which the print process is initiated, the printer <b>104</b> rendering the electronic document as hardcopy output, the print driver used to process the electronic document, the date and time of the print process, the number of copies made, and so on.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Referring now to the method illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, at block <b>500</b>, an electronic document is received and a print process is initiated. The electronic document is typically received from an application program executing on a client computer <b>102</b>. The print process includes formatting the electronic document into a PDL (page description language) at block <b>502</b>, and sending the PDL to a printer for rendering as hardcopy output at block <b>504</b>. At block <b>506</b>, print history information is recorded into the electronic document regarding the print process. Similar to the previous method, the print history information typically includes identification information for the computer <b>102</b> from which the print process is initiated, the printer <b>104</b> rendering the electronic document as hardcopy output, the print driver used to process the electronic document, the date and time of the print process, the number of copies made, and so on. At block <b>508</b>, the print history information is displayed. The information is typically displayed on a computer display screen through the user interface of a print driver upon selection by a user of a document properties option.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Referring now to the method illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, at block <b>600</b>, a first print process is implemented for printing an electronic document. The first print process typically begins when a user selects a print command from within an application program. The print process activates a print driver which processes the electronic document for printing. At block <b>602</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, print history information regarding the first print process is recorded into the electronic document. The print history information is generally recorded into a first print instance of a print history property on the electronic document. As in the previous methods, the information typically includes identification information for the computer <b>102</b> from which the first print process is initiated, the printer <b>104</b> rendering the electronic document as hardcopy output, the print driver used to process the electronic document, the date and time of the print process, the number of copies made, and so on.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">At block <b>604</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a second print process is implemented for printing the electronic document. The second print process may be initiated from the same computer <b>102</b> as the first print process, or it may be initiated from a different computer <b>102</b>. Again, the second print process typically begins when a user selects a print command from within an application program. The second print process activates a print driver which processes the electronic document for printing. At block <b>606</b>, print history information regarding the second print process is recorded into the electronic document. The print history information is generally recorded into a second print instance of the print history property on the electronic document. Thus, print history information from different print processes is distinguishable by different print instances stored on the electronic document. As in the previous methods, the print history information typically includes identification information for the computer <b>102</b> from which the first print process is initiated, the printer <b>104</b> rendering the electronic document as hardcopy output, the print driver used to process the electronic document, the date and time of the print process, the number of copies made, and so on. The various items of print history information may vary between each print instance. For example, the computer, printer, and printer driver may be different for each print instance. The date and time of each print instance will also be different.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Although the description above uses language that is specific to structural features and/or methodological acts, it is to be understood that the invention defined in the appended claims is not limited to the specific features or acts described. Rather, the specific features and acts are disclosed as exemplary forms of implementing the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Additionally, while one or more methods have been disclosed by means of flow diagrams and text associated with the blocks of the flow diagrams, it is to be understood that the blocks do not necessarily have to be performed in the order in which they were presented, and that an alternative order may result in similar advantages.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is: </us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A computer-readable medium storing a computer-executable program comprising computer-executable instructions configured for:
<claim-text>implementing a first print process for an electronic document; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>recording print history information into the electronic document regarding the first print process,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print history information comprises identification of a computer device from which the first print process was initiated, identification of a printer used for the first print process, a time of the first print process, and a date of the first print process.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the implementing further comprises:
<claim-text>receiving the electronic document;</claim-text>
<claim-text>formatting the electronic document into a PDL (page description language); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>sending the PDL to a printer to be rendered as hardcopy output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the recording print history information into the electronic document regarding the first print process further comprises recording print history information in a first print instance print history property of the electronic document.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, comprising further computer-executable instructions configured for:
<claim-text>implementing a second print process for the electronic document; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>recording print history information into the electronic document regarding the second print process.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the recording print history information into the electronic document regarding the second print process further comprises recording print history information in a second print instance print history property of the electronic document.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, comprising further computer-executable instructions configured for:
<claim-text>displaying the print history information through a printer driver user interface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the displaying further comprises displaying a user-selectable print history category within a document properties dialog box.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the print history information further comprises identification of a printer driver which processed the electronic document for the first print process, a number of copies made during the first print process, and a hardcopy output format of the first print process.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the PDL is in a format selected from the group of formats comprising:
<claim-text>PCL (printer control language); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>PostScript.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A computer-readable medium storing a computer-executable program comprising computer-executable instructions configured for:
<claim-text>implementing a first print process for an electronic document;</claim-text>
<claim-text>recording print history information into the electronic document as a first print instance regarding the first print process;</claim-text>
<claim-text>implementing a second print process for the electronic document; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>recording print history information into the electronic document as a second print instance regarding the second print process,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first print instance and the second print instance are different, and the print history information from the first print instance and the print history information from the second print instance are different.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the implementing further comprises:
<claim-text>formatting the electronic document into a PDL (page description language); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>sending the PDL to a printer to be rendered as hardcopy output.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, comprising further computer-executable instructions configured for:
<claim-text>displaying the print history Information through a printer driver user interface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A computer-readable medium storing a computer-executable program comprising computer-executable instructions configured for:
<claim-text>receiving an electronic document from an application program executing on a computer device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>formatting the electronic document into a PDL (page description language);</claim-text>
<claim-text>sending the PDL to a printer to be rendered as hardcopy output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>recording print history information into the electronic document; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>displaying the print history information in a user interface of a printer driver on a display screen of the computer device,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print history information comprises a computer identification identifying the computer device, a printer identification identifying the printer, a printer driver identification identifying a printer driver used for the formatting a date associated with the sending, a time associated with the sending, and a number of copies of hardcopy output rendered.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A computer-readable medium as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref>, wherein the print history information further comprises a document format associated with the hardcopy output.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A method of recording document print history comprising:
<claim-text>implementing a print process for an electronic document; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>recording document print history information into the electronic document regarding the print process,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print history information comprises identification of a computer device from which the print process was initiated, identification of a printer used for the print process, a time of the print process, and a date of the print process.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method of recording document print history comprising:
<claim-text>implementing a first print process for an electronic document;</claim-text>
<claim-text>recording print history information into the electronic document as a first print instance regarding the first print process;</claim-text>
<claim-text>implementing a second print process for the electronic document; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>recording print history information into the electronic document as a second print instance regarding the second print process,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first print instance and the second print instance are different, and the print history information from the first print instance and the print history information from the second print instance are different.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method of recording document print history comprising:
<claim-text>receiving an electronic document from an application program executing on a computer device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>formatting the electronic document into a PDL (page description language);</claim-text>
<claim-text>sending the PDL to a printer to be rendered as hardcopy output;</claim-text>
<claim-text>recording print history information into the electronic document; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>displaying the print history information in a user interface of a printer driver on a display screen of to computer device,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print history information comprises a computer identification identifying the computer device, a printer identification identifying the printer, a printer driver identification identifying a printer driver used for the formatting, a date associated with the sending, a time associated with the sending, and a number of copies of hardcopy output rendered.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A computer comprising:
<claim-text>an electronic file;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a printer driver; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a print history module associated with the printer driver, the print history module configured to record print history information into the electronic file as a different print instance each time a print process is implemented with respect to the electronic file,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the electronic file includes more than one print instance for the electronic file, and each print instance contains the print history information corresponding with the particular print process implemented for the respective print instance.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A computer as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00018">claim 18</claim-ref>, further comprising a display screen, the print history module further configured to display on the display screen, a document properties dialog box that includes a user-selectable print history category for displaying the print history information upon selection by a user.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A computer comprising:
<claim-text>an electronic file that includes print history information;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a printer driver, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a print history module associated with the printer driver, the print history module configured to update the print history information when a print process is implemented with respect to the electronic file,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print history information comprises identification of a computer from which the print process was initiated, identification of a printer used for the print process, a time of the print process, and a date of the print process.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A system comprising:
<claim-text>an application program for generating an electronic document and initiating a print process for the electronic document; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a print driver for recording print history information into the electronic document regarding the print process,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the print history information comprises identification of a computer from which the print process was initiated, identification of a printer used for the print process, a time of the print process, and a date of the print process.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
