<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296715-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296715</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11348688</doc-number>
<date>20060207</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>26</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>D</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>91</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>223101</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Ergonomic thimble</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>190897</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Porter et al.</name>
<date>18770500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>260695</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lubin</name>
<date>18820700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>223101</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>534211</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>English</name>
<date>18950200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>1522484</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Baker</name>
<date>19250100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>D150696</doc-number>
<kind>S</kind>
<name>Howser</name>
<date>19480800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2494439</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gorka et al.</name>
<date>19500100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>  7121</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2568951</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cudly</name>
<date>19510900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2588528</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Howser</name>
<date>19520300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>223101</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2953286</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Fowler</name>
<date>19600900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3531029</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lee</name>
<date>19700900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>223101</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3722763</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Heinz</name>
<date>19730300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4102479</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Braley</name>
<date>19780700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4149661</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Curtiss</name>
<date>19790400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4694843</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Casenhiser</name>
<date>19870900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4955515</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Brull</name>
<date>19900900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>223101</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00016">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>D409829</doc-number>
<kind>S</kind>
<name>Hanner</name>
<date>19990500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00017">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6726068</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Miller</name>
<date>20040400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>223 99</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>223101</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  2 21</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>  7121</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 30127</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jerome</last-name>
<first-name>G. Victoria</first-name>
<address>
<street>530 Peregrine Cir.</street>
<city>Longmont</city>
<state>CO</state>
<postcode>80501</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tracy</last-name>
<first-name>Emery L.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Welch</last-name>
<first-name>Gary L.</first-name>
<department>3765</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Sutton</last-name>
<first-name>Andrew W</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A thimble device for protecting fingers and thumb from a needle during a sewing operation is provided. The thimble device comprises a top needle bearing surface having a dimple formed therein and two side surfaces with each side surface having an angled portion and a curved portion. The curved portions are sized and shaped for receiving a portion of the fingers when the thimble device is seated between the fingers. The thimble device further includes an angled front surface, an angled rear surface, and a curved bottom surface sized and shaped for receiving a portion of the thumb.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="76.71mm" wi="132.93mm" file="US07296715-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="209.21mm" wi="151.47mm" file="US07296715-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="244.77mm" wi="167.13mm" file="US07296715-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates generally to a thimble and, more particularly, the invention relates to an ergonomic thimble allowing a user to always maintain a sewing needle in hand while wearing the ergonomic thimble in the user's dominant hand for better maneuverability and keeping the user's other hand free for holding and manipulating the fabric or project with maximum efficiency.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">It is well known in the art that hand sewing can require a considerable amount of repetitive force to be applied to a sewing needle by a finger in order to stitch fabric. Finger protective devices and thimbles have long been used for their ability to prevent injury to the fingers during stitching operation, especially with heavy fabrics. Among the earliest examples of thimbles is a somewhat truncated conical shaped metal cap designed to slip over and be adhered to the end of the sewing digit by frictional means. The top and sides of the thimble are dimpled to receive the end of the needle and prevent slippage as force is applied. Unfortunately, these small dimples rapidly become either filled with dirt or grime or else the dimples are not deep enough to adequately engage the eye end of needles when considerable pressure is applied in order to force them through the fabric being sewn. Such thimbles are in use even today.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is often difficult to keep the needle in hand when using a thimble. Sometimes, the user will stop to put the thimble on, push the needle through, and then remove the thimble to grab the needle once more. Alternatively, the user wears the thimble on the opposite hand and continues to work uninterrupted. Unfortunately, this means that the thimble is not being worn on the user's dominant hand and sewing efficiency is compromised.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In addition, while it is sometimes awkward to manage the fabric or project while wearing a conventional thimble, it can also be painful if the conventional thimble fits too tight or if there is a health problem such as arthritis affecting the user's fingers or hands. Wearing the thimble over a thumb or finger can be problematic for persons with digits that are smaller, or more likely, larger than the typical “one size fits all” thimble. Or, a nice manicure can make wearing the typical thimble impractical.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Accordingly, there exists a need for an ergonomic thimble which allows a user to always maintain a sewing needle in hand. Additionally, a need exists for an ergonomic thimble which can be worn on the user's dominant hand for better maneuverability. Furthermore, there exists a need for an ergonomic thimble which keeps the user's other hand free for holding and manipulating the fabric or project with maximum efficiency.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention is a thimble device for protecting fingers from a needle during a sewing operation. The thimble device comprises a top needle bearing surface and two side surfaces with each side surface having a curved portion for receiving a portion of the fingers. The thimble device further includes a front surface, a rear surface, and a bottom surface.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In addition, the present invention includes a thimble device for protecting fingers and thumb from a needle during a sewing operation. The thimble device comprises a top needle bearing surface having a dimple formed therein and two side surfaces with each side surface having an angled portion and a curved portion. The curved portions are sized and shaped for receiving a portion of the fingers when the thimble device is seated between the fingers. The thimble device further includes an angled front surface, an angled rear surface, and a curved bottom surface sized and shaped for receiving a portion of the thumb.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present invention further includes a method for using the thimble device for protecting a hand during sewing operations with the hand having an index finger, a middle finger, and a thumb. The method comprises positioning the thimble device between the index finger and the middle finger, resting a portion of the index finger in the curved portion of one of the side surfaces, resting a portion of the middle finger in the curved portion of the other side surface, seating a portion of the thumb into the curved bottom surface, positioning an eye end of the needle in the dimple, and applying pressure to the needle.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a top plan view illustrating an ergonomic thimble, constructed in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an elevational front view illustrating the ergonomic thimble, constructed in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an elevational side view illustrating the ergonomic thimble, constructed in accordance with the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective view illustrating the ergonomic thimble, constructed in accordance with the present invention, with the ergonomic thimble being used to push a needle through fabric; and</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a perspective view illustrating the ergonomic thimble, constructed in accordance with the present invention, with the ergonomic thimble being maintained in the user's hand while the user manipulates a needle.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-5</figref>, the present invention is an ergonomic thimble, indicated generally at <b>10</b>, for sewing with a sewing needle <b>12</b>, thread <b>14</b> within the sewing needle <b>12</b>, and fabric <b>16</b>. The ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> of the present invention allows a user to always maintain the sewing needle <b>12</b> in hand while wearing the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> in the user's dominant hand for better maneuverability and keeping the user's other hand free for holding and manipulating the fabric <b>16</b> or project with maximum efficiency.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> of the present invention is preferably constructed from a durable material including, but not limited to, wood, plastic, metal, ceramics, etc. The ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> preferably has a height of approximately 1.125 inches, a width of approximately 0.4375 inches, and a depth of approximately 0.75 inches. It should be noted that while specific heights, widths, and depths of the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> have been described and illustrated herein, it is within the scope of the present invention for the ergonomic thimble to have any height, width, or depth, depending on the desires of the user.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">As best illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref>, the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> of the present invention has a top needle bearing surface <b>18</b>, two side surfaces <b>20</b>, a front surface <b>22</b>, a rear surface <b>24</b>, and a bottom surface <b>26</b>. Preferably the top needle bearing surface <b>18</b> has an indented or concave dimple <b>28</b> for receiving an eye end of the needle <b>12</b>. The dimple <b>28</b> is sized and shaped to maintain the eye end of the needle <b>12</b> therein during sewing operations.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The side surfaces <b>20</b> of the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> of the present invention each include a curved portion <b>30</b> adjacent the bottom surface <b>26</b> and an angled portion <b>32</b> adjacent the top needle bearing surface <b>18</b>. The curved portion <b>30</b> of the side surfaces <b>20</b> are sized and shaped for receiving the fingers of the user when the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> is seated between the fingers. Preferably, the curved portions <b>30</b> of the side surfaces <b>20</b> are curved with an approximately 0.5 inch curve radius. While the curved portions <b>30</b> of the side surfaces <b>20</b> have been described as having an approximately 0.5 inch curve radius, it is within the scope of the present invention for the curved portions <b>30</b> of the side surfaces <b>210</b> to have a curve radius greater than or less than approximately 0.5 inch.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The bottom surface <b>26</b> of the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> of the present invention is curved for receiving the thumb of the user when the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> is seated between the fingers. Preferably, the bottom surface <b>26</b> is curved with an approximately 0.5 inch curve radius. Like the side surfaces <b>20</b>, while the bottom surface <b>26</b> has been described as having an approximately 0.5 inch curve radius, it is within the scope of the present invention for the bottom surface <b>26</b> to have a curve radius greater than or less than approximately 0.5 inch.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The front surface <b>22</b> and the rear surface <b>24</b> of the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> of the present invention are angled inward from the bottom surface <b>26</b> to the top needle bearing surface <b>18</b> such that the area of the bottom surface <b>26</b> is greater than the area of the top needle bearing surface <b>18</b>. Angling of the front surface <b>22</b> and the rear surface <b>24</b>, together with the angled portions <b>32</b> of the side surfaces <b>20</b>, allows the top needle bearing surface <b>18</b> to maneuver into tight, small spaces as may be required during sewing operations.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Operation and use of the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> of the present invention will now be described. It will be understood by those persons skilled in the art that the following description is merely one manner of operating and using the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> and other manners of use are within the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> is positioned between the index finger and middle finger of the desired hand with the curved portion <b>30</b> of one of the side surfaces <b>20</b> receiving the user's index finger and the curved portion <b>30</b> of the other side surface <b>20</b> receiving the user's middle finger. The user's thumb is then seated into the curved bottom surface <b>26</b> of the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b>. With the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> seated between the fingers, the eye end of the needle <b>12</b> is seated in the dimple <b>28</b> formed in the top needle bearing surface <b>18</b>. At this point, the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> can be used to apply pressure to the needle <b>12</b> to force the needle <b>12</b> through the fabric <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, once the needle <b>12</b> has been forced through the fabric <b>16</b>, the user's thumb is removed from its seating in the curved bottom surface <b>26</b>. By simply removing the thumb from the bottom surface <b>26</b>, all of the user's fingertips are available for further maneuvering of the needle <b>12</b>, thread <b>14</b>, and/or fabric <b>16</b>. Sewing is accomplished unimpeded by the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> which remains firmly seated between the index finger and the middle finger of the user.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> of the present invention allows the user to keep the needle <b>12</b> in hand and wear the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> with the dominant hand for better maneuverability while keeping the other hand free to hold and manipulate the fabric <b>12</b> or project with maximum efficiency. The ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> is constructed from a durable material and can be reused over and over again. In sum, the ergonomic thimble <b>10</b> of the present invention is more comfortable than a conventional thimble while increasing the efficiency of the sewing project.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The foregoing exemplary descriptions and the illustrative preferred embodiments of the present invention have been explained in the drawings and described in detail, with varying modifications and alternative embodiments being taught. While the invention has been so shown, described and illustrated, it should be understood by those skilled in the art that equivalent changes in form and detail may be made therein without departing from the true spirit and scope of the invention, and that the scope of the present invention is to be limited only to the claims except as precluded by the prior art. Moreover, the invention as disclosed herein, may be suitably practiced in the absence of the specific elements which are disclosed herein.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A thimble device for protecting fingers and a thumb from a needle during a sewing operation, each finger having a tip and at least one side facing an adjacent finger, the thumb having a tip and at least one side surface, the thimble device comprising:
<claim-text>a top needle bearing surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first side surface and a closed second side surface, each side surface having a concave portion, the first side surface receiving a portion of the side of a first finger and the second side surface receiving a portion of the side of an adjacent second finger;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a front surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a rear surface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a closed bottom surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the thimble device is grippable between the sides of the adjacent first finger and the second finger with the thumb restable against the closed bottom surface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the tips of the fingers and the thumb are free from being covered by the thimble device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the top needle bearing surface includes a dimple formed therein.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the dimple formed on the top needle bearing surface is sized and shaped for receiving an eye end of the needle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the side surfaces further include an angled portion, the angled portion of the side surfaces being adjacent the top needle bearing surface and the concave portions of the side surfaces being adjacent the bottom surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the concave portions of the first side surface and the second side surface are concavoconcave surfaces sized and shaped for receiving the sides of two adjacent fingers when the ergonomic thimble is seated between the adjacent fingers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref> wherein the side surfaces are concave with an approximately 0.5 inch radius.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the bottom surface is concave for receiving a side surface of the thumb only when the ergonomic thimble is seated between the fingers.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref> wherein the bottom surface is concave with an approximately 0.5 inch radius.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the front surface and the rear surface are tapered inward from the bottom surface to the top needle bearing surface such that the area of the bottom surface is greater than the area of the top needle bearing surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A thimble device for protecting fingers and thumb from a needle during a sewing operation, each finger having a tip and at least one side facing an adjacent finger, the thumb having a tip and at least one side surface, the thimble device comprising:
<claim-text>a top needle bearing surface having a dimple formed therein;</claim-text>
<claim-text>two side surfaces, each side surface having a tapered portion and a concave portion, the side surfaces being concavoconcave surfaces, the concave portions sized and shaped for gripping between the sides of adjacent fingers when the thimble device is seated between the fingers distant from the tips of the fingers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tapered front surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tapered rear surface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a closed, curved bottom surface sized and shaped for receiving a portion of the side of the thumb, the tip of the thumb free from covered by the thimble device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the dimple formed on the top needle bearing surface is sized and shaped for receiving an eye end of the needle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the tapered portion of the side surfaces is adjacent the top needle bearing surface and the concave portions of the side surfaces are adjacent the bottom surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the side surfaces are concave with an approximately 0.5 inch radius.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the bottom surface is concave with an approximately 0.5 inch radius.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> wherein the front surface and the rear surface are tapered inward from the bottom surface to the top needle bearing surface such that the area of the bottom surface is greater than the area of the top needle bearing surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method for using a thimble device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> for protecting a hand during sewing operations, the hand having an index finger, a middle finger, and a thumb, the method comprising:
<claim-text>positioning the thimble device between the index finger and the middle finger;</claim-text>
<claim-text>resting a portion of the side of the index finger against the concave portion of one of the side surfaces;</claim-text>
<claim-text>resting a portion of the side of the middle finger against the concave portion of the other side surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>seating a portion of the thumb against the concave bottom surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>positioning an eye end of the needle in the dimple; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>applying pressure to the needle.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> and further comprising:
<claim-text>removing the thumb from against the curved bottom surface; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>maintaining the thimble device between side surfaces of the middle finger and the index finger.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> wherein the side surfaces are curved with an approximately 0.5 inch radius.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> wherein the bottom surface is curved with an approximately 0.5 inch radius.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> wherein the front surface and the rear surface are tapered inward from the bottom surface to the top needle bearing surface such that the area of the bottom surface is greater than the area of the top needle bearing surface.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
