<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298098-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298098</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11327476</doc-number>
<date>20060109</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>116</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315307</main-classification>
<further-classification>315291</further-classification>
<further-classification>315 75</further-classification>
<further-classification>315 74</further-classification>
<further-classification>315247</further-classification>
<further-classification>362378</further-classification>
<further-classification>362251</further-classification>
<further-classification>362194</further-classification>
<further-classification>362247</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Intellectual lamp unit able to be installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6168282</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Chien</name>
<date>20010100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>362 84</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0001563</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Logan</name>
<date>20050100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>315291</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315307</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315291</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315297</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315 50- 59</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315247</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315246</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362194</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362195</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362247-251</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362377</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362378</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070159111</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070712</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wang</last-name>
<first-name>Robert</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taoyuan</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chow</last-name>
<first-name>Ming</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sinorica, LLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Ceramate Technical Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taoyuan</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Vo</last-name>
<first-name>Tuyet</first-name>
<department>2821</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An intellectual lamp unit able to be installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch includes a bypass connected in parallel with a wall switch and provided with a resistance or a diode for producing potential difference or power phase difference when the wall switch is turned off. An intellectual lamp to be installed on a conventional lamp socket consists of a lamp main body disposed therein with a power processing circuit, a detecting switch, a charging circuit, a charging battery, a driving circuit, a microprocessor and a lamplight source. When the wall switch is turned on or off under the condition of normal power supply, the lamplight source can be controlled to produce or extinguish lighting, and during blackout, the lamplight source can be started to produce emergency lighting immediately, supplied with power by the charging battery.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="174.58mm" wi="233.85mm" file="US07298098-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="234.87mm" wi="176.11mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298098-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="244.09mm" wi="173.48mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298098-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="234.10mm" wi="165.95mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298098-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to an intellectual lamp unit, particularly to one able to be installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Conventional lamps controlled by wall switches are widely used for lighting a home, an office or an assembly hall.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, the conventional lamps are only used for lighting without other functions; therefore, during electric interrupting, they cannot carry out lighting and at this time, people have to rely upon emergency lamps for lighting, but it costs a lot to purchase and install emergency lamps. In addition, emergency lamps cannot function to produce lighting ordinarily; therefore, once disasters should occur and cause electric stoppage or a fire, with no emergency lighting equipment ready for use, danger might be likely to result.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The objective of the invention is to offer an intellectual lamp unit able to be installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch, which includes a bypass connected in parallel with a wall switch and provided with a resistance or a diode for producing potential difference or power phase difference when the wall switch is turned off. An intellectual lamp to be installed on a conventional lamp socket consists of a lamp main body disposed therein with a power processing circuit, a detecting switch, a charging circuit, a charging battery, a driving circuit, a microprocessor and a lamplight source. When the wall switch is turned on or off under the condition of normal power supply, the lamplight source of the intellectual lamp can be controlled to produce or extinguish lighting, and when blackout occurs, the lamplight source can be started immediately and supplied with power by the charging battery for producing emergency lighting whether the wall switch is turned on or off.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">This invention will be better understood by referring to the accompanying drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block diagram of a first preferred embodiment of the inner structure and the circuit disposition of an intellectual lamp in the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a block diagram of a second preferred embodiment of the inner structure of an intellectual lamp in the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block diagram of the second preferred embodiment of the inner structure of an intellectual lamp, having a bypass connected in parallel in another mode in the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">A first preferred embodiment of an intellectual lamp unit able to be installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch in the present invention, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, includes a bypass <b>10</b> and an intellectual lamp <b>20</b>. The intelligent lamp unit can be installed on a conventional lamp socket <b>40</b> controlled by a wall switch <b>30</b> that is connected with a main power source <b>50</b> for supplying AC to the wall switch <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The intelligent lamp <b>20</b> consists of a lamp main body <b>21</b>, a power processing circuit <b>22</b>, a detecting switch <b>23</b>, a charging circuit <b>24</b>, a charging battery <b>25</b>, a driving circuit <b>26</b>, a microprocessor <b>27</b> and a lamplight source <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The bypass <b>10</b> is connected in parallel with the wall switch <b>30</b> and provided thereon with an electronic element, such as a resistance <b>11</b> or a diode <b>12</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Thus, when the wall switch <b>30</b> is turned ON, the main power source <b>50</b> will transmit AC with a normal voltage to the lamp socket <b>40</b> through the wall switch <b>30</b>. On the contrary, when the wall switch <b>30</b> is turned OFF, it will form an open circuit to let the power source <b>50</b> pass through the bypass <b>10</b> connected in parallel with the wall switch <b>30</b>. When the bypass <b>10</b>, through which the power source <b>50</b> passes, is provided with the resistance <b>11</b>, the power source <b>50</b> will produce a reduced voltage potential difference, and when the bypass <b>10</b> is provided with a diode <b>12</b>, the power source <b>50</b> will produce a power phase difference and transmit AC with a reduced voltage or a phase-difference to the lamp socket <b>40</b>, but during blackout, the power source <b>50</b> cannot supply the lamp socket <b>40</b> with AC.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The lamp main body <b>21</b> includes a transparent shell <b>211</b> having its interior formed with an accommodating space <b>212</b> and having one end connected with a lamp connector <b>213</b> to be threadably combined and electrically connected with the conventional lamp socket <b>40</b> so that the lamp connector <b>213</b> can receive a normal-voltage alternating current supplied through the wall switch <b>30</b> and the lamp socket <b>40</b>, or receive AC with an abnormal voltage supplied through the bypass <b>10</b> and the lamp socket <b>40</b>. The AC with an abnormal voltage means AC with a reduced voltage or with a phase-difference produced after AC is transmitted by the power source <b>50</b> and passes through the bypass <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The power processing circuit <b>22</b> is installed in the accommodating space <b>212</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b> and connected with the lamp connector <b>213</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b> for receiving AC with a normal voltage or an abnormal-voltage supplied by the lamp connector <b>213</b> and rectifying it into DC with a normal voltage or an abnormal voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The detecting switch <b>23</b> is positioned in the accommodating space <b>212</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b> and connected with the power processing circuit <b>22</b> for detecting DC supplied by the power processing circuit <b>22</b>. When DC is detected to have a normal voltage or an abnormal voltage, the detecting switch <b>23</b> will transmit outward a normal signal, letting the detecting switch <b>23</b> form an open circuit. On the other hand, when the voltage value of DC is detected to be zero, the detecting switch <b>23</b> will transmit outward a blackout signal, letting the detecting switch <b>23</b> electrically turned ON.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The charging circuit <b>24</b> is disposed in the accommodating space <b>212</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b> and connected with the power processing circuit <b>22</b> for receiving DC supplied by the power processing circuit <b>22</b> and supplying DC needed for charging.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The charging battery <b>25</b> is received in the accommodating space <b>212</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b> and connected with the charging circuit <b>24</b> for receiving DC supplied by the charging circuit <b>24</b> for carrying out charging. The charging battery <b>25</b> is also connected with the detecting switch <b>23</b> so that when the detecting switch <b>23</b> is electrically connected, it will supply the charging battery <b>25</b> with DC.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The driving circuit <b>26</b> is assembled in the accommodating space <b>212</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b> and connected with both the power processing circuit <b>22</b> and the detecting switch <b>23</b> so that the driving circuit <b>26</b> can receive DC with a normal voltage or an abnormal voltage supplied by the power processing circuit <b>22</b> or receive DC supplied by the charging battery <b>25</b> through the detecting switch <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The microprocessor <b>27</b> is connected with the charging circuit <b>24</b> and the charging battery <b>25</b> as well as the detecting switch <b>23</b>. On receiving a normal signal transmitted by the detecting switch <b>23</b>, the microprocessor <b>27</b> will command the charging circuit <b>24</b> to charge the charging battery <b>25</b>. On the other hand, when receiving a blackout signal transmitted by the detecting switch <b>23</b>, the microprocessor <b>27</b> will command the charging battery <b>25</b> to supply the driving circuit <b>26</b> with DC through the detecting switch <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The lamplight source <b>28</b> is set in the accommodating space <b>212</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b> and connected with the driving circuit <b>26</b>. On receiving DC with a normal voltage supplied by the power processing circuit <b>22</b> through the driving circuit <b>26</b>, the lamplight source <b>28</b> can be started to produce lighting. Further, the lamplight source <b>28</b> can automatically start to produce lighting when receiving DC supplied by the charging battery <b>25</b> through the detecting switch <b>23</b> and the driving circuit <b>26</b>. Furthermore, the lamplight source <b>28</b> can be turned off to extinguish lighting when receiving DC with an abnormal voltage supplied by the power processing circuit <b>22</b> through the driving circuit <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In addition, the power processing circuit <b>22</b>, the detecting switch <b>23</b>, the charging circuit <b>24</b>, the charging battery <b>25</b>, the driving circuit <b>26</b> and the micro-processor <b>27</b> of the intellectual lamp <b>20</b> can be disposed on a circuit board (not shown) to be positioned in the accommodating space <b>212</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">A second preferred embodiment of an intellectual lamp unit able to be installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch in the present invention, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, is to have the micro-processor <b>27</b> of the intellectual lamp <b>20</b> connected with a human body detector <b>291</b>, an earthquake detector <b>292</b>, a fire detector <b>293</b> and a warning indicator <b>294</b>, or optionally connected with any one of them. The human body detector <b>291</b>, the earthquake detector <b>292</b>, the fire detector <b>293</b> and the warning indicator <b>294</b> are positioned at the outer side of the lamp main body <b>21</b> and could be installed on a ceiling or a wall so that when people pass by, or when an earthquake or a fire occurs, they can quickly detect or produce induction and give out warning.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In assembling, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, firstly, select a conventional lamp socket <b>40</b> controlled by a wall switch <b>30</b> according to a user's requirement and then assemble the intellectual lamp <b>20</b> of this invention on the conventional lamp socket <b>40</b>. Next, the bypass <b>10</b> provided with a resistance <b>11</b> is connected in parallel with the wall switch <b>30</b> to finish assembly of the intellectual lamp <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Different conditions of using the intellectual lamp <b>20</b> are described as follows.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">1. Under the condition of normal power supply of the main power source:</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">(1-1). When the wall switch is turned ON or positioned at ON, the main power source <b>50</b> can supply the lamp socket <b>40</b> with AC with a normal-voltage through the wall switch <b>30</b> and then AC with the normal voltage is transmitted to the power processing circuit <b>22</b> through the lamp connector <b>213</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b> and rectified into DC. After the detecting switch <b>23</b> detects DC with the normal voltage transmitted by the power processing circuit <b>22</b>, it will form an open circuit and transmit a normal signal to the microprocessor <b>27</b>, which then commands the charging circuit <b>24</b> to charge the charging battery <b>25</b>. In addition, the power processing circuit <b>22</b> can simultaneously supply the driving circuit <b>26</b> with DC through the driving return circuit <b>26</b> for starting the lamplight source <b>28</b> to produce lighting. If the intellectual lamp <b>20</b> is provided with a fire or an earthquake detecting circuit <b>293</b> or <b>292</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the fire detector <b>293</b> or the earthquake <b>292</b> can immediately detect the occurrence of a fire or an earthquake and transmit a detected signal to the micro-processor <b>27</b>, which then commands the warning indicator <b>294</b> to give out flickering light or sounds for warning.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">(1-2). When the wall switch is turned OFF or positioned at OFF, it will form an open circuit and AC of the power source <b>50</b> will supply a reduced abnormal voltage for the lamp socket <b>40</b> through the bypass <b>10</b> connected in parallel with the wall switch <b>30</b>. Simultaneously, AC with the reduced abnormal voltage is transmitted to the power processing circuit <b>22</b> through the lamp connector <b>213</b> of the lamp main body <b>21</b> and rectified into DC to let the detecting switch <b>23</b> detect DC with a reduced voltage and form an open circuit and then transmit a normal signal to the micro-processor <b>27</b>, which then commands the charging circuit <b>24</b> to charge the charging battery <b>25</b>. In addition, the power processing circuit <b>22</b> can simultaneously supply the driving circuit <b>26</b> with DC with a reduced abnormal voltage to let the driving circuit <b>26</b> turn off the lamplight source <b>28</b> to extinguish the lighting. If the intellectual lamp <b>20</b> of this invention is provided with a fire or an earthquake detecting circuit <b>293</b> or <b>292</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the fire detector <b>293</b> or the earthquake detector <b>292</b> can work normally to carry out detection for security.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">2. Under the condition of blackout of the main power source owing to a fire or other natural disasters, such as typhoon, earthquake or twister:</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">(2-1). If the wall switch <b>30</b> is turned ON or positioned at ON and blackout occurs., the power source <b>50</b> cannot supply the lamp socket <b>40</b> with AC through the wall switch <b>30</b> or through the bypass <b>10</b>; therefore, the detecting switch <b>23</b> impossible to detect a direct current will be in a turned-on condition and transmit a blackout signal to the micro-processor <b>27</b>. Then, the micro-processor <b>27</b> will command the charging battery <b>25</b> to supply the driving circuit <b>26</b> with DC through the turned-on detecting switch <b>23</b> to let the driving circuit <b>26</b> automatically start the lamplight source <b>28</b> to give out emergency lighting at the instant of blackout, and after power recovers, they will regress to the original condition described above in the item (1-1). In addition, when the intellectual lamp <b>20</b> of this invention is provided with a fire or an earthquake detecting circuit <b>293</b> or <b>292</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the fire detector <b>293</b> or the earthquake detector <b>292</b> can be supplied with power by the charging battery <b>25</b> to work normally to carry out detection for security.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">(2-2). If the wall switch <b>30</b> is turned OFF or positioned at OFF and blackout occurs, the power source <b>50</b> is unable to supply the lamp socket <b>40</b> with AC; therefore, the detecting switch <b>23</b> cannot detect DC and becomes turned on, transmitting a blackout signal to the micro-processor <b>7</b>. Then, the microprocessor <b>27</b> will command the charging battery <b>25</b> to supply the driving circuit <b>26</b> with DC through the detecting switch <b>23</b> and synchronously the driving circuit <b>26</b> will automatically start the lamplight source <b>28</b> to give out emergency lighting at the instant of blackout. Additionally, when the power of the charging battery <b>25</b> is used up, the charging battery <b>25</b> can carry out charging automatically through the bypass <b>10</b> of the wall switch <b>30</b> when power recovers, thus enabling the charging battery <b>25</b> to always maintain sufficient power. If the intellectual lamp <b>20</b> of this invention is provided with a fire or an earthquake circuit <b>293</b> or <b>292</b>, the fire detector <b>293</b> or the earthquake detector <b>292</b> will be supplied with power by the charging battery <b>25</b> to carry out detecting work normally for security.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">As can be understood from the above description, the intellectual lamp <b>20</b> of this invention has the following advantages.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">1. The intellectual lamp <b>20</b> can be directly installed on a conventional lamp socket <b>40</b> controlled by the wall switch <b>30</b>; therefore, it is needless to dispose new circuit or alter the original circuit, only necessary to have the bypass <b>10</b> with the resistance <b>11</b> or the diode <b>12</b> connected in parallel with the wall switch <b>30</b>, convenient and quick in assembly.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">2. The intellectual lamp <b>20</b> can be used for lighting at ordinary times and in emergency, so it has more functions and is more useful than a conventional lamp or an emergency lamp, able to be installed on a conventional lamp socket <b>40</b> for use at any place where a wall switch <b>30</b> is provided for controlling the conventional lamp socket <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">3. The intellectual lamp <b>20</b> can be optionally provided with a human body detector <b>291</b>, an earthquake detector <b>292</b>, a fire detector <b>293</b> and/or a warning indicator <b>294</b> for carrying out human body induction or disasters detection and giving out warning, able to insure security of the environment or people around and greatly elevate the additional value of products.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">While the preferred embodiments of the invention have been described above, it will be recognized and understood that various modifications may be made therein and the appended claims are intended to cover all such modifications that may fall within the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An intellectual lamp unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch, said intellectual lamp unit comprising:
<claim-text>a bypass connected in parallel with a wall switch, said bypass provided with an electronic element, said electronic element functioning to convert AC passing therethrough into AC with an abnormal voltage to be transmitted to a lamp socket, a lamp main body formed with a transparent shell, said shell of said lamp main body having its interior formed with an accommodating space connected with a lamp connector, said lamp connector threadably assembled on and electrically connected with a conventional lamp socket, said lamp connector receiving AC with a normal voltage supplied through said wall switch and said lamp socket, said lamp connector also receiving AC with an abnormal voltage supplied through said bypass and said lamp socket;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power processing circuit installed in said accommodating space of said lamp main body, said power processing circuit connected with said lamp main body, said power processing circuit receiving AC with a normal voltage or an abnormal voltage supplied by said lamp connector, said power processing circuit synchronously rectifying AC with a normal voltage or an abnormal voltage DC with a normal voltage or an abnormal-voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detecting switch disposed in said accommodating space of said lamp main body, said detecting switch connected with said power processing circuit, said detecting switch functioning to detect DC supplied by said power processing circuit, said detecting switch transmitting outward a normal signal and forming an open circuit when said detecting switch detects DC to have a normal voltage or an abnormal voltage, said detecting switch transmitting outward a blackout signal and becoming turned on when said detecting switch detects the voltage value of DC to be zero;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a charging circuit set in said accommodating space of said lamp main body, said charging circuit connected with said power processing circuit, said charging circuit receiving DC supplied by said power processing circuit, said charging circuit supplying DC needed for charging;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a charging battery assembled in said accommodating space of said lamp main body, said charging battery connected with said charging circuit, said charging battery receiving DC supplied by said charging circuit to carry out charging, said charging battery also connected with said detecting switch, said charging battery supplied with DC through said detecting switch when said detecting switch is turned on;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a driving circuit positioned in said accommodating space of said lamp main body, said driving circuit connected with said power processing circuit and said detecting switch so that said driving circuit may receive DC with a normal voltage or an abnormal voltage supplied by said power processing circuit or supplied by said charging battery through said detecting switch;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a micro-processor connected with said charging circuit and said charging battery as well as said detecting switch, said micro-processor commanding said charging circuit to charge said charging battery when said micro-processor receives a normal signal transmitted by said detecting switch, said micro-processor commanding said charging battery to supply said driving circuit with DC through said detecting switch when said micro-processor receives a blackout signal transmitted by said detecting switch; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lamplight source located in said accommodating space of said lamp main boy, said lamplight source connected with said driving circuit, said lamplight source started to produce lighting when said lamplight source receives DC with a normal voltage supplied by said power processing circuit through said driving circuit, said lamplight source started automatically to produce lighting when said lamplight source receives DC supplied by said charging battery through said detecting switch and said driving circuit, said lamplight source turned off to extinguish lighting when said lamplight source receives DC with an abnormal voltage supplied by said power processing circuit through said driving circuit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The intellectual lamp bulb unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said lamplight source is composed of at least one LED lamp.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The intellectual lamp unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein when said wall switch is turned OFF, said lamp socket will receive AC with a reduced voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The intellectual lamp bulb unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein when said wall switch is turned OFF, said lamp socket will receive AC with a phase difference.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The intellectual lamp bulb unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said electronic element is a resistance for cutting down voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The intellectual lamp bulb unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said electronic element is a diode for producing phase difference.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The intellectual lamp bulb unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said micro-processor is connected with a human body detector and a warning indicator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The intellectual lamp bulb unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said microprocessor is connected with an earthquake detector and a warning indicator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The intellectual lamp bulb unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said microprocessor is connected with a fire detector and a warning indicator.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The intellectual lamp bulb unit installed on a conventional lamp socket controlled by a wall switch as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said microprocessor is connected with a human body detector, an earthquake detector, a fire detector and a warning indicator.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
