<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298624-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298624</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10417111</doc-number>
<date>20030417</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>05</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361727</main-classification>
<further-classification>361683</further-classification>
<further-classification>361724</further-classification>
<further-classification>361816</further-classification>
<further-classification>361818</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Data storage device chassis, case and clamp mechanism</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4813194</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dobyns et al.</name>
<date>19890300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 5230913</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5142447</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cooke et al.</name>
<date>19920800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361685</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5483423</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lewis et al.</name>
<date>19960100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361816</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6466449</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Sheen et al.</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361752</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>14</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361683</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361685</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361686</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361816</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361818</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361724-727</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174 35 R</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>174 35 G</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>349 59</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3122231</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3122232</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3123321</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>312333</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248633</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248634</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248636</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248638</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248618</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60383126</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20020528</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20030222550</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20031204</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Boswell</last-name>
<first-name>Graham P</first-name>
<address>
<city>Southampton</city>
<country>GB</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>GB</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>GB</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Scicluna</last-name>
<first-name>Mark</first-name>
<address>
<city>Long Sutton</city>
<country>GB</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>GB</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>GB</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Pillsbury Winthrop Shaw Pittman LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Xyratex Technology Limited</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Hampshire</city>
<country>GB</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Vortman</last-name>
<first-name>Anatoly</first-name>
<department>2835</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Edwards</last-name>
<first-name>Anthony Q.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A data storage device chassis for housing a plurality of data storage devices has a plurality of walls at least some of which have at least one guide strip along at least part of the length of the wall to define a plurality of bays in which data storage devices (<b>18</b>) can be housed. The guide strips support respective data storage devices in the bays such that the data storage devices can be slid into and out of the bays by sliding along the guide strips. The at least some of the walls are composed of a non-metallic material such that the surface of said guide strips along which a data storage device slides is non-metallic. Each of said at least some of the walls have an electrically conductive portion passing through the wall to provide for electrical conduction between the bays thereby providing electrical shielding for data storage devices housed in the bays.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="117.69mm" wi="215.65mm" file="US07298624-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="251.54mm" wi="134.28mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298624-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="245.11mm" wi="143.51mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298624-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="256.37mm" wi="163.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298624-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="191.94mm" wi="136.23mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298624-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="254.00mm" wi="165.86mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298624-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="258.66mm" wi="188.30mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298624-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="203.12mm" wi="174.67mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298624-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="154.43mm" wi="144.61mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298624-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority to U.S. provisional application No. 60/383,126, filed May 28, 2002, the entire content of which is hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention relates generally to a data storage device chassis, a wall therefor, and a data storage device case and clamp mechanism.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Discussion of Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">As is well known, data storage devices, such as disk drive units, are used to store data. In many applications, plural data storage device are housed in a single chassis and are removable therefrom for maintenance or replacement as and when necessary. In practice, it is desirable to fit as many data storage devices in a single chassis as possible in order to save space. A typical known chassis of standard 19″ rack width and height of 3U (5¼″) may hold 12 or 15 data storage devices at most, the devices being arranged in a regular array.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A number of difficulties arise in the design of a chassis of this type, particularly when trying to accommodate a greater number of data storage devices in a standard volume as space is at a premium and thin chassis walls are therefore required.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">First, it is important to ensure that the cases of the data storage devices are held securely in the chassis and particularly in a way that minimises vibration of the data storage device. In the case of disk drive units, it is important to minimise the rotary vibrations that can arise because of the spinning disk.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">It is furthermore important to minimise any damage to the chassis or data storage device case that might arise on sliding the data storage device in and out of the chassis. Given that data storage devices are typically housed in metal cases, it is important to ensure that metal flakes or other particles do not scrape off the data storage device case or the chassis because such metallic particles can interfere with the proper operation of the data storage device in use. One known solution to this particular problem is to glue or rivet plastics strips along the metal runners of metal walls that define the bays for the data storage devices in the chassis. Practical problems with this approach include the fact that the plastics strips are often not glued or otherwise fixed in the correct place and that they may become loose and even detached after repeated sliding in and out of the data storage devices. The use of discrete plastics strips also increases the parts count and the gluing or other fixing of the plastics strips adds significantly to the labour costs.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In such a chassis, it is furthermore important to ensure that electromagnetic interference both out of and into the chassis is minimised, not only to meet legal requirements in regard to emissions but also to minimise the possibility of the operation of the data storage devices being affected by stray electromagnetic radiation entering the chassis.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">According to a first aspect of the present invention, there is provided a data storage device chassis for housing a plurality of data storage devices, the chassis having a plurality of walls, at least some of the walls having at least one guide strip along at least part of the length of the wall to define a plurality of bays in which data storage devices can be housed, said guide strips supporting respective data storage devices in the bays such that said data storage devices can be slid into and out of the bays by sliding along the guide strips, said at least some of the walls being composed of a non-metallic material such that the surface of said guide strips along which a data storage device slides is non-metallic, each of said at least some of the walls having an electrically conductive portion passing through the wall to provide for electrical conduction between the bays thereby providing electrical shielding for data storage devices housed in the bays.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The use of a non-metallic material for the wall and particularly for the guide strip or strips along which the data storage devices slide means that there is no metal-to-metal contact between the data storage device and the wall. This in turn avoids the scraping of metal, which can otherwise lead to formation of metallic particles that can affect performance of the data storage devices. This construction furthermore avoids having to glue or otherwise fix strips of plastics along the guide strips along which the data storage devices slide, thus reducing the parts count and labour costs and avoiding the problem of such plastics strips becoming detached in use. The non-metallic wall can be formed very cheaply and yet have the high stiffness required of such a wall in a data storage device chassis.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Said guide strips may project into respective bays for supporting respective data storage devices in the bays. As an alternative, the guide strips may be in the form of recesses in the respective walls.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In an embodiment, the non-metallic material of said at least some of the walls is plastics. Plastics is preferred because it can be manufactured simply at low cost and within a narrow range of dimensional tolerances. Also, through selection of the appropriate plastics material, the walls can have a very high stiffness, which is important in minimising vibration of data storage devices housed in the chassis. In a preferred embodiment, the non-metallic material of said at least some of the walls is polycarbonate.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In an embodiment, the electrically conductive portion of said at least some of the walls is metal.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In a preferred embodiment, the non-metallic material of said at least some of the walls is plastics and the electrically conductive portion of said at least some of the walls is metal, each of said walls being formed by over-moulding the metal electrically conductive portion with plastics such that the metal electrically conductive portion is held captive in the plastics part of the wall. The use of over-moulding, which will be discussed further below, allows for simple, low cost and accurate manufacture of the walls. The metal electrically conductive portion preferably has projecting ears that are engaged by the plastics part of the wall to hold the metal electrically conductive portion captive in the plastics part of the wall.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">According to a second aspect of the present invention, there is provided a wall for a data storage device chassis that houses a plurality of data storage devices, the wall having at least one guide strip along at least part of the length of the wall, the guide strip being constructed and arranged to at least partially support a respective data storage device in the data storage device chassis such that said data storage device can be slid into and out of the chassis by sliding along the guide strip, the wall being composed of a non-metallic material such that the surface of said guide strip along which a data storage device slides is non-metallic, the wall having an electrically conductive portion passing through the wall to provide for electrical conduction across the wall to enable electrical shielding for data storage devices housed in the chassis.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In an embodiment, the non-metallic material of said wall is plastics.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In an embodiment, the non-metallic material of said wall is polycarbonate.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In an embodiment, the electrically conductive portion of said wall is metal.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In a preferred embodiment, the non-metallic material of said wall is plastics and the electrically conductive portion of said wall is metal, said wall being formed by over-moulding the metal electrically conductive portion with plastics such that the metal electrically conductive portion is held captive in the plastics part of the wall.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The metal electrically conductive portion preferably has projecting ears that are engaged by the plastics part of the wall to hold the metal electrically conductive portion captive in the plastics part of the wall.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">According to a third aspect of the present invention, there is provided a method of manufacturing a wall for a data storage device chassis that houses a plurality of data storage devices, the method comprising: placing a conductive strip in a mould; introducing molten non-metallic material into the mould; and, allowing the molten non-metallic material to solidify; the conductive strip being supported in the mould such that the conductive strip is held captive by the solidified non-metallic material and passes through the non-metallic portion of the wall to provide for electrical conduction across the wall.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The conductive strip preferably has projecting ears that are engaged by the non-metallic portion of the wall to hold the conductive strip captive in the non-metallic portion of the wall.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In an embodiment, the non-metallic material of the wall is plastics.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In an embodiment, the non-metallic material of the wall is polycarbonate.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In an embodiment, the electrically conductive strip is metal.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">According to another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a data storage device chassis and a data storage device case having a clamp mechanism for clamping the data storage device case in the data storage device chassis, the clamp mechanism comprising: a lever mounted for pivotable movement about a pivot axis between an open position in which the data storage device case is unclamped and a closed position in which the data storage device case is clamped; the lever having a cam surface constructed and arranged to engage a cam surface in the data storage device chassis in the closed position; the lever cam surface having a bevel substantially parallel to the pivot axis and the chassis cam surface having a complementary bevel such that, as the lever is pivoted about the pivot axis from the open position towards the closed position, the bevels on the lever cam surface and the chassis cam surface engage to clamp the data storage device case in the data storage device chassis.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The use of bevelled cam surfaces causes the data storage device case to be drawn closely into and clamped strongly against the adjacent wall of the data storage device chassis. This gives the effect of an interference fit in the clamped position, whereas sliding in and out of the data storage device can be an easy, almost loose fit. The strong clamp load that can be applied serves to minimise vibrations that may arise during operation of the data storage device.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In a preferred embodiment, the lever cam surface is positioned at one end of the lever and the opposite end of the lever has a projecting tab that engages in a slot in the data storage device case when the data storage device case is in the clamped position.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">According to another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a data storage device case having a clamp mechanism for clamping the data storage device case in a data storage device chassis, the clamp mechanism comprising: a lever mounted for pivotable movement about a pivot axis between an open position in which the data storage device case is unclamped and a closed position in which the data storage device case is clamped; the lever having a cam surface constructed and arranged to engage a cam surface in a data storage device chassis in the closed position; the lever cam surface having a bevel substantially parallel to the pivot axis and for engagement with a complementary bevel on a said chassis cam surface such that, as the lever is pivoted about the pivot axis from the open position towards the closed position, the bevels on the lever cam surface and the chassis cam surface engage to clamp the data storage device case in the data storage device chassis.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">In a preferred embodiment, the lever cam surface is positioned at one end of the lever and the opposite end of the lever has a projecting tab that engages in a slot in a said data storage device case when the data storage device case is in the clamped position.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">According to yet another aspect of the present invention, there is provided a data storage device chassis for housing one or more data storage devices, the chassis having walls that define an aperture through which a module can be passed to be housed in the chassis, the periphery of the aperture being surrounded by an electromagnetic interference shielding gasket, the gasket having a base portion and an upstanding portion upstanding therefrom that engages a said module when a said module is housed in the chassis, the base portion of the gasket being received in a recess or recesses in the walls of the chassis to retain the gasket in position around the aperture, the recess or recesses having an opening through which the upstanding portion of the gasket projects into the periphery of the aperture.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">This arrangement means that the gasket does not have to be fixed by gluing, rivetting or the like, which reduces labour costs and helps to ensure that the gasket is correctly positioned initially and that the gasket stays in the correct position in use. In practice, the base portion of the gasket will typically be slid into the recess from an end of the recess or recesses during assembly of the chassis.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The opening of the recess or recesses preferably has a width that is substantially the same as the cross-sectional width of the upstanding portion of the gasket. This arrangement assists in making a close sealing engagement between the gasket and the module as it provides some support for the upstanding portion of the gasket.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The gasket is preferably generally T-shape in cross-section such that the base portion of the gasket is generally rectangular in cross-section and the upstanding portion of the gasket is upstanding generally centrally therefrom.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Embodiments of the present invention will now be described by way of example with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view from the front of an example of a data storage device chassis according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view from the rear of the chassis of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a side elevation of an example of a mid-wall of a data storage device chassis in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is an end elevation of the wall of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a plan view from above of the wall of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a side elevation of an electrically conductive strip of the wall of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A to 7C</figref> are partially sectioned views from above of an example of a data storage device having a clamp mechanism engaging a wall of a data storage device chassis in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention, the clamp mechanism being shown in a fully open, partially open and a clamped position respectively; and,</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a sectioned perspective view of the periphery of openings at the rear of a data storage device chassis in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Referring initially to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, a generally box-like data storage device chassis <b>10</b> has side walls <b>11</b>, a top wall <b>12</b> and a bottom wall <b>13</b>. Three vertical mid walls <b>14</b> pass from the front <b>15</b> to approximately the mid point of the chassis <b>10</b>. Each mid-wall <b>14</b> has on each side five guide strips <b>16</b> and the inner most facing surfaces of the side walls <b>11</b> have similar guide strips <b>16</b> which together in this example define a regular array of 4×4 bays <b>17</b>. Each bay <b>17</b> can receive a data storage device <b>18</b> which can be slid into and out of the base <b>17</b> through the open front <b>15</b> of the chassis <b>11</b>, the guide strips <b>16</b> providing the surface along which the cases <b>19</b> of the data storage devices <b>18</b> slide.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">A preferred arrangement for the walls <b>14</b> will now be described with particular reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 to 6</figref>. Each wall <b>14</b> is generally rectangular in shape. The main body of the wall <b>14</b> is made of a non-metallic material, preferably plastics and in one embodiment polycarbonate. The wall <b>14</b> contains a conductive strip <b>20</b>, which may be an aluminium casting. In the most preferred embodiment, the wall <b>14</b> is formed by over-moulding the conductive strip <b>20</b> with the plastics material of the body of the wall <b>14</b>. For this purpose, the conductive strip <b>20</b> has through holes <b>47</b> which can be used to mount the conductive strip <b>20</b> on pegs in a moulding tool whilst plastics material is introduced into the tool. The conductive strip <b>20</b> has plural projecting ears <b>48</b> on each side which are encapsulated by the moulded plastics material of the wall <b>14</b> in order to hold the conductive strip <b>20</b> securely in the formed wall <b>14</b>. Moreover, as can be seen particularly clearly in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the guide strips <b>16</b> overlie the conductive strip <b>20</b>, again serving to hold the conductive strip <b>20</b> securely in place.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">This arrangement for forming the wall <b>14</b>, including the selection of materials and the method of manufacture, has several distinct advantages in the context of a wall as used in a data storage device chassis <b>10</b>. In particular, in a chassis <b>10</b> for a plurality of data storage devices <b>18</b>, space is at a premium as it is always desirable to fit as many data storage devices as possible across the standard rack width of 19″. The dividing walls must therefore be thin. On the other hand, it is also desirable to construct the chassis <b>10</b> so that the chassis <b>10</b> can itself act to minimise vibration passing into and out of the data storage devices <b>18</b>. Where the data storage devices <b>18</b> are disk drives which have spinning disks, it is important to damp the rotary vibrations that can arise during operation of the disk drives. These vibration damping requirements imply that the walls <b>14</b> should have a high stiffness. Last, it is necessary that the walls <b>14</b> be formed within close tolerances given their function not only in supporting the data storage devices but also in minimising vibrations. All of these requirements are met in the preferred embodiment of the wall <b>14</b> and its method of manufacture as described above.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">In the preferred embodiment, the walls <b>14</b> each have a generally trapezoidal slot <b>21</b> in the region of the wall <b>14</b> at the front of each bay <b>17</b>. Each of these trapezoidal slots <b>21</b> has a bevelled leading edge <b>22</b>. Moreover, a short keying rib <b>23</b> is provided on each side of the wall <b>14</b> at the portion at the rear of each bay <b>17</b>. The chassis <b>10</b> has similar trapezoidal slots <b>24</b> and short keying ribs <b>25</b> for the left most and right most bays. The function of these features will be discussed further below.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7A to 7C</figref>, each data storage device <b>18</b> is generally rectangular in plan and fits snugly in a respective bay <b>17</b> in the chassis <b>10</b>. The case <b>19</b> contains the actual storage device such as a hard disk, read/write heads, etc. (not shown). The data storage device <b>14</b> has a clamp mechanism <b>30</b> which includes an operating lever <b>31</b> which is pivotable about a pivot <b>32</b> which is perpendicular to the direction of insertion of the data storage device <b>18</b> and parallel to the bevelled edge <b>22</b> of the trapezoidal slots <b>21</b>,<b>24</b>. The operating lever <b>31</b> has a cam surface having a corresponding bevel <b>33</b> on a leading edge. The lever <b>31</b> furthermore has a projecting stop <b>34</b> close to the bevel <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">As a data storage device <b>18</b> is slid into a bay <b>17</b> of the chassis <b>10</b>, the case <b>19</b>, which is typically metal, slides along the guide strips <b>16</b> that define the bay <b>17</b>. Because the guide strips <b>16</b> are provided by the non-metallic and preferably plastics wall <b>14</b>, there is no sliding of metal on metal. This serves practically to reduce to zero the possibility of metal flakes or particles scraping off any of the components when the data storage device <b>18</b> is moved into and out of position in the chassis <b>10</b>, thereby reducing the risk of damage or other interference to the electronic components of the chassis <b>10</b> and the data storage devices <b>18</b>. Moreover, avoiding the metal-on-metal contact of typical known arrangements means that the action of sliding the data storage devices <b>18</b> in and out has a much better “feel” for the user or operator.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">The case <b>19</b> of the data storage device has short elongate keying recesses <b>26</b> which correspond to and receive the respective keying ribs <b>23</b>,<b>25</b> of the walls <b>14</b> or chassis <b>10</b> as the data storage device <b>18</b> moves towards its fully home position in the bay <b>17</b>. The ribs <b>23</b>,<b>25</b> are a loose fit in the recesses <b>26</b> so that they do not interfere with engagement of the data and power connector at the back of the data storage device <b>18</b> with the data and power connector provided in the chassis <b>10</b> at the rear of each bay <b>17</b>. These keying ribs <b>23</b>,<b>25</b> and recesses <b>26</b> help to ensure that the data storage device <b>18</b> is inserted the right way up and, indeed, help to ensure that the correct module is being inserted into the chassis <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">As can be seen in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7A</figref>, as the data storage device <b>18</b> moves towards its fully home position, the stop <b>34</b> of the lever <b>31</b> abuts the leading edge of the wall <b>14</b> (or chassis wall <b>11</b> as the case may be). At that point, the lever <b>31</b> is then pivoted, this action causing the bevel <b>33</b> of the lever cam surface to engage the bevel <b>22</b> in the trapezoidal slot <b>21</b>,<b>24</b> in the wall <b>14</b> or chassis <b>10</b> as the case may be. This can be seen most clearly in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7B</figref>. Further pivoting of the lever <b>31</b> and the resultant action of the bevelled surfaces <b>33</b>,<b>22</b> against each other clamps the case <b>19</b> of the data storage device <b>18</b> securely against the wall <b>14</b>,<b>11</b> on that side. The end of the lever <b>31</b> opposite the cam surface <b>33</b> has a projecting tab <b>35</b> on the end of a resilient U-shape formation <b>36</b> which engages in a slot <b>37</b> in the case <b>19</b> when the data storage device <b>18</b> is in the fully clamped position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7C</figref>. This provides a lock against accidental opening of the clamp mechanism <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In the fully clamped position, the metal walls of the data storage device case <b>19</b> engage the conductive strips <b>20</b> of the mid walls <b>14</b> and also the metal side walls <b>11</b> of the chassis <b>11</b>, optionally through metal leaf springs mounted on the case <b>19</b>. This metal-to-metal contact provides an earth path between all of the data storage devices <b>18</b> in the bays <b>17</b> of the chassis <b>10</b>. This serves to reduce electromagnetic interference either entering or leaving the chassis <b>10</b>. Thus, despite the non-metallic material used for the walls <b>14</b>, earthing conduct can be made through the walls <b>14</b> in a simple manner and is effected whenever the data storage device <b>18</b> is in its clamped position in a bay <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In a manner known per se, the pivot <b>32</b> may travel slightly in a direction along the length of the case <b>19</b> when the data storage device <b>18</b> is moved into its fully home position. Similarly, in a manner known per se, a torsion spring may be mounted around the pivot <b>32</b> which winds up to its full force as the lever <b>31</b> is moved to its home position. These effects act together to provide a load on the case <b>19</b> towards the rear of the chassis <b>10</b>, which serves to ensure that the power and data connections between the data storage device <b>18</b> and the chassis components at the rear of the data storage device <b>18</b> are strongly made.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The combined action of the bevelled cam surface <b>33</b> of the lever <b>31</b> engaging the bevelled cam surfaces <b>22</b> of the trapezoidal slot <b>21</b>,<b>24</b>, the engagement of the cam surface <b>33</b> in the trapezoidal slot <b>21</b>,<b>24</b> itself, and the engagement of the data and power connector on the data storage device <b>18</b> with the connector on the motherboard at the rear of the bay <b>17</b>, provides for a secure 3-point mounting of the case <b>19</b> in the bay <b>17</b>, with the case <b>19</b> being locked in three perpendicular axes. This results in extremely efficient damping of vibrations and provides strong resistance against shock.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, there is shown a portion around the periphery of apertures <b>40</b> at the rear of the chassis <b>10</b>. These apertures <b>40</b> can receive a module, such as a power supply and cooling fans, etc., for data storage devices <b>18</b> located in the chassis <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">It is desirable in practice to provide for electromagnetic shielding around the periphery of these openings, both to prevent leakage out and leakage in of electromagnetic interference. Conventionally, such shielding has been provided by strips of short metallic fingers which are glued around the periphery of the aperture <b>40</b>. The gluing of such fingers increases labour costs and it is also a fact that such fingers or similar may well not be glued in the correct place in the first instance and that they can become detached during use.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Accordingly, in the preferred embodiment, a gasket <b>41</b> of generally T-shape cross section is employed. The gasket <b>41</b> has a plastics base <b>42</b> with an upstanding urethane foam portion <b>43</b>, which are both entirely covered by a woven fabric covering <b>44</b> which is either made of metallic material or which is metallised. A preferred material for the metal or metallised coating is nickel or silver. A suitable gasket <b>41</b> is manufactured by Schlegel Systems Inc. The region of the chassis <b>10</b> around the periphery of the apertures <b>40</b> has a recess <b>45</b> of rectangular cross section which can receive the base portion of the gasket <b>41</b>, the recess <b>45</b> having an opening <b>46</b> through the chassis wall through which the upstanding portion of the gasket <b>41</b> projects into the aperture <b>40</b> in the chassis <b>10</b>. The depth of the recess <b>45</b> is selected so that the gasket <b>41</b> is compressed somewhat when a module is loaded in the aperture <b>40</b>. The gasket <b>41</b> can be introduced into the recess <b>45</b> during assembly of the chassis <b>11</b> by sliding the gasket <b>41</b> in from one open end of the recess <b>45</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Not only does the preferred gasket <b>41</b> provide for good electromagnetic shielding, it also provides a good air seal around the module in the aperture <b>40</b>. This is of particular advantage in a data storage device chassis <b>10</b> given that temperature control of the data storage devices <b>18</b> is provided by special cooling fans under specific software control and it is therefore desirable to prevent air leaking into or out of the chassis <b>10</b> other than through the air flow paths occupied by the cooling fans.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Embodiments of the present invention have been described with particular reference to the examples illustrated. However, it will be appreciated that variations and modifications may be made to the examples described within the scope of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A data storage device chassis for housing a plurality of data storage devices each containing a disk drive, the chassis having a plurality of walls, at least some of the walls having at least one guide strip along at least part of the length of the wall to define a plurality of bays in which data storage devices can be housed, said guide strips supporting respective data storage devices in the bays such that said data storage devices can be slid into and out of the bays by sliding along the guide strips, said at least some of the walls being composite walls that are composed of a non-metallic material such that the surface of said guide strips along which a data storage device slides is non-metallic and such that the parts of the walls that are in sliding contact with a data storage device are non-metallic, and a metal electrically conductive portion passing through the wall to provide for electrical conduction between the bays thereby providing electrical shielding for data storage devices housed in the bays and to provide for additional stiffness to the walls to damp rotary vibrations arising during operation of said disk drives when said data storage devices are housed in the bays, the metal electrically conductive portion being held captive in the wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A data storage device chassis according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the non-metallic material of said at least some of the walls is plastics.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A data storage device chassis according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the non-metallic material of said at least some of the walls is polycarbonate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A data storage device chassis according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the non-metallic material of said at least some of the walls is plastics, each of said walls being formed by over-moulding the metal electrically conductive portion with plastics such that the metal electrically conductive portion is held captive in the plastics part of the wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A data storage device chassis according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the metal electrically conductive portion has projecting ears that are engaged by the plastics part of the wall to hold the metal electrically conductive portion captive in the plastics part of the wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A composite wall for a data storage device chassis that houses a plurality of data storage devices each containing a disk drive, the wall having at least one guide strip along at least part of the length of the wall, the guide strip being constructed and arranged to at least partially support a respective data storage device in the data storage device chassis such that said data storage device can be slid into and out of the chassis by sliding along the guide strip, the wall composite being composed of a non-metallic material such that the surface of said guide strip along which a data storage device slides is non-metallic and such that the parts of the wall that are in sliding contact with a data storage device are non-metallic, and having a metal electrically conductive portion passing through the wall to provide for electrical conduction across the wall to enable electrical shielding for data storage devices housed in the chassis and to provide for additional stiffness to the wall to damp rotary vibrations arising during operation of said disk drives when said data storage devices are housed in the bays, the metal electrically conductive portion being held captive in the wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A wall according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the non-metallic material of said wall is plastics.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A wall according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the non-metallic material of said wall is polycarbonate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A wall according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the non-metallic material of said wall is plastics, said wall being formed by over-moulding the metal electrically conductive portion with plastics such that the metal electrically conductive portion is held captive in the plastics part of the wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A wall according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the metal electrically conductive portion has projecting ears that are engaged by the plastics part of the wall to hold the metal electrically conductive portion captive in the plastics part of the wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method of manufacturing a composite wall for a data storage device chassis that houses a plurality of data storage devices each containing a disk drive which can be slid into and out of said data storage device chassis, the method comprising:
<claim-text>placing a metal conductive strip in a mould;</claim-text>
<claim-text>introducing molten non-metallic material into the mould; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>allowing the molten non-metallic material to solidify to form a non-metallic wall having at least one non-metallic guide strip along at least part of its length for slidably supporting thereon in use a data storage device and such that the parts of the wall that are in sliding contact with a data storage device are non-metallic;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the metal conductive strip being supported in the mould such that the metal conductive strip is held captive by the solidified non-metallic material and passes through the non-metallic portion of the wall to provide for electrical conduction across the wall and to provide for additional stiffness to the wall to damp rotary vibrations arising during operation of said disk drives when said data storage devices are housed in the bays.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the conductive strip has projecting ears that are engaged by the non-metallic portion of the wall to hold the conductive strip captive in the non-metallic portion of the wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the non-metallic material of the wall is plastics.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the non-metallic material of the wall is polycarbonate.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
