<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297030-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297030</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11419526</doc-number>
<date>20060522</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>24</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439676</main-classification>
<further-classification>439638</further-classification>
<further-classification>439571</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Telecommunication cable adapter</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4188505</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>O'Connor</name>
<date>19800200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439676</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>5</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439676</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439638</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439527</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439571-572</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070093087</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070426</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chang</last-name>
<first-name>Hsi-Fan</first-name>
<address>
<street>8F-6, No. 18, Lane 609, Sec., 5, Chung Shin Road</street>
<city>Sanchung, Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Shia</last-name>
<first-name>Banger</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nasri</last-name>
<first-name>Javaid H.</first-name>
<department>2839</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A communication adapter for wall-mounting panel to provide better fastness, easy structure, lower production costs and powerful utility includes a casing comprised of an upper lid and a lower lid, a circuit board in the casing, plug and socket connecting to the circuit board, and locking hole on the lower lid to secure the upper lid to the lower lid with a locking pin; a locking tongue being disposed to the lower lid and a hole on the upper lid to allow pulling the locking tongue.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="140.21mm" wi="146.98mm" file="US07297030-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="177.04mm" wi="148.59mm" file="US07297030-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="160.44mm" wi="132.25mm" file="US07297030-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="174.75mm" wi="147.15mm" file="US07297030-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="252.05mm" wi="133.60mm" file="US07297030-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">(a) Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention is related to a communication adapter, and more particularly, to one that can be secured to a wall-mounting panel.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">(b) Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Computer and telephone have been comprehensively applied in home and office thanks to ever-advancing electronic technology in recent years. Therefore, communication adapters generally available in the market give two interfacial functions; wherein, communication signals delivered through communication cable are respectively transmitted into the computer and telephone after passing their corresponding interfaces at the part of filtration. Whereas some subscribers tend to have their telephone sets on the wall, a wall-mounting communication panel as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> of the accompanying drawings is provided. To improve its fastness to the wall, the panel is disposed with soft rubber pad on the side against the wall. However, the application of gel involves higher cost and poor fastness.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The primary purpose of the present invention is to provide an improved communication adapter in simple structure, lower production cost, and strong utility to correct the flaws found with the prior art</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">To achieve the purpose, the present invention includes a casing comprised of an upper lid and a lower lid, a circuit board contained in the casing, plug and socket connecting to the circuit board, and a locking hole to secure a locking pin is disposed on the lower lid. One or a plurality of locking tongue is disposed on the lower lid to further secure the locking pin into the locking hole, and a hole to pull the locking tongue is disposed on the upper lid to facilitate assembly or disassembly process of the communication adapter.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Two or multiple sockets are disposed on the surface of the casing, and two sockets, one for telephone communication and another for computer, are generally provided. The locking tongue is comprised of a pull part, a locking part to secure the locking pin, and a curved part connecting to the lower lid. The displacement of the locking pin is restricted on the locking pin is inserted into the locking hole to achieve the purpose of fastness. To disassembly, the pull part is activated to drive the locking part to create a certain elastic displacement so to easily remove the locking pin from the locking hole. The locking tongue and the lower lid are made in an integrated part of plastic or hardware given with certain elasticity. Two or multiple locking holes are disposed on the lower lid to be secured to a wall-mounting unit.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic view showing a construction of a communication adapter of the prior art.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view showing a construction of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is an exploded view showing the construction of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic view showing a local part taken from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a magnified view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> for a communication adapter of the prior art. Wherein, two pieces of soft rubber <b>9</b> are stick to the back of the communication adapter. Once both locking pins <b>7</b> are pushed into their respectively holes <b>5</b>, the elastic return force of the soft rubber <b>9</b> will secure both of the adapter and the locking pins <b>7</b> in place to hold firm the adapter to the wall. However, when the adapter is subject to a relatively greater upward force, the inherited property of the soft rubber <b>9</b> may disengage it from the locking pins <b>7</b>. Furthermore, the fastness of the adapter will be compromised by fatigue of the elasticity of the soft rubber <b>9</b> after a longer time of use.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, two sockets <b>4</b> are provided to a preferred embodiment of the present invention, a hole <b>8</b> to pull a locking tongue <b>6</b> is disposed to an upper lid <b>1</b> to allow the user to pull a locking tongue <b>6</b> for easy disassembly of the adapter.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Now referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref>, <b>4</b>, and <b>5</b>, the communication adapter includes a casing comprised of the upper lid <b>1</b> and a lower lid <b>2</b>, a circuit board <b>3</b> contained in the casing, two plugs <b>41</b> and two sockets <b>4</b> connecting to the circuit board <b>3</b>, and two locking holes <b>5</b> to secure the upper lid <b>1</b> to the lower lid <b>2</b> with two locking pins <b>7</b>. The locking tongue <b>6</b> is disposed to the lower lid <b>2</b> to further firmly secure the locking pin <b>7</b> to the locking hole <b>5</b>; and a hole <b>8</b> allowing to pull the locking pin is disposed on the upper lid <b>1</b> to facilitate disassemble the adapter.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Two sockets <b>4</b> provided on the surface of the casing are respectively connecting to a telephone set and a computer. The locking tongue <b>6</b> is comprised of a pull part <b>61</b>, a locking part <b>62</b> to secure the locking pin <b>7</b>, and a curved part <b>63</b> connecting to the lower lid <b>2</b>. Once the locking pin <b>7</b> is driven into the locking hole <b>5</b>, the movement of the locking pin <b>7</b> is restricted by the locking part <b>62</b> of the locking tongue <b>6</b> to achieve better fastness results. To disassemble, the pull part <b>61</b> is pulled to drive the locking part <b>61</b> for creating a certain amount of elastic displacement, thus to easily remove the locking pin <b>7</b> out of the locking hole <b>5</b>. Both of the locking tongue <b>6</b> and the lower lid <b>2</b> are made in an integrated part of a material giving certain elasticity such as plastic or hardware. Two locking holes are disposed on the lower lid <b>2</b> to secure the adapter to a wall-mounting panel.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The prevent invention provides an improved structure of a communication adapter, and the application for a utility patent is duly filed accordingly. However, it is to be noted that the preferred embodiments disclosed in the specification and the accompanying drawings are not limiting the present invention; and that any construction, installation, or characteristics that is same or similar to that of the present invention should fall within the scope of the purposes and claims of the present invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A telecommunication cable adapter includes a casing comprised of an upper lid and a lower lid, a circuit board contained in the casing, a plug and a socket connecting to the circuit board, a locking hole disposed on the lower lid to be inserted with a locking pin, one or a plurality of locking tongue being provided to the lower lid, and a hole to pull the locking tongue being provided on the upper lid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The telecommunication cable adapter of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein two or multiple sockets are provided on the surface of the casing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The telecommunication cable adapter of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the locking tongue is comprised of a pull part, a locking part to secure the locking pin, and a curved part connecting to the lower lid.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The telecommunication cable adapter of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein both of the locking tongue and the lower lid are made in an integrated part.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The telecommunication cable adapter of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein two or multiple locking holes are disposed on the upper lid.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
