<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299298-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299298</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10997237</doc-number>
<date>20041124</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<disclaimer>
<text>This patent is subject to a terminal disclaimer.</text>
</disclaimer>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>15</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709245</main-classification>
<further-classification>709223</further-classification>
<further-classification>709203</further-classification>
<further-classification>714 46</further-classification>
<further-classification>7155011</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e51">Web address converter for dynamic web pages</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5929849</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kikinis</name>
<date>19990700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>725113</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6018748</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Smith</name>
<date>20000100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6161127</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cezar et al.</name>
<date>20001200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6226642</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Beranek et al.</name>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>707 10</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6434614</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Blumenau</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>709224</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6442714</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Griffin et al.</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>714 46</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6453306</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Quelene</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6470383</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Leshem et al.</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6701307</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Himmelstein et al.</name>
<date>20040300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>707  3</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6895430</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Schneider</name>
<date>20050500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6980311</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Currans et al.</name>
<date>20051200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>358  115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<nplcit num="00012">
<othercit>URL Replacer, Pstruh.cz, pub date Oct. 13, 1999.</othercit>
</nplcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>30</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709229</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709224</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709237</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709245</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709203</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>709223</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>707 46</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>707  3</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>707 10</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>714 46</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>7155011</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>5</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<continuation>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>09560703</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20000427</date>
</document-id>
<parent-status>PENDING</parent-status>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10997237</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</continuation>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050080908</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050414</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Allen</last-name>
<first-name>Joshua</first-name>
<address>
<city>Kirkland</city>
<state>WA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ranck</last-name>
<first-name>Jeffrey L.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Sammamish</city>
<state>WA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Lee &amp; Hayes, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Microsoft Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Redmond</city>
<state>WA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Vaughn</last-name>
<first-name>William</first-name>
<department>2144</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Thanh (Tammy)</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">Herein is described an implementation of a Web address converter, which helps dynamic Web sites get the attention of spiders of Internet search engines. With the Web address converter, requests from Web browsers using static addresses access corresponding dynamic Web pages and requests from search engines generate an instance of a Web page having links with static addresses pointing to corresponding dynamic Web pages. The Web address converter performs either or both Dynamic-to-Static (D-to-S) address conversion and Static-to-Dynamic (S-to-D) address conversion. D-to-S address conversion is done when generating a spider-friendly main page for a spider of a search engine to crawl. S-to-D address conversion is used when a browser uses a static address to access a corresponding dynamic Web page. The static address that the browser uses was originally created when the spider-friendly main page was generated.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="222.25mm" wi="165.86mm" file="US07299298-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="223.35mm" wi="166.29mm" file="US07299298-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="243.59mm" wi="179.24mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299298-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="223.27mm" wi="177.97mm" file="US07299298-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="206.67mm" wi="116.16mm" file="US07299298-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="246.46mm" wi="191.43mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299298-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is a continuation of and claims priority to U.S. patent application Ser. No. 09/560,703, filed Apr. 27, 2000, the disclosure of which is incorporated by reference herein.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to accessing dynamic World Wide Web (“Web”) pages on a Web server by converting Universal Resource Locator (URL) addresses from one type to another.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">There are more than a billion documents available on the World Wide Web (“Web”) over the Internet and this number continues to rapidly increase. These documents (“Web pages”) are stored as files on Web servers. Each of these Web pages has a unique Web address. These address are also called Uniform Resource Locators (URLs) or Universal Resource Locators (URLs). URLs are more fully explained in RFC 1738 “Uniform Resource Locators (URL) Berners-Lee, Masinter &amp; McCahill.”</p>
<p id="h-0004" num="0000">Static Web Pages and Static Addressing</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">An Internet device, such as a computer using a Web browser, typically accesses a specific Web page by providing its unique Web address (e.g., a URL). That Web page is a static file stored on a Web server. The file is simply copied without change to the requesting Internet device. Every device accessing the static file sees the same results. The stored file remains unchanged until an authorized user actively modifies the file. These types of Web pages are typically called “static.” A typical URL for a static Web page looks like this:</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">domain.name.com/pagename.htm</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">This URL may be preceded by http://, which is the value of the scheme field and identifies the protocol scheme being used to transmit over the Internet. For the Web, the protocol scheme typically is HyperText Transfer Protocol (HTTP). The “domain.name.com” is the value of the hostname field and it identifies the domain (or the Web server) that hosts the Web page addressed by the static URL. The actual format of this field depends upon the domain name conventions observed. Typically, the format includes a domain name and an extension (e.g., microsoft.com).</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The “pagename” is the value of the path field and/or the file-name field. It may include a path to the specific Web page. It includes the file name of the specific Web page. The “.htm” is the value of the file-extension field and it identifies the format of the file. In this example, the format of the static file is the most common format for a Web page: HyperText Markup Language (HTML).</p>
<p id="h-0005" num="0000">Dynamic Web Pages and Dynamic Addressing</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The opposite of a static Web page is a “dynamic” Web page. A dynamic Web page is one that is created the moment the page is accessed and it is usually created based upon data in a database. Unlike a static Web page, a dynamic Web page that a viewer sees is not stored intact on a Web server. Instead, a dynamic Web page is generated anew each time it is accessed.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">A dynamic Web page is generated based upon a stored file containing instructions and an associated database. Therefore, each instance of a generated dynamic Web page may be different from a previously generated page using the same address. There are many different implementations of dynamic Web pages. The implementation differs from each other in the set of instructions used in the stored file on the Web server and the type of database accessed. Examples of such implementations include Active Server Pages (ASP) by the Microsoft Corporation and “JavaBeans” Activation Framework (JAF).</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A typical URL for a dynamic Web page may look like this: domain.name.com/pagename.asp?parm1=val1&amp;parm2=val2</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">This example uses an ASP implementation. The hostname, path, and filename fields are the same as those fields in the static URL. However, there are fields in a dynamic address that are different from fields in a static address. Note that a protocol scheme of “http://” may also precede this dynamic-Web-page URL.
<br/>
This example uses an ASP implementation. The protocol scheme, hostname, path, and filename fields are the same as those fields in the static URL. However, there are fields in a dynamic address that are different from fields in a static address.
</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The extension “.asp” is a value of a file-extension field and identifies the format of the dynamic-page-generation instructions. The extension “.asp” indicates that the page is formatted as an Active Server Page (ASP). The “?” symbol is a signal that the URL points to a dynamic page and it separates the portion of the dynamic URL referring to a specific file and the portion of the URL containing parameters.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The “parm1=” and “parm2=” elements identify the names of categorized parameter. The values of these parameters are used to generate the dynamic Web page. “val1” and “val2” are the values of the parameters. The values are typically used to access items in a database. A parameter consists of a parameter name and its associated value. There can be a series of many parameters. The “&amp;” symbol separates each parameter for the other parameters.</p>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">Web Search Engines and Spiders</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">No central bibliographic authority exists to catalog the information found on the tens of millions of Web sites on the Internet. Generally, two basic approaches are available for finding the proverbial needle in this immense Web haystack: a subject directory or a search engine.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Subject directories, such as “Snap” and “MSN”, catalog Web pages and organize them by subject. Each Web page is manually (or automatically) analyzed and categorized. Users can browse through the various categories and subcategories in the subject directories to find a Web site on a particular topic. Typically, Web pages are categorized and added to the directory by professional Web searchers or by user submissions.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">A search engine provides a searchable database of indexed keywords. A search engine examines Web pages for specified keywords and returns a list of the Web pages where the keywords were found. Although search engines are general class of programs, the term is often used to specifically describe systems like “Alta Vista” and “Excite” that enable users to search for Web pages on the Web.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">A search engine includes two main parts: index searcher and index generator. An index searcher includes a database of indexing keywords of Web pages and logic for searching that database. An index generator includes a “spider” for gathering Web pages and an “indexer” for generating an index into those pages.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Typically, a search engine works by sending out the spider to fetch as many pages as possible. The indexer then reads these pages and creates an index based on the words contained in each page. Each search engine typically uses a proprietary algorithm to create its indices such that, ideally, only meaningful results are returned for each query.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Spiders are sometimes referred to as “Web-spiders”, “robots”, “Web wanderers”, “crawlers”, “Web-crawler”, “ants”, or “worms.” These alternative names refer to programs that have the same basic functionality to visit Web sites by requesting documents from them.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A spider will “crawl” a Web page by following links found on the page. Normal Web browsers (e.g., “Internet Explorer”) are not spiders, because they are operated by humans, and don't automatically retrieve referenced documents.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Provided with a page by a spider, an indexer parses the document and inserts selected keywords into the database with references back to the original location of the source page. How this is accomplished depends on the indexer. Some indexers index the titles of the Web pages or the first few paragraphs. Some parse the entire contents and index all words. Some parse the meta-tag or other special hidden tags.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Meta-tags are special HTML tags that provide information about a Web page. Unlike normal HTML tags, meta-tags do not affect how the page is displayed. Instead, they provide information such as who created the page, how often it is updated, what the page is about, and which keywords represent the page's content. Many search engines use this information when building their indices.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">When visiting a Web site, most spiders will check a file called the “robots.txt” file. This file informs the spider whether the spider is authorized to search the site and if so authorized, which pages on the site to retrieve.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Single-destination Web sites called “portals” are often a combination of a “subject directory” and a “search engine.” These portals include a search engine (with its spider and indexer) or are closely associated with a third-party search engine. These portals often include an organized and customized subject directory.</p>
<p id="h-0007" num="0000">The Invisible Web</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The Invisible Web is made up of information stored in Web databases. Unlike pages on the visible Web, information in databases is generally inaccessible to the spiders to compile search engines.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Search engines typically index the Web by visiting Web pages and indexing their content. In particular, the spiders use the links found on pages to find new Web pages. The links include static URLs.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Most spiders tend to ignore the content of a dynamic Web address and thus, the contents of the referenced dynamic Web page. These dynamic Web pages are often ignored because the format of their dynamic URL is different from the URL format of a static Web page. Spiders are often specifically programmed to ignore dynamic addresses because of the complexity of navigating through dynamic pages.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The information found in the databases of dynamic Web sites is not indexed by search engines. Therefore, these dynamic Web sites are not found by those using search engines to search the Web. This huge, unmapped region of the Internet is called the “Invisible Web.”</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">E-commerce sites with on-line shopping catalogs typically use dynamic Web pages because their databased inventory is changing constantly. These sites wish to be indexed by search engines because to help bring users to their site.</p>
<p id="h-0008" num="0000">Conventional Solution</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">To allow search engines to index their sites, dynamic sites (such as e-commerce sites with inventory) periodically generate “snapshots” of their dynamic Web pages. These snapshots are static Web pages generated from corresponding dynamic Web pages, which are generated at a moment in time.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">However, there are several significant drawbacks to the “snapshot” approach. In a short period of time, the snapshots no longer represent the current inventory. Periodically generating the snapshots consumes processing and storage resources.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">Although the snapshot approach does allow a search engine to index the dynamic Web site, the URLs stored by the search engine are static URLs. Therefore, the search engine ultimately directs a user to the snapshot pages rather than to the preferable dynamic pages. Dynamic sites would prefer users to use their dynamic page to take full advantage of the dynamic nature of the site. If the users are using the snapshot pages, then the information seen by the user may not be accurate.</p>
<heading id="h-0009" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Herein is described an implementation of a Web address converter, which helps dynamic Web sites get the attention of spiders of Internet search engines.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">With the Web address converter, requests from Web browsers using static addresses access corresponding dynamic Web pages and requests from search engines generate an instance of a Web page having links with static addresses pointing to corresponding dynamic Web pages. The Web address converter performs either or both Dynamic-to-Static (D-to-S) address conversion and Static-to-Dynamic (S-to-D) address conversion. D-to-S address conversion is done when generating a spider-friendly main page for a spider of a search engine to crawl. S-to-D address conversion is used when a browser uses a static address to access a corresponding dynamic Web page. The static address that the browser uses was originally created when the spider-friendly main page was generated.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0010" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic illustration of an exemplary computer network (such as the Internet) that includes a Web site hosting dynamic Web pages. The site includes a converter implementing an embodiment of the Web address converter for dynamic Web pages.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a bi-directional address-conversion-mapping diagram showing:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0037">from top to bottom, an exemplary implementation of dynamic-to-static (D-to-S) address conversion; and</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0002" num="0038">from bottom to top, an exemplary implementation of static-to-dynamic (S-to-D) address conversion.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is flowchart showing a process implementing the Web address converter for dynamic Web pages.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is flowchart showing a process implementing the Web address converter for dynamic Web pages.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is an example of a computer capable of implementing the Web address converter for dynamic Web pages.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0011" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0041" num="0042">The following description sets forth a specific embodiment of the Web address converter for dynamic Web pages that incorporates elements recited in the appended claims. This embodiment is described with specificity in order to meet statutory written description, enablement, and best-mode requirements. However, the description itself is not intended to limit the scope of this patent. Rather, the inventor has contemplated that the claimed Web address converter might also be embodied in other ways, in conjunction with other present or future technologies.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0043">The following description sets forth a Web address converter for dynamic Web pages that enable the use of static addresses to access corresponding dynamic Web pages. The converter provides static to dynamic URL mapping for certain incoming static addresses. The converter also provides for the dynamic generation of an instance of a Web page containing links to dynamic Web pages, but the links include static addresses pointing to the dynamic Web pages.</p>
<p id="h-0012" num="0000">Dynamic Web Sites and the Internet</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0044"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a computer network that includes computers linked via Internet <b>20</b>. Client <b>22</b> using a Web browser (e.g., “Internet Explorer” by the Microsoft Corporation) may access the Internet via one or more Internet Service Providers (ISPs) <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0045"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a search engine (with a spider) <b>26</b> connected to the Internet <b>20</b>. The search engine <b>26</b> includes a Web server (or collection of Web servers) <b>28</b> and a database <b>29</b>. The database <b>29</b> stores indexed keywords associated with source Web pages.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0046">The search engine <b>26</b> contains the searchable database <b>29</b> of keywords that are associated with Uniform Resource Locators (URLs) pointing to Web pages. Typically, a search engine uses a “spider” program module to fetch as many documents (i.e., Web pages) as possible. An “indexer” of the search engine reads these documents and creates a database based on the words contained in each document.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> also shows a static Web site <b>30</b> connected to the Internet <b>20</b>. The static Web site <b>30</b> includes a Web server (or collection of Web servers) <b>32</b>. The static Web site <b>30</b> contains static Web pages stored in a file located in the file system of the Web server <b>32</b>, and stored in non-volatile memory, such as disk drives <b>34</b><i>a</i>-<b>34</b><i>d. </i></p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0048">Disk drives <b>34</b><i>a</i>-<b>34</b><i>d </i>illustrate a hierarchical path to a file containing a static Web page on drive <b>34</b><i>d</i>. Suppose that drive <b>34</b><i>a </i>is named “root”; drive <b>34</b><i>b </i>is named “sub1”; drive <b>34</b><i>c </i>is named “sub2”; drive <b>34</b><i>d </i>is named “sub2”; and a file <b>36</b> named “file.htm”. The path to file <b>36</b> would be “/root/sub1/sub2/sub3/file.htm”.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0049">Although the path is shown as multiple disk drives <b>34</b><i>a</i>-<b>34</b><i>d</i>, the path typically will be both file directories and subdirectories on the same file system of the Web server. Alternatively, the path may be across multiple Web servers.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a dynamic Web site <b>40</b> connected to the Internet <b>20</b>. The dynamic Web site <b>40</b> includes a Web server (or collection of Web servers) <b>42</b>. The dynamic Web pages are dynamically generated by the server <b>42</b> based upon data stored in database <b>44</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0051">The dynamic Web site <b>40</b> also includes a Web address converter <b>46</b>. The converter <b>46</b> implements the exemplary embodiment of the Web address converter. The converter <b>46</b> may be a filter designed to examine incoming requests of the dynamic Web site. Although the converter <b>46</b> is shown as a filter that is separate from the server <b>42</b>, the converter may be part of the server.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0052">A filter determines whether incoming requests meet given requirements. If so, then it performs specified actions and/or modifies the request before passing it along to the Web server <b>42</b>. A filter is typically installed on port <b>80</b> (TCP:<b>80</b>) to capture Web-related traffic.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0053">Although a filter implementing the converter <b>46</b> may be hardware, it is software in the exemplary embodiment. Specifically, the converter <b>46</b> is an ISAPI (Internet Server Application Programming Interface) filter. ISAPI is an easy-to-use, high-performance interface and API for back-end applications for “Internet Information Server” (IIS) by the Microsoft Corporation. An ISAPI filter is a replaceable dynamic link library (DLL) that the server calls on every HTTP (Hypertext Transfer Protocol) request. When the filter is loaded, it tells the server what sort of notifications in which it is interested. After that, whenever the selected events occur, the filter is called and given the opportunity to process that event.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0054">Alternatively, the filter implementing the converter <b>46</b> may be a software program designed for that purpose, it may be part of a Web serving application, and it may be part of the operating system. Also, the functional components of the filter may be distributed over multiple Web servers in one site or multiple sites.</p>
<p id="h-0013" num="0000">Web Address Mapping</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0055"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows an example of Web address mapping for converting Web addresses from one type to another type that is implemented by Web address converter <b>46</b>. This address conversion is done so that requests from Web browsers using static addresses can access dynamic Web pages. Also, it is done so that requests from spiders of search engines generate an instance of a spider-friendly Web page having links with static addresses pointing to dynamic Web pages.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0056">There are two types of Web address conversion: Static-to-dynamic (S-to-D) and dynamic-to-static (D-to-S). Each is the reverse of the other. S-to-D address conversion is performed to redirect requests from Web browsers using static addresses to corresponding dynamic Web pages. D-to-S address conversion is performed to generate an instance of a spider-friendly Web page having links with static addresses pointing to corresponding dynamic Web pages.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows the address conversion mapping generally at <b>100</b>. Reading from top to bottom shows D-to-S address conversion as represented by “down” arrow <b>102</b>. Reading from bottom to top shows S-to-D address conversion as represented by “up” arrow <b>104</b>. Unless specifically stated otherwise, the addition of any field or value in one conversion direction corresponds to the removal of the same field or value in the other conversion direction, and vice versa.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0058">Block <b>110</b> shows a generic example of a dynamic address at <b>112</b>. The dynamic address points to a dynamic Web page. The dynamic address <b>112</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is (with a protocol scheme such as “http://being omitted):</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0059">hostname/path.asp?parmx=valx&amp;parmlast=vallast</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0060">Block <b>120</b> shows the fields removed from the dynamic address <b>112</b> to convert the dynamic address of <b>112</b> to a static address that points to the same dynamic Web page. The following fields are removed:
<ul id="ul0003" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0003-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0004" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0004-0001" num="0061">a field-separator symbol (“/”) at <b>122</b>;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0002" num="0062">a dynamic file extension (“.asp”) and a file-parameter-separator symbol (“?”) at <b>124</b>;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0003" num="0063">one or more parameter names (“parm×”) and a symbol (“=”) that equates each of them to value at <b>126</b>;</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0004" num="0064">a file-parameter-separator symbol (“&amp;”) used to separate each parameter from each other parameter at <b>128</b> (a parameter includes a parameter name and its value); and</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0005" num="0065">a last parameter name (“parmlast”) in the series of parameters and the symbol (“=”) that equates it to its value at <b>130</b>.
<br/>
If there is only one parameter, then “parm1ast” will be the only parameter name and there will be no “&amp;” symbol.
</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0066">Block <b>140</b> shows the fields that are found in both the source Web address and the converted Web address. Generally, these common fields are the basis for converting from one address type to another. These common fields map from the original address to specific positions in the converted address.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0067">The common fields include “scheme” field at <b>142</b> that identifies the protocol scheme being used to transmit the request for a Web page and the protocol scheme to be used to send the requested Web page. Since the exemplary embodiment is used for converting Web addresses, the typical protocol scheme is HTTP; therefore, the value of the scheme field <b>142</b> normally is “http://”.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0068">Other common fields shown in block <b>140</b> include a “hostname” field at <b>144</b>, a “path” at <b>146</b>, a “valx” at <b>148</b>, and a “vallast” at <b>150</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0069">The hostname field <b>144</b> contains a name of a Web server (or Web site) hosting the dynamic Web page. The name in the hostname field at <b>144</b> is “hostname” and it is derived from the static Web address <b>112</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0070">The path field <b>146</b> contains a name of a hierarchical path used to access the file containing instructions for generating the dynamic Web page. The name in the path field at <b>146</b> is “path” and is derived from the static Web address <b>112</b>. Similar to the hierarchical path illustrated by the disk drives <b>34</b><i>a</i>-<b>34</b><i>d </i>of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the path in the path field <b>146</b> may be one or more levels. For example, the path may be “path”; “root/path”; or “root/subpath1/subpath2/path”.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0071">The valx value field <b>148</b> may be one or more parameter values. Each valx value field contains a value associated with a parameter name (like “parmx” <b>126</b>). The “=” symbol equates each parameter with a specific value. For example, “parm×” has a value of “valx”.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0072">The vallast value field <b>150</b> a value associated with the last parameter name (like “parmlast” <b>130</b>). The “=” symbol equates the last parameter name with a specific value. For example, “parmlast” has a value of “vallast”. If there is only one parameter in the dynamic address <b>112</b>, then “vallast” will be the only value and there will be no valx values.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0073">Block <b>160</b> shows the fields added to the common fields of block <b>140</b> to convert the dynamic address of <b>112</b> to a static address that points to the same dynamic Web page. The following fields are added:
<ul id="ul0005" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0005-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0006" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0006-0001" num="0074">a field-separator symbol (“/”) and an alias-indicator flag (“flag”) at <b>162</b>;</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0002" num="0075">one or more field-separator symbol (“/”) at <b>164</b>;</li>
        <li id="ul0006-0003" num="0076">a static file extension (“.htm”) that indicates that the format of the file is static although the file's format is actually dynamic.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0077">The alias-indicator flag <b>162</b> is inserted into the resulting static address so that the exemplary converter will recognize it as a static address that does not point to an actual static Web page. Rather, the address with the alias-indicator flag points to a dynamic Web page.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0078">Block <b>170</b> shows an example of a convened static address at <b>172</b>. This static address points to the same dynamic Web page that the dynamic address of <b>112</b> does. The static address <b>172</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is (with a protocol scheme such as “http://” being omitted):
<ul id="ul0007" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0007-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0008" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0008-0001" num="0079">hostname/flag/path/valx/vallast.htm</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0080">The arrows between the fields of block <b>160</b> and the static address <b>172</b> of block <b>170</b> illustrate the relative mapping of the fields into the static address. The fields <b>162</b>-<b>166</b> are inserted between the common fields <b>142</b>-<b>150</b> of block <b>140</b> to form the static address <b>172</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0081">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the common fields <b>142</b>-<b>150</b> of block <b>140</b> are shown underlined in the dynamic address <b>112</b> and the static address <b>172</b>. The underlining makes the common fields easier to locate in the originating dynamic address <b>112</b> and the resulting static address <b>172</b>. The underlining also highlights the existence and the relative location of each field in the both addresses. Furthermore, it distinguishes the common fields from other fields that are specific to only one type of address.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0082">The arrows between blocks <b>1110</b> and <b>130</b> illustrate which fields are removed from the dynamic address <b>112</b> and where the fields are removed. Likewise, the arrows between blocks <b>160</b> and <b>170</b> illustrate which fields are added to the common fields to form the static address <b>172</b> and where the fields are added.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0083">The above description of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is given reading from top to bottom to illustration D-to-S address conversion. However, as mentioned above, the addition of any field or value for the above-described D-to-S address conversion corresponds to the removal of the same field or value in the S-to-D address conversion. Likewise, the removal of any field or value for the above-described D-to-S address conversion corresponds to the addition of the same field or value in the S-to-D address conversion.</p>
<p id="h-0014" num="0000">Alternative Parameter Value Mapping</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0084">In the exemplary embodiment of the Web address converter, the converter places the parameter values (such as “valx” or “vallast”) based upon their relative position in the original dynamic address. For example, “valx” is before “vallast”. When such a static address is converted back (re-mapped) to a dynamic address, the converter assumes the parameter fields based upon the relative positioning of the parameter values in the static address. For example, “parm1ast” is assumed to be equal to “vallast” because “vallast” is the last field in the static address.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0085">In an alternative embodiment, the parameter associations may be specified in the static address so that values are re-mapped back specific parameters. This may occur in a variety of ways. As one example, assume the following original dynamic address (with a protocol scheme such as “http://” being omitted):</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0086">hostname/path.asp?parmA=valA&amp;parmB=valB&amp;parmC=valC</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0087">This dynamic address may be converted into this static address with a protocol scheme such as “http://” being omitted):</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0088">hostname/flag/path/parmA=valA/parmB=valB/parmC=valC.htm</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0089">An alternative encoding may be (with a protocol scheme such as “http://” being omitted):</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0090">hostname/flag/path.parmA/valA/parmB/valB/parmC/valC.htm</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0091">Any encoding that includes both the parameter name and the value in such a way that the original pairing can be extracted may be used. When such an alternative embodiment of the Web address converter maps this static address backs to its original dynamic address, it will not assume how to map the values back to the dynamic address. Rather, it will examine the static address to see exactly how to map the values to which parameters because the parameters themselves are specified in the static address.</p>
<p id="h-0015" num="0000">Method of Web Address Analysis and Conversion</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0092"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a process for handling a request for dynamic Web pages that is implemented by the Web address converter. At <b>200</b>, a request to access a Web page is received by a Web server or a filter (such as the filter <b>46</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>). For the exemplary implementation, the filter receives the request. Such a request may be a GET request in HTTP.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0093">If the request includes a dynamic address, then the filter passes it back to the Web server for normal dynamic Web page invocation. Otherwise, the request includes a static Web address. At <b>202</b>, the filter parses the request to extract the static address included therein.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0094">At <b>204</b>, the static address is examined to determine if it includes an “alias-indicator flag.” The alias-indicator flag is any set of unique (within the Web server) alphanumeric characters that may be used within a static address to identify the address as being an “alias address.” For example, the flag may be “root”, “flag”, “static”, or “alias”. The field containing the alias-indicator flag is shown at <b>162</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. An “alias address” is a static address that points to a dynamic Web page rather than a static one. There are two sources of an “alias address.”</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0095">The first source is where an alias address is a resulting static address from the exemplary D-to-S address conversion. During the D-to-S address conversion, the alias-indicator flag is inserted into the resulting static address in the manner shown at blocks <b>160</b> and <b>170</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0096">The second source of an alias address is an address stored in a file on the Web server. That file is called the “robots.txt” file. The address stored in this file includes the alias-indicator flag.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0097">This “robots.txt” file informs a spider whether the spider is authorized to search the site and if so authorized, which pages on the site to retrieve. In the exemplary embodiment, the “robots.txt” file authorizes a spider to access only one page and that page is a “spider-friendly main” Web page (i.e., “spider-friendly index” page). The spider-friendly main page is generated upon access. The generation of the spider-friendly main page is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, which is discussed below.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0098">Therefore, if the static address parsed from the request is an “alias address”, then the process will proceed to block <b>208</b> for further analysis of the static address. Otherwise, the static address is a conventional static address and it points to an actual static Web page. In this case, the process will proceed to block <b>206</b> to allow access to an actual static Web page as normal. The filter will hand the static address to the Web server so that the Web server can access and send the referenced static Web page.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0099">At <b>208</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the static address (which is now known to be an alias address) is further examined to determine if the address includes parameter values. Parameter values are fields after the path in the static address. Referring again to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, “/valx/vallast.htm” are parameter values after “path” in static address <b>172</b> of block <b>170</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0100">If the static address does not have parameter values, then the static address points to the spider-friendly main page. Therefore, the process proceeds to block <b>210</b> and the generation of the spider-friendly main page illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, which is discussed below. If the static address includes parameter values, then the static address points to dynamic Web page, then the process proceeds to block <b>212</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0101">At <b>212</b>, the static address is converted into its mapped dynamic address in the manner illustrated from bottom to top in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and described above as the S-to-D address conversion. This produces a dynamic address that points to an existing files storing instructions from dynamically generating the dynamic Web page.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0102">At <b>214</b>, the dynamic Web page referenced by the converted dynamic address is invoked. When generating the web page, meta-tags may also be inserted. Such meta-tags help the search engines properly index each individual web page. The meta-tags may be derived from a variety of sources. For example, the meta-tags may be dynamically generated from the content of the web page. Alternatively, the meta-tags may be retrieved from the database. In yet a further alternative, the meta-tags may be from a variety of sources, such as a combination of meta-tags that are dynamically generated and meta-tags that are retrieved from a database or provided by some other component.</p>
<p id="p-0093" num="0103">The purpose of inserting these meta-tags is to enhance the chances of the specific page being found during a search of a search engine. The use of meta-tags increases the breadth of keywords used on the page. This increases the likelihood of the specific page being found during a search on a search engine. At <b>216</b>, the dynamic Web page is sent to the requester. Dynamic Web pages have instructions and the dynamic addresses have parameters and values. These instructions, the parameters, the values are used to generate (i.e., invoke) a Web page based upon information in the database. At <b>218</b>, on-going Web page access continues as normal.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0104">In blocks <b>204</b> and <b>208</b>, the filter makes three determinations in this order:
<ul id="ul0009" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0009-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0010" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0010-0001" num="0105">Does the request include a normal static address to access actual static Web pages?</li>
        <li id="ul0010-0002" num="0106">If not, then does the request include a “special” static address? A static address is “special” if it includes an alias-indicator flag.</li>
        <li id="ul0010-0003" num="0107">If the static address is “special”, then does the address point to the spider-friendly main page or does it point to somewhere else?.
<br/>
The exemplary converter makes these three determinations by detecting an alias-indicator flag (like “flag” of block <b>162</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) and parameter values (like “valx” and “vallast” of blocks <b>148</b> and <b>150</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>).
</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0108">Alternatively, the determinations may be made by employing multiple flags in the static address. Each flag helps the filter make each determination. In addition, the spider-friendly main page may have a defined address that contains no flags itself, but the filter will recognize the defined address.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0109"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows more of the process for handling a request for dynamic Web pages that is implemented by the Web address converter. Specifically, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows the generation of the spider-friendly main page, which is represented by block <b>210</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0110">At <b>250</b>, the filter dynamically generates an initial main page. This initial main page includes links containing dynamic addresses pointing to dynamic Web pages. These dynamic Web pages may represent the current inventory for an e-commerce site.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0111">At <b>252</b>, meta-tags are inserted into the initial main page. The filter has a defined set of meta-tags that are inserted each time a main page is generated. Alternatively, the filter dynamically generates a set of meta-tags that are created based upon current information in the database. Further, the filter may directly retrieve the meta-tags from the database.</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0112">Like the meta-tags generated for a specific dynamic Web page of block <b>214</b>, the purpose of inserting these meta-tags into the main page is to enhance the chances of the page being found during a search of a search engine. The use of meta-tags increases the breadth of keywords used on the page. This increases the likelihood of the main page being found during a search on a search engine.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0113">At <b>254</b>, the dynamic addresses in these links are converted into static addresses in the manner described above as D-to-S address conversion and shown from top to bottom in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0114">At <b>256</b>, the filter sends the spider-friendly main page to the requester. The requester is typically a browser or a spider. At <b>258</b>, on-going Web page access continues as normal.</p>
<p id="h-0016" num="0000">Exemplary Computer</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0115"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows a computer that is an example of a Web server that is used with the exemplary implementation of the Web address converter for dynamic Web pages. This computer may be a client running a Web browser, a Web server running a search engine, a Web server hosting a static Web site, a Web server hosting a dynamic Web site, or any computer within a communications network (such as the Internet).</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0116">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, computer <b>330</b> includes one or more processors or processing units <b>332</b>, a system memory <b>334</b>, and a bus <b>336</b> that couples various system components including the system memory <b>334</b> to processors <b>332</b>. Bus <b>336</b> represents one or more of any of several types of bus structures, including a memory bus or memory controller, a peripheral bus, an accelerated graphics port, and a processor or local bus using any of a variety of bus architectures.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0117">The system memory includes read only memory (ROM) <b>338</b> and random access memory (RAM) <b>340</b>. A basic input/output system (BIOS) <b>342</b>, containing the basic routines that help to transfer information between elements within computer <b>330</b>, such as during start-up, is stored in ROM <b>338</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0105" num="0118">Computer <b>330</b> further includes a hard disk drive <b>344</b> for reading from and writing to a hard disk, not shown, a magnetic disk drive <b>346</b> for reading from and writing to a removable magnetic disk <b>348</b>, and an optical disk drive <b>350</b> for reading from or writing to a removable optical disk <b>352</b> such as a CD ROM, DVD <b>11</b> ROM or other optical media. The hard disk drive <b>344</b>, magnetic disk drive <b>346</b> and optical disk drive <b>350</b> are each connected to bus <b>336</b> by one or more interfaces <b>354</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0119">The drives and their associated computer-readable media provide nonvolatile storage of computer readable instructions, data structures, program modules, and other data for computer <b>330</b>. Although the exemplary environment described herein employs a hard disk, a removable magnetic disk <b>348</b> and a removable optical disk <b>352</b>, it should be appreciated by those skilled in the art that other types of computer readable media which can store data that is accessible by a computer, such as magnetic cassettes, flash memory cards, digital video disks, random access memories (RAMs), read only memories (ROM), and the like, may also be used in the exemplary operating environment.</p>
<p id="p-0107" num="0120">A number of program modules may be stored on the hard disk, magnetic disk <b>348</b>, optical disk <b>352</b>, ROM <b>338</b>, or RAM <b>340</b>, including an operating system <b>358</b>, one or more application programs <b>360</b> (such as a Web browser), other program modules <b>362</b>, and program data <b>364</b>. A user may enter commands and information into computer <b>330</b> through input devices such as keyboard <b>366</b> and pointing device <b>368</b>. Other input devices (not shown) may include a microphone, joystick, game pad, satellite dish, scanner, or the like. These and other input devices are connected to the processing unit <b>332</b> through an interface <b>370</b> that is coupled to bus <b>336</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0121">A monitor <b>372</b> or other type of display device is also connected to bus <b>336</b> via an interface, such as a video adapter <b>374</b>. In addition to the monitor, personal computers typically include other peripheral output devices (not shown) such as speakers and printers.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0122">Computer <b>330</b> can operate in a networked environment using logical connections to one or more remote computers, such as a Web server <b>382</b>. Web server <b>382</b> typically includes many or all of the elements described above relative to computer <b>330</b>. In addition, a Web database <b>384</b> may be connected to the Web server <b>382</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0123">A logical connection that is not depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a local area network (LAN) via network interface <b>386</b> and a general wide area network (WAN) via a modem <b>378</b>. Such networking environments are commonplace in offices, enterprise-wide computer networks, intranets, and the Internet.</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0124">Depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, is a specific implementation of a WAN via the Internet. Over the Internet, computer <b>330</b> typically includes a modem <b>378</b> or other means for establishing communications over the Internet <b>380</b>. Modem <b>378</b>, which may be internal or external, is connected to bus <b>336</b> via interface <b>356</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0125">In a networked environment, program modules depicted relative to the personal computer <b>330</b>, or portions thereof, may be stored in the remote memory storage device. It will be appreciated that the network connections shown and described are exemplary and other means of establishing a communications link between the computers may be used.</p>
<heading id="h-0017" level="1">EXAMPLE</heading>
<heading id="h-0018" level="1">“Acmetoys.store” Dynamic Web Site</heading>
<p id="p-0113" num="0126">The following example is provided to help illustrate how the exemplary implementation of the Web address converter might be used.</p>
<p id="p-0114" num="0127">Suppose that a fictional company called “Acme Toy Store” has an e-commerce Web site where it sells toys and playthings. Acme's Web address is “acmetoys.store” (with a protocol scheme such as “http://” being omitted). Like a “brick-and-mortar” store, Acme's e-commerce site has an inventory that is constantly changing as existing items are sold and shipped and new items arrive. Therefore, Acme's Web site has dynamically accessible and updateable database for tracking inventory. Acme can track its inventory in real time and users of Acme's site can order “in-stock” items in real time.</p>
<p id="p-0115" num="0128">Acme would like for Internet search engines to be a source of inexpensive advertisement for its toys. Acme would like for the spiders of search engines to crawl its Web site and index its products. That way, a search engine may direct a user (who is searching for that hot new toy from overseas) to Acme's site. Preferably, the search engine may direct the user to the particular page on the site referring to that hot new toy. Acme would like users to go directly to their dynamic Web pages so that the user can view the current product information.</p>
<p id="p-0116" num="0129">Acme implements the exemplary embodiment of the Web address converter in an ISAPI filter on its Web site. Acme modifies is “robots.txt” file on its Web server to authorize and direct spiders to crawl a spider-friendly main page at “acmetoys.store/flag/index.htm” (with a protocol scheme such as “http://” being omitted). The alias-indicator flag is “flag.”</p>
<p id="p-0117" num="0130">Subsequently, a spider from a search engine arrives to crawl Acme's site. The spider examines the “robots.txt” file and proceeds to access the spider-friendly main page.</p>
<p id="p-0118" num="0131">Referring to the flow charts shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, the filter receives (at <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) a request from the spider to access a Web page. The filter parses (at <b>202</b>) the request and pulls out this static address:</p>
<p id="p-0119" num="0132">“acmetoys.store/flag/index.htm” (with a protocol scheme such as “http://” being omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0120" num="0133">Upon examination (at <b>204</b>) of this address, the filter determines that it includes “flag”, which is the alias-indicator flag. Upon further examination (at <b>208</b>) of this address, the filter determines that the address does not include any parameter values.</p>
<p id="p-0121" num="0134">Therefore, the filter generates an initial main page having links with dynamic addresses (at <b>250</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>). The dynamic addresses point to dynamic Web pages describing the available toys and providing a means for purchasing such toys. The filter inserts (at <b>252</b>) a set of meta-tags into the initial main page. The meta-tags have many keywords related to toys and playthings.</p>
<p id="p-0122" num="0135">D-to-S conversion (at <b>254</b>) is performed on the dynamic address so that the links include static addresses. These static addresses will include the alias-<b>19</b> indicator flag and one or more parameter values.</p>
<p id="p-0123" num="0136">Below is an example of Web address conversion using a dynamic Web page on Acme's site that describes a fictional product called “megawheel.” The following example of D-to-S address conversion is done in accordance with such D-to-S address conversion illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and described above:</p>
<heading id="h-0019" level="1">Megawbeel Dynamic Address (with a Protocol Scheme Such as “http://” Being Omitted):</heading>
<p id="p-0124" num="0137">acmetoys.store/toys/wheeled.asp?age=4-or-under&amp;name=megawheel</p>
<p id="h-0020" num="0000">The following is a table identifying the fields illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and described above. The field names are italicized. The table also gives the specific values of these fields:</p>
<p id="p-0125" num="0138">
<tables id="TABLE-US-00001" num="00001">
<table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0" pgwide="1">
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="3">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="84pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="105pt" align="center"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="91pt" align="center"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="3" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Common</entry>
<entry>Dynamic</entry>
<entry>Static</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Fields</entry>
<entry>Fields Removed</entry>
<entry>Fields Added</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
<tgroup align="left" colsep="0" rowsep="0" cols="6">
<colspec colname="1" colwidth="35pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="2" colwidth="49pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="3" colwidth="77pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="4" colwidth="28pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="5" colwidth="63pt" align="left"/>
<colspec colname="6" colwidth="28pt" align="left"/>
<tbody valign="top">
<row>
<entry>scheme</entry>
<entry>http://</entry>
<entry>field separator</entry>
<entry>/</entry>
<entry>field separator</entry>
<entry>/</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="6" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>hostname</entry>
<entry>acmetoys.store</entry>
<entry>dynamic file extension</entry>
<entry>“.asp”</entry>
<entry>flag</entry>
<entry>flag</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>path</entry>
<entry>toys/wheeled</entry>
<entry>file-parameter-separator</entry>
<entry>?</entry>
<entry>field separator</entry>
<entry>/</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>valx</entry>
<entry>4-or-under</entry>
<entry>parameter</entry>
<entry>age</entry>
<entry>field separator</entry>
<entry>/</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>vallast</entry>
<entry>megawheel</entry>
<entry>parameter separator</entry>
<entry>&amp;</entry>
<entry>field separator</entry>
<entry>/</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry>last parameter</entry>
<entry>name</entry>
<entry>static file extension</entry>
<entry>“.htm”</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="1" nameend="6" align="center" rowsep="1"/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</tables>
<br/>
Resulting example static address (after D-to-S address conversion):
</p>
<heading id="h-0021" level="1">Megawbeel Static Address (with a Protocol Scheme Such as “http://” Being Omitted):</heading>
<p id="p-0126" num="0139">acmetoys.store/flag/toys/wheeled/4-or-under/megawheel.htm</p>
<p id="p-0127" num="0140">After the D-to-S address conversion of the address in the links in the initial main page, the page becomes the spider-friendly main page. The filter sends (at <b>256</b>) the spider-friendly main page to the original requester, which was the spider of the search engine.</p>
<p id="p-0128" num="0141">The indexer of the search engine indexes the spider-friendly main page of Acme's Web site. Keywords from the spider-friendly main page are stored in the search engine's database.</p>
<p id="p-0129" num="0142">Subsequently, a user searches for a toy called “megawheel” on the search engine. It discovers a link to Acme's Web site. That link includes the megawheel static address (as shown above). The user clicks on that link and is whisked away to Acme's site.</p>
<p id="p-0130" num="0143">Again referring to the flow charts shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, the filter receives (at <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) a request from the browser of the user to access a Web page. The filter parses (at <b>202</b>) the request and pulls out the megawheel static address (with a protocol scheme such as “http://” being omitted): “acmetoys.store/flag/toys/wheeled/4-or-under/megawheel.htm”.</p>
<p id="p-0131" num="0144">Upon examination (at <b>204</b>) of this address, the filter determines that it includes “flag”, which is the alias-indicator flag. Upon further examination (at <b>208</b>) of this address, the filter determines that the address includes parameter values. Specifically, the address includes “4-or-under” and “megawheel” parameter values. The filter performs S-to-D address conversion (at <b>212</b>) on the static address so that browser can be redirected to the megawheel dynamic Web page.</p>
<p id="p-0132" num="0145">S-to-D address conversion is done in accordance with such S-to-D conversion illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and described above. The static address is converted into megawheel dynamic address (with a protocol scheme such as “http://” being omitted): “acmetoys.store/toys/wheeled.asp?age=4-or-under&amp;name=megawheel”. Note that this is the megawheel dynamic address and the same address that was the source for the D-to-S address conversion performed when generating the spider-friendly main page.</p>
<p id="p-0133" num="0146">After this S-to-D address conversion, the desired megawheel dynamic Web page is invoked and megawheel-related meta tags are inserted into the page (at <b>214</b>). The page is sent to the browser of the user (at <b>216</b>). Therefore, the user views the current dynamic Web page for the “megawheel” product. The user found the megawheel dynamic Web page using a corresponding megawheel static address stored in a searchable database of a search engine.</p>
<heading id="h-0022" level="1">Conclusion</heading>
<p id="p-0134" num="0147">Using the exemplary implementation of the Web address converter, spiders can fetch and indexers can index the dynamic content of dynamic Web sites. Furthermore, browsers using a static address to a dynamic Web page of a dynamic Web site can access the referenced dynamic Web page, rather then a stale, static copy.</p>
<p id="p-0135" num="0148">Although the address converter has been described in language specific to structural features and/or methodological steps, it is to be understood that the web address converter defined in the appended claims is not necessarily limited to the specific features or steps described. Rather, the specific features and steps are disclosed as preferred forms of implementing the claimed web address converter.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. One or more computer-readable storage media having computer-executable instructions thereon that, when executed by a computer, performance acts comprising: receiving a request from a search engine for an instance of a main Web page; after the receiving of the request for the instance of the main Web page, generating the instance of the main Web page, the instance having at least one link with a dynamic address pointing to a dynamic Web page; converting the dynamic address into a static address pointing to the dynamic Web page, the converting of the dynamic address into the static address comprising:
<claim-text>parsing the dynamic address to identify and separate fields within the dynamic address, wherein at least one field has a value; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating the static address incorporating the value of the at least one field, wherein the static address points to the dynamic Web page; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>facilitating crawling, by the search engine, of the static address located on the instance of the main Web page, so that the search engine may send the static address to a computer on a network.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the dynamic and static addresses are Uniform Resource Locators (URL) having a syntax and having semantics for a compact text-string representation for a resource available via the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>an indicator for HyperText Transfer Protocol (“http”); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a static path, wherein the static path is a static hierarchically defined path to a Web page on the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>an indicator for HyperText Transfer Protocol (“http”); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a static path, wherein the static path is a static hierarchically defined path to a Web page on the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the dynamic address is a compact text-string representation for a dynamically generated resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted in accordance with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters: a scheme-identifying text;
<claim-text>a dynamic-address indicator that indicates that this address is configured to represent a dynamically generated resource; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic searchpart, wherein the searchpart provides data for dynamic generation of the dynamically generated resource.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a dynamically generated resource accessible via the internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>an indicator for HyperText Transfer Protocol (“http”);</claim-text>
<claim-text>a question-mark symbol (“?”), which indicates that this address is configured to represent</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamically generated resource; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic searchpart, wherein the searchpart provides data for dynamic generation of the dynamically generated resource.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising the act of sending the instance of the main Web page over a communications network.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the request comprises a static address pointing to the main Web page.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the generating of the instance of the main Web page comprises forming the instance of the main Web page so that the main Web page contains meta-tags for facilitating indexing by the search engine.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. One or more computer-readable storage media having computer-executable instructions thereon that, when executed by a computer, perform acts for static-to-dynamic (S-to-D) Web address conversion, the acts comprising:
<claim-text>facilitating crawling, by a search engine, of a static address located on a spider-friendly Web page, so that the search engine may send the static address to a user of the search engine;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving a request by the user of the search engine for a dynamic Web page, the request including the static address pointing to the dynamic Web page;</claim-text>
<claim-text>converting the static address to a dynamic address that also points to the dynamic Web page, wherein the converting of the static address to the dynamic address comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>parsing the static address to identify at least one value associated with a field within the static address: and</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating the dynamic address incorporating at least one value associated with a field,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the dynamic address points to the dynamic Web page; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>re-directing the user of the search engine to the dynamic Web page after selection of the static address.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the dynamic and static addresses are Uniform Resource Locators (URL) having a syntax and having semantics for a compact text-string representation for a resource available via the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>a scheme-identifying text; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a static path, wherein the path is a static hierarchically defined path to a Web page on the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>an indicator for Hyper Text Transfer Protocol (“http”); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a static path, wherein the static path is a static hierarchically defined path to a Web page on the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the dynamic address is a compact text-string representation for a dynamically generated resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted in accordance with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>a scheme-identifying text;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic-address indicator that indicates that this address is configured to represent a dynamically generated resource; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic searchpart, wherein the searchpart provides data for dynamic generation of the dynamically generated resource.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a dynamically generated resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>an indicator for HyperText Transfer Protocol (“http”);</claim-text>
<claim-text>a question-mark symbol (“?”), which indicates that this address is configured to represent a dynamically generated resource; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic searchpart, wherein the searchpart provides data for dynamic generation of the dynamically generated resource.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> further comprising providing the dynamic address to a server.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> further comprising invoking the dynamic Web page referenced by the dynamic address.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref> further comprising sending the dynamic Web page referenced by the dynamic address to the user.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. One or more computer-readable storage media having computer-executable instructions thereon that, when executed by a computer, perform acts for dynamic- to-static (D-to-S) Web address conversion, the acts comprising:
<claim-text>receiving a request from a search engine to crawl a Website;</claim-text>
<claim-text>in response to the receiving of the request from the search engine, generating an instance of a main Web page having at least one link with a dynamic address pointing to a dynamic Web page; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>converting the dynamic address to a static address also pointing to the dynamic Web page, the converting of the dynamic address to the static address comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>parsing the dynamic address to identify and separate fields within the dynamic address, wherein at least one field has a value; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating the static address incorporating the value of the at least one field, the static address also pointing to the dynamic Web page;</claim-text>
<claim-text>facilitating crawling, by the search engine, of the static address located on the instance of the main Web page, so that the search engine may send the static address to a computer on the network.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the dynamic and static addresses are Uniform Resource Locators (URL) having a syntax and having semantics for a compact text-string representation for a resource available via the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>a scheme-identifying text; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a static path, wherein the path is a static hierarchically defined path to a Web page on the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>an indicator for Hyper Text Transfer Protocol (“http”); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a static path, wherein the static path is a static hierarchically defined path to a Web page on the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00023" num="00023">
<claim-text>23. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the dynamic address is a compact text-string representation for a dynamically generated resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted in accordance with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>a scheme-identifying text;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic-address indicator that indicates that this address is configured to represent a dynamically generated resource; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic search part, wherein the search part provides data for dynamic generation of the dynamically generated resource.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00024" num="00024">
<claim-text>24. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a dynamically generated resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>an indicator for Hyper Text Transfer Protocol (“HTTP”);</claim-text>
<claim-text>a question-mark symbol (“?”), which indicates that this address is configured to represent</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamically generated resource; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic searchpart, wherein the searchpart provides data for dynamic generation of the dynamically generated resource.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00025" num="00025">
<claim-text>25. One or more computer-readable storage media having computer-executable instructions thereon that, when executed by a computer, perform acts for providing a dynamic Web page, the acts comprising: receiving a request from a search engine to crawl a Website;
<claim-text>generating an instance of a main Web page having at least one link with a dynamic Web address pointing to a dynamic Web page converting the dynamic Web address into a static Web address that also points to the dynamic Web page;</claim-text>
<claim-text>facilitating crawling, by the search engine, of the static Web address located on the main Web page, so that the search engine may send the static Web address to a computer on a network;</claim-text>
<claim-text>receiving a request for the dynamic Web page from the computer on the network, the request including the static Web address pointing to the dynamic Web page;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating an instance of the dynamic Web page such that contents of the instance appear as a static Web page; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>sending the dynamic Web page to the computer on the network.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00026" num="00026">
<claim-text>26. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref>, wherein the dynamic and static addresses are Uniform Resource Locators (URL) having a syntax and having semantics for a compact text-string representation for a resource available via the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00027" num="00027">
<claim-text>27. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>a scheme-identifying text; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a static path, wherein the path is a static hierarchically defined path to a Web page on the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00028" num="00028">
<claim-text>28. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>an indicator for Hyper Text Transfer Protocol (“http”); and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a static path, wherein the static path is a static hierarchically defined path to a Web page on the Internet.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00029" num="00029">
<claim-text>29. One or more computer-ieadable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref>, wherein the dynamic address is a compact text-string representation for a dynamically generated resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and haying semantics formatted in accordance with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>a scheme-identifying text;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic-address indicator that indicates that this address is configured to represent a</claim-text>
<claim-text>dynamically generated resource; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic searchpart, wherein the searchpart provides data for dynamic generation of the dynamically generated resource.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00030" num="00030">
<claim-text>30. One or more computer-readable storage media as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00025">claim 25</claim-ref>, wherein the static address is a compact text-string representation for a dynamically generated resource accessible via the Internet, the compact text-string representation having a hierarchical syntax and having semantics formatted with the following textual components separated by one or more delimiters:
<claim-text>an indicator for HyperText Transfer Protocol (“http”);</claim-text>
<claim-text>a question-mark symbol (“?”), which indicates that this address is configured to represent</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamically generated resource; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dynamic searchpart, wherein the searchpart provides data for dynamic generation of the dynamically generated resource.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
