<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296405-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296405</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10512156</doc-number>
<date>20030422</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>FR</country>
<doc-number>02 05010</doc-number>
<date>20020422</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>73</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>34</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60370</main-classification>
<further-classification> 91331</further-classification>
<further-classification>123 9016</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Variable flow reducing valve and gradual control valve distribution system for a compressed air injection engine operating on mono or multi energy and other engines or compressors</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>310310</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Pitchford</name>
<date>18850100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 91324</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3641988</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Torazza et al.</name>
<date>19720200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4762098</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tamba et al.</name>
<date>19880800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5456224</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Riley</name>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>123 9016</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2001/0002379</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Schechter</name>
<date>20010500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>396065</doc-number>
<kind>C</kind>
<date>19240500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>FR</country>
<doc-number>511513</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19201200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>FR</country>
<doc-number>849794</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19390100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 60370</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 91303</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 91331-333</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 91348-349</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 91354</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 9015- 9017</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 902</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 9027</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 9031</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 9041</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 9044</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>123 9047</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050224059</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051013</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Negre</last-name>
<first-name>Guy</first-name>
<address>
<city>Carros Cedex</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>FR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>FR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Negre</last-name>
<first-name>Cyril</first-name>
<address>
<city>Carros Cedex</city>
<country>FR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>FR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>FR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Connolly Bove Lodge &amp; Hutz LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>MDI Motor Development International S.A.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<country>LU</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Leslie</last-name>
<first-name>Michael</first-name>
<department>3745</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/FR03/01265</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20030422</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20050503</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO03/089764</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20031030</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A variable flow reducing valve and distribution system is disclosed for compressed air injection engines operating on mono or dual energy with dual or triple supply mode and comprising a high pressure compressed air tank and a buffer capacity. The system can control the stroke of an engine piston and stop the piston at the dead centre. Moreover, the air supply in the buffer capacity and to the cylinders is controlled by pilot valves. A cam for the pilot valves is positioned directly on the flanges of a crankshaft and drives the rocker arm rods to pivot rocker arms around corresponding mobile shafts that can move between two ends of the rocker arms, thereby controlling lifting of the pilot valves according to the movement of the rocker arm rods.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="152.91mm" wi="209.30mm" file="US07296405-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="210.90mm" wi="154.35mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296405-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="207.35mm" wi="151.47mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296405-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="191.01mm" wi="116.76mm" file="US07296405-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="186.01mm" wi="120.65mm" file="US07296405-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="201.93mm" wi="163.66mm" file="US07296405-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="251.29mm" wi="144.10mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296405-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention concerns a distribution system using valves notably for engines, and more specifically, for those powered by the injection of additional compressed air, comprising a compressed air tank and operating on mono or dual energy with dual or triple supply mode and on multi-energy. The invention is also suitable for use with conventional internal combustion engines and compressors.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The term engine distribution system refers to all the means used for opening and closing the pipes for the purpose of letting in and/or letting out the fluids or gases required for the engine or the compressor to work.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">There are distribution systems made up of rocker arms mounted on a fixed pin. One of the ends of the aforesaid rocker arm receives the driving thrust via a rocker arm rod, itself controlled via a cam mounted on a shaft driven via the engine crankshaft; the other end is activated so that it pushes open the valve. The lever arm ratio thus formed determines the lifting of the valve for a given movement of the rocker arm rod.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The author has registered numerous patents relating to motor drive units as well as their installations, using additional compressed air to give a totally clean operation in urban and suburban areas:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0005">WO 96/27737 WO 97/00655</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0002" num="0006">WO 97/48884 WO 98/12062 WO 98/15440</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0003" num="0007">WO 98/32963 WO 99/37885 WO 99/37886</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0008">For implementing these inventions, he has also described in his application for patent WO 99/63206, the contents of which can be referred to, a method and a device for controlling the engine piston movement making it possible to stop the piston at its top dead centre; method also described in his application for patent WO 99/20881, the contents of which can also be referred to, relating to the operating of these engines on single-energy or dual-energy, in dual or triple feed modes.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0009">According to a preferred mode, the engine unit is fitted with moving elements (crank piston rod system) comprising a device for controlling the engine piston movement such as is described in patent WO 99/20881, the contents of which can be referred to. The aforesaid device is characterized by the fact that the piston is held in its top dead centre position for a period of time, therefore for a significant angular sector during rotation. This is used at constant volume to carry out:
<ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0003" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0003-0001" num="0010">operations for transferring gas and/or compressed air, and for stopping the piston at its top dead centre.</li>
        <li id="ul0003-0002" num="0011">ignition and combustion operations in the case of standard engines.</li>
        <li id="ul0003-0003" num="0012">fuel injection operations in the case of diesel engines.</li>
        <li id="ul0003-0004" num="0013">end of exhaust, and beginning of intake operations for all engines and compressors.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0014">So that the piston can be stopped at its top dead centre, it is controlled by a pressure lever device, itself controlled by a crank piston rod system. The tern pressure lever refers to a system of two hinged arms. The end of one of the aforesaid arms, known as a pivot, is stationary and the other can move along an axis. If a force, more or less perpendicular to the axis of the two arms when they are aligned, is applied to the joint between these two arms, the free end will then move. This free end is linked to the piston and controls its movements. The piston is at its top dead centre when the two hinged rods are essentially in line with one another (around 180°).</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0015">The crankshaft is linked via a control rod to the hinge pin for the two arms The way the different elements are positioned and their sizes make it possible to modify the characteristics of the assembly kinematics. The positioning of the stationary end determines an angle between the travel axis of the piston and the axis of the two arms when they are aligned. The positioning of the crankshaft determines an angle between the control rod and the axis of the two arms when they are aligned. Varying the values of these angles, together with the lengths of the connecting rods and arms, makes it possible to determine the crankshaft rotation angle during which the piston is stopped at its top dead centre. This corresponds to the length of time for which the piston is stopped.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0016">According to a particular embodiment, the device assembly (piston and pressure lever) is balanced with its lower arm extended beyond its stationary end or pivot against a mirror-image pressure lever working in the opposing direction. This symmetrical pressure lever with identical inertia has an identical inertial weight facing in the opposing direction to that of the piston fixed to it; said inertial weight is capable of travelling along an axis parallel to the travel axis of the piston. The term inertia refers to the product of the weight multiplied by the distance between its centre of gravity and the reference point in the case of a multi-cylinder engine, the opposing weight can be a piston operating in the same way as the piston that it balances.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0017">The device according to the invention described in the application for French patent 01/13798 preferably uses this provision which is characterized in that the axis of the opposing cylinders and the fixed point of the pressure lever are essentially aligned along the same axis. It is characterized in that the pin for the control rod linked to the crankshaft is positioned, not on the pin common to the hinged arms but on the arm itself between the common pin and the fixed point or pivot. Therefore, the lower arm and its symmetry form a single arm swinging, essentially in its centre, on a pivot or fixed point with two pins at each of its free ends linked to the opposing pistons via connecting rods.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0018">In these types of engine operating with compressed air and comprising a high-pressure compressed air tank, the compressed air contained at high pressure in the tank has to be expanded but, as the tank is drained, the air pressure is reduced to a stable intermediary pressure known as the final use pressure in a buffer capacity prior to being used in the master cylinder(s). The conventional, well-known gate and spring pressure reducers have extremely low flowrates, and their use for this application requires extremely heavy-duty, inefficient appliances; plus the humidity in the air cooled during decompression is highly likely to cause them to ice up.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0019">The distribution system according to the invention which uses a cam, rocker arm and rocker arm rod assembly, on the one hand, acts as a variable flow pressure reducer, as a simplified camshaft-less control and as the drive system (chain, belt, pinion gears), and on the other hand, adjusts the lifting of the valve and the angular spread of the aforesaid opening from maximum lifting through to zero lifting thereby making it possible to ensure that the filling and/or draining flowrate of the cylinder in question is controlled and that the accelerator butterfly control is advantageously replaced. It is characterized in that the air supply in the final use buffer capacity and the supply to the cylinders are ensured by pilot valves where:
<ul id="ul0004" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0004-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0005" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0005-0001" num="0020">the cams of the aforementioned pilot valves, which are used to control the rocker arm rods, are positioned directly on the flanges of the crankshaft;</li>
        <li id="ul0005-0002" num="0021">the aforesaid cams activate one or more pressure levers which control the movement of the rocker arm rods.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0022">Each rocker arm, one end of which receives the driving thrust whilst the other activates the valve, pivots around a mobile pin that can move between the two ends thereof, thereby enabling the changing of the lever arm ratio which determines the lifting of the valve according to the movement of the rocker arm rod.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0023">When the swivel pin for the rocker arm is positioned close to the control rod, the lifting of the valve is at its maximum, when the pin is positioned halfway along, the lifting of the valve is equal to the movement of the control rod and when it is close to the valve, the lifting of the valve is less than the movement of the control rod.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0024">Preferably, the rocker arm is essentially in the shape of an arc of a circle, one end of which activates the valve whilst the other end is linked to the control rod, known as the rocker arm rod, and pivots around a mobile pin fitted with the means to enable it to move through the arc of a circle in a slotted hole, and according to an arc of an essentially concentric circle. This thereby enables the changing of the ratio of the aforesaid rocker arm lever arms which are located on either side of the mobile pin, and which thus determine the lifting of the valve according to the movement of the control rod.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0025">Preferably, the contact area of the aforesaid rocker arm on the valve is made up of an arc of a circle having as its axis the position of the rocker arm swivel pin when it is in its smallest possible opening position close to the valve thus enabling the rocker arm pivoting on the same pin to stop exerting pressure on the valve and keep the valve closed during the pivoting of the rocker arm.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0026">Advantageously, the rocker arm pin is moved by a yoke supporting the mobile pin. It is mounted on the same pin as the arc of the circle from the mobile pin slotted hole and is driven by mechanical, electrical or hydraulic means.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0027">This control can be directly linked to the accelerator pedal of the vehicle making it possible to gradually increase the lifting of the valve(s) and regulate the amount of gas let into the buffer capacity —whilst maintaining a constant pressure—then into the master cylinders.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0028">In the case of an electric control, for example by one or more stepper motors, the mechanical controls for the traditional accelerator can be removed and an electronic control unit used with a suitable cartography to control the lifting of the valves for all the selected parameters according to the pressure in the storage tank and the pressure in the buffer capacity, the position of the accelerator, the requested torque, the required speed or other conditions.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0029">The advantages of the distribution system according to the invention are then clear. In addition to its role of opening and closing the pipes, the distribution system makes it possible to replace the accelerator device customary to engines, by keeping the engine valve(s) closed so that they can then be opened via gradual lifting according to the required filling and/or draining needs, moreover the effort required by the opening device is proportional to the lifting of the valve.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0030">Preferably, and notably in the case of an opposed piston engine, the moving of the rocker arm rods is controlled by a pressure lever made up of two hinged arms, the common end of which comprises a means of contact, ball bearings or other, which is driven back by the cam housed on the flange of the crankshaft.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0031">The distribution system according to the invention particularly applies to compressed air engines. However, it can be used for traditional engines or compressors, in the same way that the rocker arm rod can be controlled by a camshaft, where the camshaft can directly activate the rocker arm.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<p id="p-0024" num="0032">Other objects, advantages and features of the invention will become apparent upon reading the nonlimiting description of a number of embodiments which are given with reference to the appended drawings where:</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a diagrammatic depiction in cross section of an engine fitted with the distribution system according to the invention when the valve lifting control is at its maximum, at the end of letting air in during filling.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> depicts this same engine during the expansion and exhaust strokes.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a detailed depiction of the distribution system on the same engine showing notably the kinematics of the rocker arm in its valve constantly closed position.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a detailed depiction of the distribution system whilst letting air in with the valve in a half-open position.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a detailed depiction of the distribution system in the opposing control position</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0038"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> depicts a variation of the rocker arm according to the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0039"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a diagrammatic depiction in cross section of the control device according to the invention adapted for a conventional engine with an overhead camshaft.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0040"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a diagrammatic depiction of an independent pressure reducing device for miscellaneous applications,</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0033" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> are diagrammatic depictions in cross section of the architecture for the moving elements of an engine fitted with the distribution system according to the invention comprising two essentially opposing pistons and cylinders on the same XX′ axis where it is possible to see the pistons <b>1</b> and <b>1</b>A equipped with their piston ring seals <b>3</b> and <b>3</b>A and sliding into their cylinder <b>4</b> and <b>4</b>A, each piston also comprising bosses <b>8</b> and <b>8</b>A making it possible to connect them via a pin, called the piston pin, <b>9</b> and <b>9</b>A to the crank piston rod system via the connecting rods <b>10</b> and <b>10</b>A, themselves connected via a common pin <b>11</b> and <b>11</b>A to the two free ends of an arm <b>12</b> mounted so that it swings, essentially in its centre, on a fixed pin <b>12</b>A, located essentially along the axis of the cylinders X,X′; the fixed pin <b>12</b>A thus divides the arm <b>12</b> into two half-arms <b>12</b>B and <b>12</b>C. On one of the two half-arms, here the <b>12</b>B, a control rod <b>13</b>, connected to the crankpin <b>13</b>A of a crankshaft <b>14</b> turning on its pin <b>15</b>, is attached via a pin <b>12</b>D. During the rotation (direction of the arrow) of the crankshaft, the control rod <b>13</b> applies a force to the pin <b>12</b>D, causing the swinging arm <b>12</b> to move, thus allowing the pistons <b>1</b> and <b>1</b>A to travel along the axis of the cylinders <b>4</b>, <b>4</b>A, or even the axis XX′ of the bottom dead centre (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) to the top dead centre (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>), and on its backstroke, it transmits the forces applied to the pistons <b>1</b> and <b>1</b>A during the power stroke from the top dead centre to the bottom dead centre to the crankshaft <b>14</b> thus generating the rotation of the aforesaid crankshaft. When the pistons are at their top dead centre (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) the connecting rods <b>10</b> and <b>10</b>A and the swinging arm <b>12</b> are essentially aligned along axis XX′. In this position the distance between the crankpin <b>13</b>A of the crankshaft and the axis XX′ is essentially identical during part of the rotation of the crankshaft thus controlling the travel of the pistons which remain stopped at their top dead centre for a significant angular sector of the crankshaft rotation.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0042">Advantageously, the rocker arm <b>20</b> is moved by a yoke <b>23</b> supporting the mobile pin <b>21</b>. It is mounted on the same pin as the arc of the circle from the mobile pin slotted hole and is driven by mechanical, electrical or hydraulic <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0043">This control can be directly linked to the accelerator pedal <b>42</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, of the vehicle making it possible to gradually increase the lifting of the valve(s) and regulate the amount of gas let into the buffer capacity—whilst maintaining a constant pressure—then into the master cylinders.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0044">In the case of the means <b>42</b> being an electric control, for example by one or more stepper motors, the mechanical controls for the traditional accelerator can be removed and an electronic control unit used with a suitable cartography to control the lifling of the valves for all the selected parameters according to the pressure in the storage tank <b>30</b> and the pressure in the buffer capacity <b>31</b>, the position of the <b>42</b>, the requested torque, the required speed or other conditions.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0045">The engine depicted is fitted with the distribution system according to the invention where it is possible to see the control cam <b>15</b>A housed on the flange <b>14</b>A of the crankshaft <b>14</b>. Along the periphery of the aforesaid crankshaft runs, on the one hand, a roller <b>17</b> which controls a rocker arm rod <b>19</b> which controls the pivoting of a rocker arm <b>20</b> around its mobile pin <b>21</b> that can move through the arc of a circle in a slotted hole <b>22</b> housed in the rocker arm when it is activated by a rotating, alternating control <b>23</b> which has the same radius and the same axis as the slotted hole <b>22</b>. This rocker arm controls the opening of a valve <b>24</b> to allow the opening and closing of the pipe <b>25</b> which links the high pressure storage tank <b>30</b> and the final use buffer capacity <b>31</b>; a return spring <b>26</b> allows the valve <b>24</b> to close when it is not being opened by the rocker arm <b>20</b>. And, along the periphery of the aforesaid crankshaft runs, on the other hand, a roller <b>17</b>A mounted on the common pin of a pressure lever made of two arms <b>18</b> and <b>18</b>A, the common ends of which are in the axis of the roller <b>17</b>, and the free ends of which are linked to two rocker arm rods <b>19</b>A and <b>19</b>B which control the pivoting of the rocker arms <b>20</b>A and <b>20</b>B around their mobile pin <b>21</b>A that can move through the arc of a circle in slotted holes <b>22</b>A and <b>22</b>B, housed in the rocker arms, when they are activated by their rotating, alternating controls <b>23</b>A, <b>23</b>B which have the same radius and the same axis as their slotted holes <b>22</b>A, <b>22</b>B. The rocker arms <b>20</b>A, <b>20</b>B control the opening of the valves <b>24</b>A and <b>24</b>B to allow the opening of the pipes <b>25</b>A, <b>25</b>B and the springs <b>26</b>A, <b>26</b>B are used to close the pipes <b>25</b>A, <b>25</b>B by returning the valves to their seating when they are no longer being opened by the rocker arms.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0046">When the pistons are at their top dead centre, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the rotation of the cam <b>15</b>A drives back the roller <b>17</b>A which activates the pressure lever arms <b>18</b> and <b>18</b>A so that they move the rocker arm rods <b>19</b> and <b>19</b>A in the direction of the arrows. The aforesaid rocker arm rods pivot the rocker arms <b>20</b>A and <b>20</b>B around the mobile pins <b>21</b>A and <b>21</b>B, driving back the valves <b>24</b>A and <b>24</b>B to let the compressed air from the pipes <b>25</b>A and <b>25</b>B into the cylinders <b>4</b> and <b>4</b>A. In this figure, the mobile pins <b>21</b>A and <b>21</b>B of the rocker arms are positioned as close as possible to the rocker arm rods in the slotted holes. Under these conditions, the distance between the mobile pin and the rocker arm rod thrust point is less than the distance between the mobile pin and the contact of the rocker arm on the valve, and the movement of the valves <b>24</b>A, <b>24</b>B will be greater than that of the rocker arm rods <b>19</b>A, <b>19</b>B, lifting the valves higher and improving the filling the cylinders.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0047">As the crankshaft continues to rotate. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the cam <b>15</b>A disappears in front of the roller <b>17</b> and the springs <b>26</b>A and <b>26</b>B return the valves to the closed position by driving back the rocker arms which, pivoting on their mobile pins <b>21</b>A, <b>21</b>B, drive back the rocker arm rods <b>19</b>A, <b>19</b>B and the pressure lever arms <b>18</b>, <b>18</b>A in the direction of the arrows, thus making it possible for the cylinder to close during the expansion and exhaust strokes (the exhaust system is not shown in these figures). In its rotation, the cam <b>15</b>A drives back the roller <b>17</b> which moves the rocker arm rod <b>19</b> in the direction of the arrow. This then pivots the rocker arm <b>20</b> around its mobile pin <b>21</b> driving back the valve <b>24</b> to let compressed air from the high pressure storage tank <b>30</b> through pipe <b>25</b> into the buffer capacity <b>31</b> at final use pressure enabling this capacity <b>31</b> to be maintained at a virtually constant pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a detailed diagrammatic depiction of a rocker arm and its control according to the invention, where the contact area of the rocker arm <b>20</b> on the pushrod <b>26</b>D of the stem of the valve <b>24</b>, forms an arc of a circle <b>27</b> with the same axis as the mobile pin <b>21</b> when it is positioned as close as possible to the valve <b>24</b>; when the rocker arm pivots around its mobile pin during the movement of the rocker arm rod <b>19</b>, position depicted by dotted lines, the contact area <b>27</b> of the rocker arm operates in a circle around the mobile pin <b>21</b> and does not generate any movement in the valve <b>24</b> thus keeping the pipe closed.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0049"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a detailed depiction of the elements of the distribution system according to the invention where the mobile pin <b>21</b> is positioned half-way between the contact point of the rocker arm rod <b>19</b> and the activation point <b>27</b> of the rocker arm on the valve <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0050">When the control <b>23</b> for the mobile pin <b>21</b> of the rocker arm <b>20</b> moves, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the ratio of the lever arms located on either side of the aforesaid mobile pin <b>21</b> determines a pivoting of the rocker arm <b>20</b> which opens the valve <b>24</b> according to the movement of the rocker arm rod <b>19</b>. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the swivel pin is shown essentially at the centre of the rocker arm and the lifting of the valve <b>24</b> is therefore essentially equal to the movement of the rocker arm rod <b>19</b>. It is therefore possible with this device to authorize valves to be gradually lifted; starting from zero lift which corresponds to the engine being turned off and finishing with maximum lift, defined by the geometric construction of the distribution system, thus piloting the engine according to requirements.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0051"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a detailed depiction of a variation of the elements of the distribution system according to the invention where the arc of the circle formed by the rocker arm <b>20</b> and the control <b>23</b> for the mobile pin <b>21</b> of the rocker arm <b>20</b> is in an opposing position to the valve <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0052"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> depicts a variation of the embodiment of a rocker arm according to the invention where the rocker arm <b>20</b> and its slotted hole <b>22</b> are rectilinear.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0053"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> depicts the distribution system according to the invention adapted for a traditional engine where it is possible to see in diagrammatic section a piston <b>1</b>B sliding into a cylinder <b>4</b>B, with an overlying combustion chamber wherein fits a spark plug <b>29</b>, fed by an inlet pipe <b>25</b>D and a valve <b>24</b>D) activated by a rocker arm <b>20</b>D pivoting around a mobile pin <b>21</b>D positioned in the slotted hole <b>22</b>D of the rocker arm. An overhead camshaft <b>15</b>D, driven by the engine at half crankshaft (not shown) speed, rotates thus giving a thrust to the rocker arm <b>20</b>D which pivoting on its mobile swivel pin <b>21</b>D activates the valve <b>24</b>D according to the laws governing opening for the engine in question. The device according to the invention as described above authorizes the engine to operate from off and/or idling mode through to its maximum speed by piloting the lifting of the valve by controlling the position of the mobile swivel pin <b>21</b>D for the rocker arm <b>20</b>D.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0054"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> depicts a dynamic variable flow pressure reducing device according to the invention where it is possible to see a compressed gas tank <b>30</b> linked to a use capacity <b>31</b> of this gas expanded to its use pressure, by a pipe <b>26</b> sealed by a valve <b>24</b>. The opening of the aforesaid valve is controlled by a device comprising a camshaft <b>16</b>D driven by an electric motor <b>1</b>E, and a rocker arm <b>20</b>D pivoting around a mobile pin <b>21</b>. The position of the aforesaid mobile pin, used to vary the lifting of the valve <b>24</b>, and consequently, the flowrate of the compressed air let in, is controlled by a yoke <b>23</b>. The rocker arm <b>20</b>D comprises a slotted hole <b>22</b>, wherein the mobile swivel pin <b>21</b> is mounted, The end of the aforesaid rocker arm <b>20</b>D furthest from the camshaft <b>15</b>D activates a valve <b>24</b> via a pushrod <b>26</b>D. During the rotation of the camshaft <b>15</b>D, the rocker arm <b>20</b>D pivots around its mobile pin <b>21</b> and opens the valve <b>24</b> authorizing an amount of the compressed air contained in the storage tank <b>30</b> to be let into the buffer capacity <b>31</b>. According to the pressures prevailing in the tank <b>30</b> and the capacity <b>31</b>, the lifting of the valve <b>24</b> will be regulated either to keep the valve closed for a zero flowrate, or to let a greater or lesser amount of compressed air into the capacity <b>31</b>, making it possible to maintain the required pressure in the latter,</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0055">The rotation speed of the electric engine <b>15</b>E for driving the camshaft <b>15</b>D will also be taken into account for improving the accuracy of the amount of compressed air let into the buffer capacity <b>31</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0056">The means for driving the camshaft <b>15</b>D, and controlling the yoke can be mechanical, electronic, hydraulic or other without changing the described invention in any way.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0057">The invention is not restricted to hew embodiments described and depicted: the equipment, the means of control, the devices described can vary subject to them being equivalent, and producing the same results, without changing the invention which has just been described hereinabove in any way.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A flow pressure reducer and distribution system for compressed air injection engines operating on mono or dual energy with a dual or triple supply mode and comprising:
<claim-text>a high-pressure compressed air tank;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a buffer capacity positioned in line with said high-pressure compressed air tank and arranged to supply compressed air to at least one piston;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first valve assembly arranged to regulate a supply of compressed air in said buffer capacity, said first valve assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a first valve;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first rocker arm rod arranged to be controlled by a cam positioned directly on a flange of a crankshaft; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first rocker arm arranged to receive driving thrust from said first rocker arm rod and arranged to activate said first valve, wherein said first valve is pivotable around a first mobile pin that is movable between two ends of said first rocker arm to change a lever arm ratio of said first valve and thereby determine lifting of said first valve according to movement of said first rocker arm rod; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one additional valve assembly arranged to regulate a supply of compressed air to said at least one piston, said at least one additional valve assembly comprising:
<claim-text>an additional valve;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an additional rocker arm rod arranged to be moved by a pressure lever that is controlled by said cam; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an additional rocker arm arranged to receive driving thrust from said additional valve rocker arm rod and arranged to activate said additional valve, wherein said additional valve is pivotable around an additional mobile pin that is movable between two ends of said additional rocker arm to change a lever arm ratio of additional rocker arm and thereby determine lifting of said additional valve according to movement of said additional rocker arm rod.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first rocker arm is essentially arc-shaped, and said first rocker arm has a first end which activates said first valve and a second end which is linked to said first rocker arm rod and pivots around said first mobile pin;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said first mobile pin is arranged to move in an arc-shaped slotted hole in said first rocker arm along a path that is essentially concentric with said first rocker arm;</claim-text>
<claim-text>said additional rocker arm is essentially arc-shaped, and said additional rocker arm has a first end which activates said additional valve and a second end which is linked to said additional rocker arm rod and pivots around said additional mobile pin; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said additional mobile pin is arranged to move in an arc-shaped slotted hole in said additional rocker arm along a path that is essentially concentric with said additional rocker arm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>a contact area of said first rocker arm on the first valve is made up of an arc of a circle having as its axis a position of said first mobile pin when said first rocker arm is in a position close to said first valve thus enabling said first rocker arm to pivot on said first mobile pin to stop exerting pressure on said first valve and keep said first valve closed during pivoting of said first rocker arm; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a contact area of said additional rocker arm on said additional valve is made up of an arc of a circle having as its axis a position of said additional mobile pin when said additional first rocker arm is in a position close to said additional valve thus enabling said additional rocker arm to pivot on said additional mobile pin to stop exerting pressure on said additional valve and keep said additional valve closed during pivoting of said additional rocker arm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first mobile pin is controlled by a first rotating, pivoting yoke supporting said first mobile pin and being mounted so as to have the same radius as said arc-shaped slotted hole in said first rocker arm; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said additional mobile pin is controlled by an additional rotating, pivoting yoke supporting said additional mobile pin and being mounted so as to have the same radius as said arc-shaped slotted hole in said additional rocker arm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. An appliance requiring compressed gas expansion, said appliance comprising the flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>a contact area of said first rocker arm on the first valve is made up of an arc of a circle having as its axis a position of said first mobile pin when said first rocker arm is in a position close to said first valve thus enabling said first rocker arm to pivot on said first mobile pin to stop exerting pressure on said first valve and keep said first valve closed during pivoting of said first rocker arm; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a contact area of said additional rocker arm on said additional valve is made up of an arc of a circle having as its axis a position of said additional mobile pin when said additional first rocker arm is in a position close to said additional valve thus enabling said additional rocker arm to pivot on said additional mobile pin to stop exerting pressure on said additional valve and keep said additional valve closed during pivoting of said additional rocker arm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first mobile pin is controlled by a first rotating, pivoting yoke supporting said first mobile pin and being mounted so as to have the same radius as said arc-shaped slotted hole in said first rocker arm; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said additional mobile pin is controlled by an additional rotating, pivoting yoke supporting said additional mobile pin and being mounted so as to have the same radius as said arc-shaped slotted hole in said additional rocker arm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An internal combustion engine comprising the flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first mobile pin is controlled by a first rotating, pivoting yoke supporting said first mobile pin and being mounted so as to have the same radius as said arc-shaped slotted hole in said first rocker arm; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>said additional mobile pin is controlled by an additional rotating, pivoting yoke supporting said additional mobile pin and being mounted so as to have the same radius as said arc-shaped slotted hole in said additional rocker arm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first rotating, pivoting yoke and said additional rotating, pivoting yoke are controlled by mechanical means directly linked to an accelerator making it possible to gradually supply said buffer capacity and engine cylinders according to required engine power.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. An internal combustion engine comprising the flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first rotating, pivoting yoke and said additional rotating, pivoting yoke are controlled by electric means and an electronic control system which takes into account pressure in the buffer capacity as well as pressure in the compressed air tank so as to maintain said pressure in said buffer capacity virtually constant.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. An internal combustion engine comprising he flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>said first rotating, pivoting yoke and said additional rotating, pivoting yoke are controlled via electric means and an electronic control system used with a suitable cartography to control lifting of said first valve and said additional valve for all selected parameters according to: a position of the accelerator, requested torque, required speed or other specified conditions.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. An internal combustion engine comprising the flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. An internal combustion engine comprising the flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A flow pressure reducer and distribution system for compressed air injection engines operating on mono or dual energy with a dual or triple supply mode and comprising:
<claim-text>a high-pressure compressed air tank;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a buffer capacity positioned in line with said high-pressure compressed air tank and arranged to supply compressed air to at least one piston;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first valve assembly arranged to regulate a supply of compressed air in said buffer capacity, said first valve assembly comprising:
<claim-text>a first valve; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first rocker arm controlled by a first overhead camshaft that is driven by mechanical means or other means linked to engine rotation, said first rocker arm having a first end arranged to receive driving thrust from a first cam on said first overhead camshaft and said first rocker arm having a second end arranged to activate said first valve, wherein said first rocker arm is pivotable about a first mobile pin that is movable between said first and second ends of said first rocker arm to change a lever arm ratio of said first rocker arm and thereby determine lifting of said first valve according to movement of said first rocker arm rod; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one additional valve assembly arranged to regulate a supply of compressed air to said at least one piston, said at least one additional valve assembly comprising:
<claim-text>an additional valve; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an additional rocker arm controlled by an additional overhead camshaft that is driven by said mechanical means or said other means linked to said engine rotation, said additional rocker arm having a first end arranged to receive driving thrust from an additional cam on said additional overhead camshaft and said additional rocker arm having a second end arranged to activate said additional valve, wherein said additional rocker arm is pivotable about an additional mobile pin that is movable between said first and second ends of said additional rocker arm to change a lever arm ratio of said additional rocker arm and thereby determine lifting of said additional valve according to movement of said additional rocker arm rod.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein said first camshaft and said additional camshaft are driven by an independent electric motor capable of being piloted by rotation speed.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. An appliance requiring compressed gas expansion, said appliance comprising the flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. An internal combustion engine comprising the flow pressure reducer and distribution system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
