<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296772-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296772</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11103855</doc-number>
<date>20050412</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>93205571 U</doc-number>
<date>20040412</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>37</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>47</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2483091</main-classification>
<further-classification>211 706</further-classification>
<further-classification>206349</further-classification>
<further-classification>248113</further-classification>
<further-classification>248339</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Hangtag for plaster trowel</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5906350</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kao</name>
<date>19990500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>248688</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6076669</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ling</name>
<date>20000600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206349</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6193200</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kao</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>2483091</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6637591</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Chen</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206349</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6672555</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Chang</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>248317</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6679379</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Kao</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206349</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0256530</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Wheeler et al.</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>248317</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0086636</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kuo</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206495</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>4</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2483091</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248317</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248339</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248689</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248113</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206349</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206378</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206  15</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>211 706</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050224673</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051013</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Wang</last-name>
<first-name>See-Tuh</first-name>
<address>
<street>No. 14, Jhenping St.</street>
<city>Fusing Township, Changhua County</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Egbert Law Offices</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ramirez</last-name>
<first-name>Ramon O</first-name>
<department>3632</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A special hangtag for plaster trowel, which is in flat shape, has a hanging hole on top. The limit section of the grip is placed in the middle of the hangtag, which can be lifted up forward, and the structure is designed to place the grip of the plaster trowel. On one side of the hole for supporting rod is a guiding slot coming from one side of the hangtag, which makes the supporting rod that is located between the grip and the low profile of the plaster trowel to be located in the hole for supporting rod from the guiding slot. Thus, the grip of the plaster trowel and the supporting rod are horizontally and vertically supported by the limit section of the grip and the hole for supporting rod, and forms a one-unit position with hangtag.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="151.55mm" wi="81.28mm" file="US07296772-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="177.38mm" wi="67.39mm" file="US07296772-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="180.51mm" wi="91.44mm" file="US07296772-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="180.51mm" wi="113.37mm" file="US07296772-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="183.56mm" wi="95.08mm" file="US07296772-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="189.40mm" wi="87.55mm" file="US07296772-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="191.43mm" wi="82.13mm" file="US07296772-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="194.48mm" wi="89.49mm" file="US07296772-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">RELATED U.S. APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">Not applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">STATEMENT REGARDING FEDERALLY SPONSORED RESEARCH OR DEVELOPMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Not applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">REFERENCE TO MICROFICHE APPENDIX</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Not applicable.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The present invention relates generally to a hangtag, and more particularly to a hangtag that is specially designed for plaster trowel.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Many products sold in the market today rely on the hangtag for display and management. Moreover, this type of hangtag is widely used with all kinds of hand tools and the products with related components, and the structure varies depending on the shape and feature of the product that is placed upon it. For instance, some hangtags are made with the combination of blister and paperboard with the product placed in it; some hangtags have holders for the handles of hand tools to clip. Even though there are many types of hangtags, however, there are many types of products as well, some of the products are still used without the design of the hangtags, for instance, the common hand tools like plaster trowel used in the construction is one of them. Because its unique appearance, it is still being displayed by placing it on the shelf, which is hard to get a better display effect and the best availability for space.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Thus, to overcome the aforementioned problems of the prior art, it would be an advancement if the art to provide an improved hangtag structure that is used specially for the product with special shapes that can significantly improve the efficacy.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The effects of the present invention are as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">1. Providing a hangtag that has limit section of the grip in the middle of the hangtag, and a hole for supporting rod is created on the bottom of the hangtag for the plaster trowel. This hangtag is indeed the first seen in the industry that meets the requirement for new patent.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">2. To assemble the plaster trowel <b>20</b> with the hangtag <b>10</b>, first force the supporting rod <b>23</b> of the plaster trowel <b>20</b> to go in the hole for the supporting rod <b>13</b> through the guiding slot <b>14</b>, and then lift up the limit section <b>12</b> of the grip of the plaster trowel to complete the assembling. To disassemble it, just do it backwards, therefore, it is easy and convenient to assemble as well as disassemble the unit.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The new effects of the present invention:</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">1. This hangtag <b>10</b> and plaster trowel <b>20</b> would still be in original condition, and the user can use the hangtag <b>10</b> to store the plaster trowel <b>20</b> when not using it. This advantage is obviously more advanced than the known blister hangtag.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">A through slot <b>15</b> is created on the hangtag <b>10</b>, so that when the limit section <b>12</b> of the grip of the U-shaped holder is restored, it would be back in the through hole <b>15</b>, and the hangtag <b>10</b> would in the flat position. By doing so, not only it can save its volume, but also save more storage space for the industry.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">2. The through slot <b>15</b> is created on the hangtag <b>10</b>, so that when the limit section <b>12</b> of the grip of the U-shaped holder is restored, it would be back in its structure, and the hangtag <b>10</b> would be in a flat position when not being used. By doing so, not only it can save its volume, but also save more storage space for the industry.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0007" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE SEVERAL VIEWS OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a perspective view of the hangtag in the first state.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a perspective view of the hangtag in the second state.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a perspective view of the hangtag and plaster trowel in an unassembled state.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> shows a perspective view of the hangtag and plaster trowel in an assembled state.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows another perspective view of the hangtag assembled onto the trowel.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6-9</figref> show partial perspective views of the embodiments of the supporting rod of the hangtag in the guiding slot to form the limit section.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The features and the advantages of the present invention will be more readily understood upon a thoughtful deliberation of the following detailed description of a preferred embodiment of the present invention with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, there is a hangtag for plaster trowel embodied in the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The invention includes a hangtag <b>10</b>, which is in flat shape, has a hanging hole <b>11</b> on the top, which can be hung on the hook in the market.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The limit section of the grip <b>12</b> that can be lifted up is placed in the middle of the hangtag <b>10</b>, and the shape of this limit section of the grip is made for the grip <b>21</b> of the plaster trowel. There is hole for supporting rod <b>13</b> placed between the bottom of hangtag <b>10</b> and the limit section <b>12</b> of the grip, and on one side of this hole for supporting rod <b>13</b> is a guiding slot <b>14</b> coming from one side of the hangtag <b>10</b>, which makes the supporting rod <b>23</b> that is located between the grip <b>21</b> and the low profile <b>22</b> of the plaster trowel to be placed in the hole for the supporting rod <b>13</b> from the guiding slot <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Thus, the grip <b>21</b> of the plaster trowel <b>20</b> and the supporting rod <b>23</b> are placed horizontally and vertically with the limitation from the limit section <b>12</b> of the grip and the hole for supporting rod <b>13</b>, and forms a unit position with hangtag <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The limit section <b>12</b> of the grip is a U-shaped holder that is attached to the hangtag <b>10</b> by the thin film <b>121</b> on both ends, and the surrounding frame <b>122</b> of this U-shaped holder can be lifted up easily. A through slot <b>15</b> is created on the hangtag <b>10</b> that when the limit section <b>12</b> of the grip of the U-shaped holder is restored, it would be back in the through hole <b>15</b>, and the hangtag <b>10</b> would be in the flat position. By doing so, not only it can save its volume, but also save more storage space for the industry.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The width of the guiding slot <b>14</b> of the supporting hole <b>13</b> is smaller than the supporting rod <b>23</b> of the plaster trowel <b>20</b>, and the direction of the guiding slot <b>14</b> is going up to one side of hangtag in an angle, therefore, the supporting rod <b>23</b> of the plaster trowel <b>20</b> must be forced to go through the guiding slot <b>14</b>, so when the supporting rod <b>23</b> is clipped in the supporting rod hole <b>13</b>, it can not be pushed out from the guiding slot <b>14</b> easily, which is in a secure position.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Through the above structure and design, the operation of the assembling and disassembling of the unit disclosed by the present is explained as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">To assemble the plaster trowel <b>20</b> with the hangtag <b>10</b>, first force the supporting rod <b>23</b> of the plaster trowel <b>20</b> to go in the supporting rod hole <b>13</b> through the guiding slot <b>14</b>, then lift up the surrounding frame <b>122</b> of the limit section <b>12</b> of the grip and place the grip <b>21</b> of the plaster trowel <b>20</b> inside the frame limitation, this way, the plaster trowel <b>20</b> receives the restrictive effect horizontally and vertically, and it is combined with the hangtag <b>10</b> in one. Moreover, when the user buys the plaster trowel <b>20</b>, all he needs to do is lifting up the surrounding frame <b>122</b> of the limit section <b>12</b> of the grip to move the grip <b>21</b> of the plaster trowel <b>20</b> off the fixed position, and forces the supporting rod <b>23</b> out from the hole for the supporting rod <b>13</b> through the guiding slot <b>14</b>. By doing so, separate the plaster trowel <b>20</b> and the hangtag <b>10</b> easily and quickly, and the hangtag <b>10</b> would still be in original condition, and the user can use the hangtag <b>10</b> to store the plaster trowel <b>20</b> when not using it. This advantage is obviously more advanced than the known blister hangtag.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a three dimensional figure of the hangtag <b>10</b> of this invention combined with the plaster trowel <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The location of the guiding slot <b>14</b> of this supporting rod hole <b>13</b> has the stopper that can block that guiding slot <b>14</b> (see later part for detail). By adding this stopper, it would help the plaster trowel <b>20</b> from coming loose (from the hangtag <b>10</b>) after it is put up, this way, it can secure the plaster trowel in this position when it is being displayed in the market, and it would not be easily stolen by thieves. There are also several styles of that stopper, the examples are described as follows:</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, through holes <b>16</b> can be made from both sides of guiding slot <b>14</b> as well as a U-shaped locating pin <b>30</b>, and set the snap <b>31</b> on both ends, and clip it to the through holes <b>16</b> mentioned above to block the guiding slot <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, same through holes <b>16</b> can be made from both sides of guiding slot <b>14</b> to block the guiding slot <b>14</b> through stringing <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, staple <b>50</b> the opening the guiding slot <b>14</b> to block the guiding slot <b>14</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, placing removable panel <b>61</b> that has clip bolt <b>60</b> on one side of the guiding slot <b>14</b>, and make a clip hole <b>62</b> on the other side of the guiding slot <b>14</b>, by doing so, the clip bolt <b>60</b> is clipped to the clip hole <b>62</b>, so that the removable panel <b>61</b> blocks the guiding slot <b>14</b>.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An article for receiving a handle of a plastic trowel, the handle having a supporting rod extending therefrom, the article comprising:
<claim-text>a hangtag having a flat shape;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first hole formed at a top of said hangtag;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a grip positioned in a middle of said hangtag, said grip movable upwardly and forwardly such that an interior of said grip can receive the handle of the plastic trowel therein; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second hole formed on said hangtag between a bottom of said hangtag and said grip, said second hole suitable for receiving the supporting rod therein, said second hole having a guiding slot extending to one side of said hangtag, said guiding slot allowing the supporting rod to pass therethrough and into said second hole.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The article of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, said grip having a U-shape in which a pair of legs of said U-shape have respective ends that are flexibly affixed to said hangtag, said hangtag having a slotted area formed in a surface thereof, said grip received within said slotted area.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The article of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, said guiding slot having a width dimension that is less than a diameter dimension of the supporting rod, said guiding slot extending angularly upwardly toward said one said of said hangtag.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The article of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a stop affixed to said hangtag and extending across said guiding slot.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
