<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296365-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296365</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11604413</doc-number>
<date>20061127</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 33613</main-classification>
<further-classification> 33644</further-classification>
<further-classification> 33655</further-classification>
<further-classification> 33832</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Method and system for inserting a probe</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6195577</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Truwit et al.</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>600411</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6694832</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Gleeson</name>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 738665</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7188433</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Boge et al.</name>
<date>20070300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 33706</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7261796</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Byrnes et al.</name>
<date>20070800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 33613</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0115095</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kurfiss et al.</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 33613</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 33613</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 33644-645</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 33655</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 33719</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 33832</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 33836</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>St. Louis</last-name>
<first-name>Robert T.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Greenville</city>
<state>SC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jacobs</last-name>
<first-name>Tyler</first-name>
<address>
<city>Greenville</city>
<state>SC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Marquez</last-name>
<first-name>Elias</first-name>
<address>
<city>Queretaro</city>
<country>MX</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>MX</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>MX</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Channell</last-name>
<first-name>Heidi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Easley</city>
<state>SC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Davis</last-name>
<first-name>Dale J.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Cusick</last-name>
<first-name>Ernest G.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Landgraff</last-name>
<first-name>Frank</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>General Electric Company</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Schenectady</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Guadalupe-McCall</last-name>
<first-name>Yaritza</first-name>
<department>2859</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A system for inserting a probe into a turbomachine. The system may include a male measurement fixture having a shaft and a female portion a housing for receiving the male measurement fixture. The male measurement fixture may include: a tip portion, an indicator, and a target zone.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="166.54mm" wi="242.65mm" file="US07296365-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="242.82mm" wi="173.06mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296365-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="245.79mm" wi="157.14mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296365-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="179.15mm" wi="166.29mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296365-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="230.29mm" wi="84.33mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296365-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="255.27mm" wi="114.64mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296365-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="180.93mm" wi="165.27mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296365-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application relates generally to a combustion system on a turbomachine; and more particularly to, a method and system for inserting a continuous dynamics monitoring probe about a combustion liner on a combustion gas turbine.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">As part of the monitoring controls and diagnostic tools for a combustion system in a gas turbine, combustion dynamics data is typically measured and acquired. The combustion dynamics data is generally used to determine the operational health of the combustion system as a whole and also may be used to tune the combustion system to ensure operation within an appropriate balance between combustion dynamics and emissions.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Combustion dynamics monitoring systems are currently used on many classes of gas turbines. A dependable combustion measurement generally requires accurate and repeatable installation of the measurement tip of the dynamic probe of the combustion dynamics monitoring system. Improperly installed dynamics probes can lead to inaccurate readings of the combustor dynamics, possibly resulting in hardware damage and increased outages. Combustion dynamics monitoring systems typically use a depth-setting tool that assists with an accurate and repeatable installation of the dynamic probe.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">There are a few possible problems with the currently known depth-setting tools. The combustion liner and flow sleeve designs vary among combustion systems. This requires a different depth setting tool for certain combustion systems. For example, but not limiting of the invention, some known depth setting tools cannot work with the combustion systems of certain combustion gas turbines sold by General Electric Company of Schenectady, N.Y. Specifically, these combustion systems include a movable ferrule located on a female bung that is attached to the combustion liner. The movable ferrule allows for current depth-setting tools to derive an inaccurate measurement of the required length of dynamics probe.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">For the foregoing reasons, there is a need for a depth-setting tool that can accommodate the geometry of certain classes of turbines. The depth-setting tool should provide an accurate and repeatable installation of a combustion dynamics monitoring system probe and similar types of probes. The tool should include a taper about a tip that allows a user to easily manipulate the movable ferrule, thereby allowing for accurate placement of the tool within the flow sleeve and combustion liner. The tool should also include a tip appropriately sized to compensate for the differing dimensions of gas turbines. The tool should also include a target zone that ensures that the tool is properly inserted in the combustion can.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In accordance with an embodiment of the present invention, a system for inserting a probe into a turbomachine, the system comprising: a male measurement fixture for inserting into at least one wall of the turbomachine, the male measurement fixture measures a probe insertion depth and comprises: a shaft, wherein the shaft includes a tip portion provided at a distal end of the shaft, and wherein the tip portion includes a taper near a distal end of the tip; at least one indicator for indicating the probe insertion depth on the shaft; at least one target zone for determining whether the male measurement fixture is correctly positioned within the at least one wall.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The system also comprises a female measurement fixture for transferring the probe insertion depth from the male measurement fixture to a probe holder device, the female measurement fixture comprises a housing defining a receptacle for receiving the shaft and the tip portion, wherein the receptacle is selectively adjustable to correspond to the probe insertion depth, and wherein the housing can receive the probe holder device in a manner to set the probe insertion depth on the probe holder device.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWING</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic illustrating the environment in which an embodiment of the present invention operates.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic exploded view, partly in cross-section, of a male measurement fixture in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a schematic illustration of the step of measuring a target probe depth using the male measurement fixture of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a schematic exploded view, partly in cross-section, of a female measurement fixture in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic view in cross-section showing the transfer of the probe insertion depth from a male measurement fixture to a female measurement fixture in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a schematic in cross-section showing the transfer of the target probe depth from a female measurement fixture to a probe holder device in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a schematic illustration of the probe holder device installed in a gas turbine combustion can.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Certain terminology is used herein for convenience only and is not to be taken as a limitation on the invention. For example, words such as “upper,” “lower,” “left,” “right,” “horizontal,” “vertical,” “upward,” and “downward” merely describe the configuration shown in the Figures. Indeed, the components may be oriented in any direction and the terminology, therefore, should be understood as encompassing such variations unless specified otherwise.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">A probe holder device is a generic phrase for a combustion dynamics monitoring system assembly, which includes a probe that is positioned about the gas flow path within the combustion system. The probe holder device coupling is a generic phrase for a coupling or mounting hardware that secures the combustion dynamics monitoring assembly to a combustion can. In a combustion gas turbine (hereinafter turbine), the combustion dynamics monitoring (hereinafter CDM) probe assemblies should be mounted to the combustion can so that the probe tips are all disposed at a specific probe insertion depth. The probe insertion depth is the distance between the inside of the combustion liner and the combustion flow path, and is measured relative to a combustion liner surface. The probe insertion depth should be identical across all CDM probes used in the turbine.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">To provide for reliable, repeatable probe insertions depths, an embodiment of the present invention includes a kit for determining the probe insertion depth relative to a combustor casing wall, a flow sleeve wall, and a liner wall. The kit includes a male measurement fixture (MMF) <b>150</b> (shown, for example, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) for measuring the probe insertion depth, and a female measurement fixture (FMF) <b>300</b> (shown, for example, in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>) for transferring the probe insertion depth to the CDM probe assembly <b>400</b>. The MMF includes a tip portion <b>225</b> corresponding in axial length to probe insertion depth.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Referring now to the figures, where the various numbers represent like parts throughout the several views, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic illustrating the environment in which an embodiment of the present invention operates. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a turbine <b>100</b> includes a plurality of combustion cans <b>110</b>. Each combustion can <b>110</b> comprises a first casing wall <b>120</b>, a second flow sleeve wall <b>130</b>, and a third liner wall <b>140</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> also illustrates the MMF <b>150</b> inserted in the combustion can <b>110</b> for determining the probe insertion depth. As discussed, the probe insertion depth is determined relative to the liner wall <b>140</b> and the combustion flow path <b>550</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> further illustrates that the method of the present invention affixes the CDM assembly <b>400</b> to each combustion can <b>110</b> at the proper probe insertion depth.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, which is a schematic exploded view, partly in cross-section, of a male measurement fixture (MMF) <b>150</b> in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention. The MMF <b>150</b> includes a shaft <b>160</b>, a head <b>170</b>, and a lock nut <b>240</b> for locking a measurement barrel <b>250</b> in a target position.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The shaft <b>160</b> may be an elongated body extending from the shoulder <b>215</b>, defined by the difference in diameters of the shaft <b>160</b> and the tip portion <b>225</b>, to the head <b>170</b>. The tip portion <b>225</b> may be adapted to span the distance between a reference surface to an access/insertion point that is remote from the reference surface e.g., from the liner wall <b>140</b> through the flow sleeve wall <b>130</b>, and through the casing wall <b>120</b>, and beyond a casing coupling <b>125</b> provided on the casing wall <b>120</b> for coupling the CDM assembly <b>400</b> to the casing wall <b>120</b> (the aforementioned is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). For example, but not limiting of the invention, the casing coupling <b>125</b> used for access/insertion point may be a Swagelok® (Swagelok is a registered trademark of Swagelok corporation of Solon, Ohio) fitting, or the like. However, the present invention is not intended to be limited to only those types of coupling devices.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The tip portion <b>225</b> may correspond in axial length to a desired or target probe insertion depth inwardly with respect to a reference surface, which in the present embodiment is the outer surface <b>145</b> of the liner wall <b>140</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). The tip portion <b>225</b> includes a taper <b>230</b> that aids the user in manipulating the movable ferrule assembly <b>500</b> that may rest on the female bung <b>525</b>, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The length of the tip portion <b>225</b> may be fixed or, if adjustment is desired, the length may be varied. For example, but not limiting of the invention, a specific length may be required for a certain gas turbine having a distinct combustion system, and a different length may required for the same gas turbine having a second distinct combustion system. The length may be changed, for example, but not limiting of the invention, by providing a threaded tip portion that may be lengthened or shortened; alternatively interchangeable tip portions may also be used to change the length.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">The shaft <b>160</b> also includes an unthreaded portion <b>190</b> and may comprise a target zone <b>195</b>, an upper limit <b>200</b>, and a lower limit <b>205</b>. The unthreaded portion extends from the shoulder <b>215</b> to the threaded portion <b>180</b>. The target zone <b>195</b> allows a user to clearly gauge whether the MMF fixture <b>150</b> is properly inserted in the combustion can <b>110</b>. Hence, the target zone <b>195</b> may determine whether the operator is correctly measuring the probe insertion depth. The breadth of the target zone <b>195</b> may be bound an upper limit <b>200</b> and a lower limit <b>205</b>. For ease of use, the upper limit <b>200</b> and the lower limit <b>205</b> may be machined into the unthreaded portion <b>190</b>. For example, but not limiting of the invention, if an operator, after inserting the MMF <b>150</b> into a combustion can <b>110</b>, can see both the upper limit <b>200</b> and the lower limit <b>205</b>, then a portion of the MMF <b>150</b> may be caught on either the flow sleeve wall <b>130</b> or on the movable ferrule assembly <b>500</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). Moreover, if an operator cannot see the upper limit <b>200</b> and the lower limit <b>205</b>, then the MMF <b>150</b> may be inserted too far and the shoulder <b>215</b> may be resting on a sloped side (not shown) of the movable ferrule assembly <b>500</b>. It is to be understood, however, that if the target zone <b>195</b> is indicated, recorded or marked on the MMF <b>150</b> in another manner, such as by noting indicia or solely by the position of the distal face of the measurement barrel <b>250</b>, then the threaded portion <b>180</b> may extended along a greater extent of the shaft <b>160</b> length or along substantially the entire length of the shaft <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The measurement barrel <b>250</b> has an inner bore including a barrel smooth surface portion <b>260</b> and a barrel threaded portion <b>255</b>. The barrel smooth surface portion <b>260</b> is provided to slidably engage the unthreaded portion <b>190</b> of the shaft <b>160</b>, whereas the barrel threaded portion <b>255</b> is adapted to threadably engage the threaded portion <b>180</b> of the shaft <b>160</b>. Providing a barrel smooth surface portion <b>260</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, limits the proximal displacement of the measurement barrel <b>250</b> with respect to the unthreaded portion <b>190</b> of the shaft <b>160</b>. It is to be understood, however, that the inner diameter of the barrel smooth portion <b>260</b> may be an optional feature of the MMF <b>150</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In an embodiment of the present invention, the MMF <b>150</b> is about 8 inches long, the tip portion <b>225</b> is from about 0.37 to about 1.25 inches long, and the threaded portion <b>180</b> is about 2.5 inches long. Furthermore, in an embodiment of the present invention, the diameter of the tip portion <b>225</b> is about 0.3 inches and the diameter of the unthreaded portion <b>190</b> is about 0.8 inches.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">A head <b>170</b> is provided at the proximal end of the MMF <b>150</b> for retaining the measurement barrel <b>250</b> and lock nut <b>240</b> on the shaft <b>160</b>. In a non-limiting embodiment of the present invention, the head <b>170</b> has an outer diameter of about 1.2 inches, however, the head <b>170</b> may have an outer diameter of any size, and may have a knurled surface to facilitate handling.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The measurement barrel <b>250</b> may advantageously have a total length generally corresponding to the length of the threaded portion <b>180</b>. The barrel threaded portion <b>255</b> is generally an inner bore of the measurement barrel <b>250</b> threaded less than the total length of the measurement barrel <b>250</b> by an amount generally corresponding to the length of the lock nut <b>240</b>. For example, but not limiting of the invention, if the lock nut <b>240</b> has a length of about 0.3 inches, the barrel-threaded portion <b>255</b> is about 1.7 inches. Here, when the measurement barrel <b>250</b> is fully engaged with the threaded portion of the MMF <b>150</b> and the lock nut <b>240</b> is interposed between the measurement barrel <b>250</b> and the head <b>170</b> of the shaft <b>160</b>, the threaded portion <b>180</b> may be fully covered and the measurement barrel <b>250</b> should project distally from the threaded portion <b>180</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, which is a schematic illustration of the step of measuring a probe insertion depth using the MMF <b>150</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention. Here, the MMF <b>150</b> is inserted through the casing coupling <b>125</b> opening provided on the combustor can <b>110</b> to dispose the tip portion <b>225</b> near the outer surface <b>145</b> defined in the combustion liner wall <b>140</b>. The MMF <b>150</b> is advanced until the shoulder <b>215</b> engages the movable ferrule <b>500</b>, which may be connected to the female bung <b>525</b>. Here, and as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, an aft end of the measurement barrel <b>250</b> may engage a distal end of the connection <b>310</b>, and the aft end of the connector <b>310</b> may engage at least one distal surface of the casing coupling <b>125</b>. As discussed, the tip portion <b>225</b> advantageously has a length corresponding to the distance that the CDM tip <b>420</b> desirably extends inwardly from the outer surface <b>145</b> of the liner wall <b>140</b>. This distance will generally correspond to the liner wall <b>140</b> thickness.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The measured probe insertion depth is then indicated, recorded, or marked on the MMF <b>150</b> at a predetermined point with respect to the combustor casing wall <b>120</b>. Thus, once the MMF <b>150</b> is inserted so that the shoulder <b>215</b> abuts the movable ferrule assembly <b>500</b>, the measurement barrel <b>250</b> is rotated to advance distally. After the measurement barrel <b>250</b> is in position to indicate the probe insertion depth, the lock nut <b>240</b> is advanced distally to lock the measurement barrel <b>250</b> in place. The outer surfaces of the measurement barrel <b>250</b> and lock nut <b>240</b> may be knurled to facilitate manipulation.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">It is to be understood that the MMF <b>150</b> may be marked to indicate the probe insertion depth. For example, but not limiting the invention, indicia may be applied to the MMF <b>150</b> as by applying a physical mark, tape, or the like to indicate the determined probe insertion depth with respect to the combustor casing wall <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, which is a schematic exploded view, partly in cross-section, of a female measurement fixture (FMF) <b>300</b> in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention. The FMF <b>300</b> is provided for transferring the probe insertion depth as determined by the MMF <b>150</b> ultimately to the CDM probe assembly <b>400</b>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the FMF <b>300</b> includes at a first, open end thereof, a connector <b>310</b> corresponding to the casing coupling <b>125</b> provided on the combustor casing wall <b>120</b>, shown for example in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. The FMF <b>300</b> includes a receptacle <b>320</b> having an adjustable cavity area to correspond to the probe insertion depth as determined by the MMF <b>150</b>. In an embodiment of the present invention, the size of the cavity in the receptacle <b>320</b> may be adjusted by the adjustment bolt <b>360</b>, which is threadably engaged within the housing <b>330</b>. The adjustment bolt <b>360</b> includes an adjustment head <b>370</b>, which may include a knurled surface. The adjustment head <b>370</b> may be used to facilitate the displacement of the adjustment bolt <b>360</b> with respect to the housing <b>330</b>. A lock ring <b>350</b> is further provided for locking the adjustment bolt <b>360</b> with respect to the housing <b>330</b>. The housing <b>330</b> may include at least one flat face <b>340</b> for clamping the housing <b>330</b> to a structure during use.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, which is a schematic view in cross-section showing the transfer of the probe insertion depth from a male measurement fixture to a female measurement fixture in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention. The MMF <b>150</b> set to the probe insertion depth is slidably inserted through the connector structure <b>310</b> into the MMF <b>300</b> until the indicator thereof is aligned with a complimentary portion or feature provided on the connector <b>310</b>. In an embodiment of the present invention, the measurement barrel <b>250</b> is used to the mark probe insertion depth on the MMF <b>150</b>. The adjustment bolt <b>360</b> is then adjusted so that the tip portion <b>230</b> of the MMF <b>150</b> engages the adjust bolt <b>360</b>. The lock ring <b>350</b> is then tightened to lock the new position of the adjustment bolt <b>360</b>. This new position is the probe insertion depth position as transferred from the MMF <b>150</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">After the lock ring <b>350</b> locks the position of the adjustment bolt <b>360</b>, the MMF <b>150</b> may be removed so the FMF <b>300</b> can mark the probe insertion depth on the CDM probe assembly <b>400</b>. More particularly, referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, which is a schematic in cross-section showing the transfer of the probe insertion depth from the FMF <b>300</b> to a CDM probe assembly <b>400</b> in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention. The CDM probe assembly <b>400</b> is inserted through the connector structure <b>310</b> such that the CDM tip <b>420</b> abuts the adjustment bolt <b>360</b>. While the CDM probe assembly <b>400</b> is so disposed, at least one ferrule <b>425</b> and at least one collar <b>430</b> is displaced so as to align with the connector <b>310</b> of the FMF <b>330</b>. The CDM connector assembly <b>415</b> may then be tightened to lock the at least one ferrule <b>425</b> in place at the correct position on the CDM shaft <b>410</b>. With the probe insertion depth recorded or marked on the CDM probe assembly <b>400</b>, the connector <b>310</b> can be released and the assembly <b>400</b> removed for engagement in due course with the combustion casing wall <b>120</b>. Since the ferrule <b>425</b> has been locked in position on the CDM shaft <b>410</b>, when the CDM probe assembly <b>400</b> is inserted through the casing coupling <b>125</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, engagement of the at least one locked ferrule <b>425</b> and the at least one collar <b>430</b>, with the casing coupling <b>125</b> indicates that the CDM tip <b>420</b> is properly disposed with respect to the liner wall <b>140</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Although the present invention has been shown and described in considerable detail with respect to only a few exemplary embodiments thereof, it should be understood by those skilled in the art that we do not intend to limit the invention to the embodiments since various modifications, omissions and additions may be made to the disclosed embodiments without materially departing from the novel teachings and advantages of the invention, particularly in light of the foregoing teachings. Accordingly, we intend to cover all such modifications, omission, additions and equivalents as may be included within the spirit and scope of the invention as defined by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A system for inserting a probe into a turbomachine, the system comprising:
<claim-text>a male measurement fixture for inserting into at least one wall of the turbomachine, the male measurement fixture measures a probe insertion depth and comprises:
<claim-text>a shaft, wherein the shaft includes a tip portion provided at a distal end of the shaft, and wherein the tip portion includes a taper near a distal end of the tip;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one indicator for indicating the probe insertion depth on the shaft;</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one target zone for determining whether the male measurement fixture is correctly positioned within the at least one wall; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a female measurement fixture for transferring the probe insertion depth from the male measurement fixture to a probe holder device, the female measurement fixture comprises a housing defining a receptacle for receiving the shaft and the tip portion, wherein the receptacle is selectively adjustable to correspond to the probe insertion depth, and wherein the housing can receive the probe holder device in a manner to set the probe insertion depth on the probe holder device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the tip portion has a diameter less than the shaft.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising a shoulder defined between the tip portion and the shaft.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the indicator comprises a measurement barrel mounted to the shaft, and wherein the measurement barrel functions to be selectively axially shifted on the shaft.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising a lock nut for locking the measurement barrel in position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the shaft includes an unthreaded portion and a threaded portion, and wherein the measurement barrel is disposed on the threaded portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the indicator comprises at least one ferrule slidably disposed on the shaft and at least one collar slidably disposed on the shaft.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one ferrule and the at least one collar are slidably disposed on the unthreaded portion of the shaft.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the taper aids with the insertion of the tip into the at least one wall of the turbomachine.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the taper maneuvers a movable ferrule attached to a female bung, and wherein the female bung is attached to the at least one wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the at least one wall comprises a first liner wall, a second flow sleeve wall, and a third casing wall and wherein the tip portion of the male measurement fixture has a length corresponding to a target length of a probe tip as determined inwardly from an outer surface of the liner wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the tip portion comprises a length of about 0.370 inches (about 9.398 millimeters) to about 1.250 inches (about 19.05 millimeters).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a connection coupling located near an open end of the receptacle of the female measurement fixture, wherein the connection coupling corresponds to a probe holder device coupling provided on it least one wall.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the target zone is bounded by at least two limiters.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the at least two limiters are machined into the shaft.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein an axial depth bolt adjustably mounted to the housing determines a depth of the receptacle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the tip portion comprises a variable length.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, wherein the tip portion comprises a threaded portion, and wherein the threaded portion is used to set the length of the tip portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the tip portion comprises a distinct length.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref>, wherein a second tip portion comprises a second distinct length replaces the tip portion.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
