<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297916-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297916</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11064346</doc-number>
<date>20050222</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>62</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>27</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>225</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2502081</main-classification>
<further-classification>348340</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Optically improved CMOS imaging sensor structure to lower imaging lens requirements</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5796154</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sano et al.</name>
<date>19980800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257432</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6111247</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Sengupta</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>250226</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6362513</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Wester</name>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257432</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6577342</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Wester</name>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348340</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0173599</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Nakai</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257225</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0165097</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Drowley et al.</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348340</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2502081</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257225</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348340</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438 70</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>8</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Feng</last-name>
<first-name>Chen</first-name>
<address>
<city>Bothell</city>
<state>WA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Greenberg Traurig, LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>MagnaChip Semiconductor, Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Chungcheongbuk-Do</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Epps</last-name>
<first-name>Georgia</first-name>
<department>2878</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Wyatt</last-name>
<first-name>Kevin</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A sensor die that lowers the lens requirements by the use of a variable thickness distribution over the sensor die. The sensing portion of the sensor die has a different number of layers than the non-sensing portion of the sensor die. By reducing the thickness of each layer and/or eliminating one or more unnecessary layers in the sensing portion, the thickness of the sensing portion is reduced to lower the amount of stray light and allow an increase in chief ray angle as well as a decrease in the F-number of the imaging system coupled to the sensor die without compromising the image quality of the sensor die. Also, the thickness reduction provides the design engineers with extra allowance in handling the chief ray angle and F-number for a given lens requirements.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="93.81mm" wi="185.08mm" file="US07297916-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="152.65mm" wi="121.24mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297916-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="241.72mm" wi="189.31mm" file="US07297916-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="179.41mm" wi="105.24mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297916-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="234.95mm" wi="184.15mm" file="US07297916-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="187.11mm" wi="120.90mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297916-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to CMOS image sensor design and more particularly to lowering imaging lens requirements of CMOS image sensors.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Background of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">There has been an increase of digital image devices using CMOS image sensors. A conventional CMOS image sensor requires a matching imaging lens unit which includes one or more lens elements to direct incoming light to its sensor surface and generate an image on the sensor. In general, the chief ray angle for a pixel at the center of the sensor surface is zero, while the chief ray angles for pixels at corners and/or edges of the sensor surface reach to a considerable amount. To mitigate the negative effects of large chief ray angles and consequently generate a uniform image over the entire sensor surface, the imaging system of the CMOS image sensor may be customized under given imaging lens requirements.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In general, the imaging lens requirements may refer to the limitations on the number of lens elements and size of the imaging lens unit (assembly). A complex imaging lens unit having multi lenses may require a complicated optical design and a high manufacturing cost. Thus, it is desirable to minimize the number of imaging lens elements without degrading the performance of the imaging system.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The overall physical dimension of the imaging system may determine the size of imaging lens unit. Thus, the lens size requirement may become more significant as the size of the imaging device decreases as in typical mobile applications. For this reason, the mobile sensor device engineers often make significant efforts to minimize the lens size without compromising the performance of the imaging system.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">However, the conventional approaches to change the number of lens elements and size of the imaging lens unit in an effort to lower the lens requirements may encounter additional difficulties as these requirements may be accompanied by a considerable amount of alteration and customization of the entire CMOS image sensor layout. Thus, there is a need for an improved methodology that lowers the lens requirements without modifying the overall imaging system significantly and compromising the image quality and performance of the sensor.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention provides a sensor die that lowers the lens requirements by the use of a variable thickness distribution over the sensor die. The sensing portion of the sensor die has a different number of layers than the non-sensing portion of the sensor die. Also, by reducing the thickness of each layer and/or eliminating one or more unnecessary layers in the sensing portion, the thickness of the sensing portion is reduced to provide the design engineers with extra allowance in handling chief ray angles and F-number of the imaging system without compromising the image quality of the sensor die.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In one aspect of the present invention, a sensor die includes: a sensing potion having a plurality of pixels, each of the plurality of pixels having a first set of layers and a microlens; and a non-sensing portion having a second set of layers, the second set of layers having a different number of layers than the first set of layers.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In another aspect of the present invention, a sensor die formed on a substrate having a plurality of passive components includes: a sensing potion including a plurality of pixels, each of the plurality of pixels having a microlens and a first set of layers that comprises: a photodiode partially embedded on the substrate; a first insulting layer on top of the photodiode and the substrate; a plurality of metal layers on top of the first insulating layer, the photodiode and the plurality of passive components connected to at least one of the plurality of metal layers; a plurality of middle insulating layers, each of the plurality of metal layers sandwiched by corresponding two of the plurality of middle insulating layers; a passivation layer on top of the plurality of middle insulating layers; a color filter; and a planar layer on top of the color filter; and a non-sensing portion having a second set of layers, the second set of layers having a different number of layers than the first set of layers.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In yet another aspect of the present invention, an imaging device includes a sensor die that comprises: a sensing potion including a plurality of pixels, each of the plurality of pixels having a first set of layers and a microlens; and a non-sensing portion having a second set of layers, the second set of layers having at least one more layer than the first set of layers. The imaging device further includes an imaging lens unit that includes one or more lens elements to direct incoming light to the sensor die.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In still another aspect of the present invention, a sensor die includes: a sensing potion comprising a plurality of pixels, each of the plurality of pixels having a first set of layers and a microlens; and a non-sensing portion having a second set of layers, the thickness of the second set of layers being larger than that of the first set of layers.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">These and other features, aspects and advantages of the present invention will become better understood with reference to the following drawings, description and claims.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of an exemplary image module assembly in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>a </i>is a top view of the CMOS sensor die shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>b </i>is a side cross sectional view of a conventional CMOS sensor die.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref><i>a</i>-<i>b </i>are schematic diagrams of a sensor die having shifted microlenses in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>a </i>is a schematic diagram of an exemplary embodiment of a conventional sensor pixel.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>b </i>is a schematic diagram of an exemplary embodiment of a sensor pixel in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a side cross sectional view of an exemplary embodiment of a sensor die in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Foregoing described embodiments of the invention are provided as illustrations and descriptions. They are not intended to limit the invention to precise form described. In particular, it is contemplated that functional implementation of invention described herein may be implemented equivalently in hardware, software, firmware, and/or other available functional components or building blocks. Other variations and embodiments are possible in light of above teachings, and it is thus intended that the scope of invention should not be limited by this Detailed Description, but rather by Claims following.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Unless defined otherwise, all technical and scientific terms used herein have the same meaning as commonly understood by one of ordinary skill in the art to which this invention belongs. Although any methods and materials similar or equivalent to those described herein can be used in the practice or testing of the present invention, the preferred methods and materials are now described.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">It must be noted that, as used herein and in the appended claims, the singular forms “a”, “an”, and “the” include plural referents unless the context clearly dictates otherwise. Thus, for example, reference to “a pixel” includes a plurality of such pixels, i.e., pixel array, and equivalents thereof known to those skilled in the art, and so forth.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic diagram of an exemplary image module assembly <b>100</b> in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. The image module assembly <b>100</b> may be included in a digital image device, such as digital image camera and cellular phone with imaging capabilities. The image module assembly <b>100</b> includes: an outer case having barrel members <b>102</b><i>a</i>-<i>b </i>and a bottom <b>102</b><i>c</i>; a lens unit (or, equivalently lens assembly) <b>103</b> having one or more lens elements <b>104</b><i>a</i>-<i>c</i>; and a CMOS sensor die <b>106</b>. The sensor die <b>106</b> may contain more than a hundred thousand, or even more than a million pixels, and the detailed structure of the pixels will be described in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref><i>a</i>-<i>b</i>. In one embodiment, the width and length of the sensor die <b>108</b> may be about, but not limited to, 5 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The lens elements <b>104</b><i>a</i>-<i>c </i>may direct incoming optical rays <b>108</b> to form an image on the sensor die <b>106</b>. A chief ray <b>110</b> may be at the center of a light ray pencil <b>111</b> collected by a pixel. Likewise, a chief ray angle <b>114</b> may be defined as an angle between a normal to the surface of the sensor die <b>106</b> and a chief ray <b>116</b>. The chief ray angle of the center pixel of the sensor die <b>106</b> may be zero, while that of a corner pixel (e.g., the angle <b>114</b>) may be up to 25-30 degrees. As will be explained later, the chief ray angle <b>114</b> may be determined by several factors including the lens requirements. A marginal ray angle <b>112</b> may be the largest angle between two rays within a light ray pencil collected by a pixel. For simplicity, only three lens elements <b>104</b><i>a</i>-<i>c </i>are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. However, it should be apparent to those of ordinary skill that the present invention can be practiced with any number of lens elements that satisfy the limiting lens requirements specific to the module assembly <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">As mentioned above, the lens requirement, i.e., the number of lens elements <b>104</b><i>a</i>-<i>c </i>and the size of the lens unit <b>103</b>, may be closely related to the design factors of the image module assembly <b>100</b>, such as, the physical dimension of the module assembly <b>100</b> (e.g., the height <b>122</b> and width <b>118</b>), the chief ray angle <b>114</b>, the distance <b>120</b> between the lens element <b>104</b><i>c </i>and surface of the sensor die <b>106</b>, and the physical dimension of the sensor die <b>106</b>. For example, the size of the imaging lens elements <b>104</b><i>a</i>-<i>c </i>may become the major factor limiting the module dimension. The module height <b>122</b> and footprint size may be limited by the lens size especially when the sensor resolution gets higher with a high number of imaging lens elements.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The lens requirements may also affect the chief ray angle of corner pixels and the F-number of the compound imaging lens unit <b>103</b> having the lens elements <b>104</b><i>a</i>-<i>c</i>. For example, for a fixed sensor die dimension and the distance <b>120</b>, a decrease in the diameter of imaging lens elements <b>104</b><i>a</i>-<i>c </i>may yield an increase in the chief ray angle while a decrease in the number of lens elements may yield an increase in the F-number to maintain the image quality. The chief ray angle of the corner pixel (e.g., <b>114</b>) may determine the image uniformity, while the F-number may determine the marginal ray angle <b>112</b>, and as a consequence, the overall module sensitivity. As the major goals in module design may be maximizing the chief ray angle of corner pixels and minimizing the F-number of the compound imaging system without degrading the image quality, the imaging system design may be directed toward lowering the lens requirements. In one embodiment of the present invention, in contrast to the conventional approaches to modify the imaging lens elements <b>104</b><i>a</i>-<i>c</i>, the thickness of the sensor die <b>106</b> may be changed to generate an effect equivalent to lowering the lens requirement.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>a </i>is a top view of the CMOS sensor die <b>106</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>a</i>, the sensor die <b>106</b> includes: a sensing portion <b>204</b> having a plurality of pixels and a non-sensing portion <b>204</b> having circuits to process the signal generated by the sensing portion <b>204</b>, wherein each pixel may include a microlens <b>206</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>b </i>is a side cross sectional view of a conventional CMOS sensor die <b>230</b>. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>b</i>, the conventional sensor die <b>230</b> includes a sensing portion <b>232</b> and a non-sensing portion <b>234</b>. The sensing portion <b>232</b> may includes a plurality of pixels <b>222</b> located on a substrate <b>218</b>, preferably a silicon substrate, and each pixel includes: a photodiode <b>220</b> partially embedded in the substrate layer <b>218</b>; four transparent insulating layers <b>208</b><i>a</i>-<i>d</i>; four metal layers <b>210</b><i>a</i>-<i>d</i>, the four metal layers being insulated by the four transparent insulating layers <b>208</b><i>a</i>-<i>d </i>and connected to the photodiode <b>220</b>; a passivation layer <b>212</b>, the passivation layer being a transparent insulating layer and having a flat top surface; a color filter <b>216</b> for transmitting a specific wavelength or wavelength band of light to the photodiode <b>220</b>; a planar layer <b>214</b> for providing a flat surface; and a microlens <b>206</b> for focusing light rays to the photodiode <b>220</b>. The sensor die <b>230</b> may further include a plurality of passive components (such as transistors, resistors and capacitors) partially embedded in the silicon substrate layer <b>218</b>, which are not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>b </i>for simplicity. The metal layers <b>210</b><i>a</i>-<i>d </i>may function as connecting means for the photodiodes <b>220</b> and passive components to the non-sensing area of the sensor die <b>230</b>, where the signals from the photodiodes and passive components may be transmitted using a column transfer method. Further details of the sensor die <b>230</b> are disclosed in U.S. patent application Ser. No. 11/004,465 entitled “Microlens alignment procedures in CMOS image sensor design” filed Dec. 2, 2004, which is hereby incorporated herein by reference in its entirety.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Each color filter <b>216</b> filters light rays directed to its corresponding photodiode <b>220</b> and transmits light rays of only one wavelength or wavelength band. In one embodiment, a RGB color system may be used, and consequently, a color filter <b>216</b> may be one of three types. In the RGB system, signals from three pixels are needed to form one complete color. However, it is noted that the number of types of filters can vary depending on the color system applied to the sensor die <b>230</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref><i>a</i>-<i>b </i>are schematic diagrams of the sensor die <b>106</b> having shifted microlenses in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref><i>a</i>-<i>b</i>, only microlenses <b>304</b> and <b>324</b> and photodiodes <b>302</b> and <b>322</b> are shown for simplicity. However, it should be apparent to those of ordinary skill that other components, such as a color filter, may be inserted between the microlens <b>304</b> (or <b>324</b>) and the photodiode <b>302</b> (or <b>322</b>) and shifted with respect to the photodiode <b>302</b>. The microlenses <b>304</b> and <b>324</b> may correspond to pixels at the center and edge of the sensor die <b>106</b>, respectively. As the chief ray angle of the center pixel may equal zero, the microlens <b>304</b> may not be shifted with respect to the photodiode <b>302</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>a</i>. However, the chief ray angle <b>332</b> of the edge pixel may be up to 25-30 degrees and, as a consequence, the microlens <b>324</b> of the pixel near the edge of the sensor die <b>106</b> may be shifted by a distance S <b>330</b> to collect the light rays <b>328</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref><i>b</i>. More detailed explanation of the photodiode shifting techniques are disclosed in the previously referenced U.S. patent application Ser. No. 11/004,465 entitled “Microlens alignment procedures in CMOS image sensor design” filed Dec. 2, 2004.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The thickness T <b>326</b> may be determined by a set of parameters including the number and thicknesses of the metal layers, transparent insulating layers, passivation layer, color filter and planar layer. The distances S <b>330</b> may be calculated by the equation:
<br/>
<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="lead"?><i>T</i>*tan θ/<i>n</i><sub>—</sub><i>eq=S</i>  (1)<?in-line-formulae description="In-line Formulae" end="tail"?>
<br/>
where θ and n_eq represent the chief ray angle <b>332</b> and the equivalent refractive index of the layers from microlens vertex to the photodiode surface, respectively. The shift distance S <b>330</b> may decrease as the thickness T <b>326</b> decreases for a fixed chief ray angle. Likewise, for a fixed shift distance S <b>330</b>, a decrease in the thickness T <b>326</b> may allow an increase in the chief ray angle <b>332</b>. Thus, the stack height, or equivalently the thickness T <b>326</b>, may be an ultimate limit to the chief ray angle <b>332</b>.
</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">As describe above in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the F-number of the compound imaging system may be related to the marginal ray angle <b>309</b>. For a given dimension of the photodiode <b>302</b>, a decrease in the thickness T <b>326</b> may yield an increase in the marginal ray angle <b>309</b>, which in turn may allow a decrease in the F-number of the compound imaging system. Thus, the thickness T <b>326</b> may be an ultimate limit to the F-number of the imaging system. As the major goals in module design may be maximizing the chief ray angle of the corner pixel and minimizing the F-number of the compound imaging system without degrading the image quality, it is desirable to decrease the thickness T <b>326</b>. Also, as the maximum chief ray angle and the minimum F-number of the compound imaging system are limited by the lens requirements, the decrease in the thickness T <b>326</b> may have an effect equivalent to lowering the lens requirements.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Another advantage of thin sensor die may be realized by the use of thick microlenses. As the thickness T <b>326</b> decreases, the focal length of a microlens (e.g., <b>304</b>) may decrease, and as a consequence, the thickness of the microlens may increase. In general, thicker microlenses may be fabricated with relative easy than thinner microlenses. Furthermore, the surface roughness of the thicker microlenses may have less negative effect on the image intensity than the thinner microlenses.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>a </i>is a schematic diagram of an exemplary embodiment <b>400</b> of the conventional sensor pixel <b>222</b> (shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>b</i>). The sensor pixel <b>400</b> may be on a substrate <b>420</b> and include: a photodiode <b>416</b>; four transparent insulating layers <b>404</b><i>a</i>-<i>d</i>; four metal layers <b>406</b><i>a</i>-<i>d</i>, the four metal layers being insulated by the four transparent insulating layers <b>404</b><i>a</i>-<i>d </i>and connected to the photodiode <b>416</b>; a passivation layer <b>408</b>, the passivation layer being a transparent insulating layer and having a flat top surface; a color filter <b>410</b> for transmitting a specific wavelength or wavelength band of light to the photodiode <b>416</b>; a planar layer <b>412</b> for providing a flat surface; and a microlens <b>414</b> for focusing light rays to the photodiode <b>416</b>. Typically, the thicknesses <b>418</b> and <b>419</b> may be about 7 and 10 microns, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>b </i>is a schematic diagram of an exemplary embodiment <b>420</b> of a sensor pixel in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. The sensor pixel <b>420</b> includes: a photodiode <b>436</b>; two transparent insulating layers <b>424</b><i>a</i>-<i>b</i>; two metal layers <b>426</b><i>a</i>-<i>b</i>; a passivation layer <b>428</b>, the passivation layer being a transparent insulating layer and having a flat top surface; a color filter <b>430</b> for transmitting a specific wavelength or wavelength band of light to the photodiode <b>436</b>; a planar layer <b>432</b> for providing a flat surface; and a microlens <b>434</b> for focusing light rays to the photodiode <b>436</b>. The sensor die <b>420</b> may be similar to the sensor pixel <b>400</b> except a difference that the sensor pixel <b>420</b> has a smaller number of metal and insulating layers to reduce its thickness. The thicknesses <b>438</b> and <b>439</b> may be about, but not limited to, 3 and 5 microns, respectively. In one embodiment, to reduce the thicknesses <b>438</b> and <b>439</b> further, the thickness of each layer of the pixel <b>420</b> may be decreased. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref><i>b</i>, only two metal layers and two insulating layers are shown for simplicity. However, it is noted that the present invention may be practiced with any number of metal and insulting layers.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a side cross sectional view of an exemplary embodiment <b>500</b> of a sensor die in accordance with one embodiment of the present invention. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the sensing portion <b>520</b> of the sensor die <b>500</b> may have a smaller number of metal and transparent insulating layers than the non-sensing portion <b>522</b>. The sensing portion <b>520</b> includes: a substrate <b>502</b>; photodiodes <b>504</b>; two metal layers <b>508</b><i>a</i>-<i>b</i>; three transparent insulating layers <b>506</b><i>a</i>-<i>c</i>; a passivation layer <b>512</b>; a planar layer <b>510</b>; color filters <b>514</b>; and microlenses <b>516</b>. The non-sensing portion <b>522</b> may include: the substrate <b>502</b>; three metal layers <b>508</b><i>a</i>-<i>c</i>; four transparent insulating layers <b>506</b><i>a</i>-<i>d</i>; the passivation layer <b>512</b>; and the planar layer <b>510</b>. In one embodiment, the two insulating layers <b>506</b><i>a </i>and <b>506</b><i>d </i>may be made of one dielectric material.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Typically, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref><i>b</i>, each layer of the conventional sensor die <b>230</b> may have a uniform thickness distribution over the portions <b>232</b> and <b>234</b>. Thus, in a conventional sensor die <b>230</b>, some of the layers may be required by only one of the two portions <b>232</b> and <b>234</b>, and become unnecessary to the other. For example, the non-sensing portion <b>522</b> may require a metal layer <b>508</b><i>c </i>coupled to a plurality of passive components (such as transistors, resistors and capacitors) embedded in the substrate <b>502</b>, which are not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> for simplicity. As the sensing portion <b>520</b> may not need the metal layer <b>508</b><i>c</i>, a corresponding part of the metal layer <b>508</b><i>c </i>may be eliminated as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In general, the top metal layer of a conventional sensor die <b>404</b><i>d </i>may be configured to reduce the amount of stray light that otherwise would be collected by the photodiode <b>416</b> and its neighboring photodiodes. However, by eliminating unnecessary layers, the thickness <b>418</b> may be reduced, and as a consequence, the amount of stray light may be reduced to make the top metal layer <b>418</b> dispensable. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the sensor die <b>500</b> does not have a metal layer configured to block the stray light, which may further reduce the thicknesses <b>438</b> and <b>439</b>. In one embodiment, the number of imaging lens elements <b>104</b><i>a</i>-<i>c </i>for a VGA (640×480 resolution) system may be reduced from 3 to 2, where the number of imaging lens elements for multi mega pixel system may be reduced from 4 to 3. In another embodiment, the lens diameter and thickness may be decreased by at least 15%.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As explained in connection with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3</figref><i>a</i>-<i>b</i>, a decrease in stack height may allow an increase in the maximum chief ray angle of corner pixels and a decrease in the minimum F-number of compound imaging system. Typically, the maximum chief ray angle and the minimum F-number of a conventional sensor die may be about 15-20 degrees and 2.8-3.5, respectively. In one embodiment, a reduced stack height may allow the maximum chief ray angle of 25-30 degrees and the minimum F-number of 1.7-2.5, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">For clarity explanation, only three metal layers are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. However, it should be apparent to those of ordinary skill that the present invention may be practiced with any number of metal layers. Also, it is should be apparent to those of ordinary skill that the difference in the number of layers between the sensing and non-sensing portions can vary without deviating from the present teachings.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Those skilled in the art will appreciate that the methods and designs described above have additional applications and that the relevant applications are not limited to those specifically recited above. It should be understood that the foregoing relates to exemplary embodiments of the invention and that modifications may be made without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as set forth in the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A sensor die comprising:
<claim-text>a sensing portion including a plurality of pixels, each of the plurality of pixels having a first set of layers and a microlens;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a non-sensing portion around an outside border of the plurality of pixels having a second set of layers, the second set of layers having a different number of layers than the first set of layers and wherein a thickness of the second set of layers is larger than a thickness of the first set of layers to reduce size of the sensor die, wherein the sensing and non-sensing portions are formed on a substrate having a plurality of passive components; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the first set of layers includes:
<claim-text>a photodiode partially embedded on the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first insulating layer on top of the photodiode and the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of metal layers on top of the first insulating layer, the photodiode and the plurality of passive components coupled to at least one of the plurality of metal layers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of middle insulating layers, each of the plurality of metal layers sandwiched by corresponding two of the plurality of middle insulating layers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a passivation layer on top of the plurality of middle insulating layers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a color filter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a planar layer on top of the color filter,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein an optical axis of the microlens and an optical axis of the color filter are shifted with respect to an optical axis of the photodiode and wherein the microlens is configured to direct incoming light to the photodiode.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A sensor die formed on a substrate having a plurality of passive components, comprising:
<claim-text>a sensing portion including a plurality of pixels, each of the plurality of pixels having a microlens and a first set of layers that comprises:
<claim-text>a photodiode partially embedded on the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first insulating layer on top of the photodiode and the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of metal layers on top of the first insulating layer, the photodiode and the plurality of passive components connected to at least one of the plurality of metal layers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>plurality of middle insulating layers, each of the plurality of metal layers sandwiched by corresponding two of the plurality of middle insulating layers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a passivation layer on top of the plurality of middle insulating layers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a color filter; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a planar layer on top of the color filter; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a non-sensing portion around an outside border of the plurality of pixels having a second set of layers, the second set of layers having a different number of layers than the first set of layers and wherein a total thickness of the second set of layers is larger than a total thickness of the first set of layers to reduce size of the sensor die.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The sensor die of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein an optical axis of the microlens and an optical axis of the color filter are shifted with respect to an optical axis of the photodiode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The sensor die of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the second set of layers includes at least one more layer than the first set of layers and wherein the at least one more layer is a metal layer, an insulating layer, or any combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The sensor die of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein thickness of the first and second sets of layers is about 4 microns.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The sensor die of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the device is a digital camera or a cellular phone with an imaging capability.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The sensor die of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the color filter passes light of one color selected from the group consisting of red, green and blue.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The sensor die of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the second set of layers includes at least one more layer than the first set of layers and wherein the at least one more layer is a metal layer, an insulating layer, or any combination thereof.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The sensor die of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the color filter passes light of one color selected from the group consisting of red, green and blue.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
