<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298019-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298019</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11024653</doc-number>
<date>20041230</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2004-0050466</doc-number>
<date>20040630</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>29</main-group>
<subgroup>72</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257532</main-classification>
<further-classification>257534</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E27048</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E27071</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E27092</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Capacitor of semiconductor device and method of manufacturing the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0160565</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Lee</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438240</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0178728</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Park et al.</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257758</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0232497</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Xi et al.</name>
<date>20031200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438627</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0013803</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chung et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>427255391</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0108587</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Chudzik et al.</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257700</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>6</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257532</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257534</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E27048</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E27071</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E27092</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060001063</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060105</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Ki Min</first-name>
<address>
<city>Cheongju-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Lowe Hauptman Ham &amp; Berner LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Dongbu Electronics Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Fourson</last-name>
<first-name>George</first-name>
<department>2823</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Garcia</last-name>
<first-name>Joannie Adelle</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A MIM capacitor includes a lower electrode disposed on a semiconductor substrate. A dielectric layer is disposed on the lower electrode to completely cover an exposed surface of the lower electrode. An upper electrode is disposed on the dielectric layer. A method for forming a MIM capacitor includes forming a lower electrode on a semiconductor substrate. A dielectric layer and an upper metal layer are formed on an entire surface of the substrate to cover the lower electrode. The dielectric and upper metal layers are patterned on the lower electrode.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="94.40mm" wi="97.54mm" file="US07298019-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="182.54mm" wi="100.33mm" file="US07298019-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="183.98mm" wi="102.87mm" file="US07298019-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="185.17mm" wi="98.72mm" file="US07298019-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">(a) Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a semiconductor, and more specifically to a metal-insulator-metal (MIM) capacitor and a method of manufacturing the MIM capacitor.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">(b) Discussion of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Generally, a capacitor used in memory cells includes a lower storage electrode, a dielectric layer and an upper plate electrode. Known techniques for increasing capacitance include: decreasing a thickness of the dielectric layer; increasing the effective surface through three dimensional capacitor structures; and using a dielectric layer having a high dielectric constant, such as TaO<sub>2 </sub>or Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>. When TaO<sub>2 </sub>is used in the dielectric layer, the capacitor has a MIS (Metal-Insulator-Semiconductor) or MIM (Metal-Insulator-Metal) structure with a metal upper electrode.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">However, when the MIS structure capacitor uses TaO<sub>2 </sub>or Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3 </sub>in the dielectric layer, a thickness of the dielectric layer increases. The increased thickness is caused by oxidation of polysilicon during a thermal treatment process performed at high temperature after the formation of the dielectric layer. Therefore, the capacitance of the MIS capacitor is reduced as the dielectric layer is made thicker. For these reasons, the MIM structure is often preferred over the MIS structure.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A method of manufacturing a related art MIM structure capacitor is explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a lower metal layer is deposited on a semiconductor substrate <b>10</b> and photolithographically patterned to form a lower electrode <b>11</b>. Then an insulating layer having a high dielectric constant and an upper metal layer are deposited, in this order, to cover the lower electrode <b>11</b>. The upper metal layer and the insulating layer are patterned to form an upper electrode <b>13</b> and a dielectric <b>12</b> by a photolithography process, to expose portions of both sides of the lower electrode <b>11</b>. This process results in the formation of the capacitor <b>100</b>, having the MIM structure.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">However, in the related art MIM structure, the lower electrode <b>11</b> is partially etched during the formation of the dielectric <b>12</b> and the upper electrode <b>13</b>. Therefore, it is probable that re-deposition of the lower metal occurs on side surfaces of the dielectric <b>12</b> and the upper electrode <b>13</b>, which may result in an electric shorts between the lower and upper electrodes <b>11</b> and <b>13</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Further, the lower electrode <b>11</b> is longer than the upper electrode <b>13</b>, and thus the lower electrode <b>11</b> has exposed side surfaces. Therefore, at the side area parasitic capacitance can result, and the characteristics of the MIM capacitor may be degraded.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">To address the above-described and other problems, the present invention advantageously provides a MIM capacitor includes a lower electrode disposed on a semiconductor substrate. A dielectric layer is disposed on the lower electrode to completely cover an exposed surface of the lower electrode. An upper electrode is disposed on the dielectric layer.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The present invention further provides a method for forming a MIM capacitor includes forming a lower electrode on a semiconductor substrate. A dielectric layer and an upper metal layer are formed on an entire surface of the substrate to cover the lower electrode. The dielectric and upper metal layers are patterned on the lower electrode.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">It is to be understood that both the foregoing general description of the invention and the following detailed description are exemplary, but are not restrictive of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The accompanying drawings, which are included to provide a further understanding of the invention and are incorporated in and constitute a part of this application, illustrate aspects of the invention and together with the description serve to explain the principle of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a sectional view of a related art MIM capacitor.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A to 2E</figref> are sectional views showing a method of forming a MIM capacitor according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Reference is made in detail to the embodiments of the present invention illustrated in the accompanying drawings. The same reference numbers are used throughout the drawings to refer to the same or similar parts.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> shows a metal layer formed on a semiconductor substrate <b>20</b> and patterned by photolithography process to form a lower electrode <b>21</b>. Preferably, the lower electrode <b>21</b> is formed from aluminum (Al), tungsten (W) or TiN metal. As a fluent film, a photoresist layer <b>22</b> is deposited on the substrate to cover the lower electrode <b>21</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>, the photoresist layer <b>22</b> is reflowed to have curved profiles at portions covering the corners of the lower electrode <b>21</b>. Preferably, the photoresist layer <b>22</b> is reflowed by thermal treating. The thermal treatment can be performed at a temperature from about 150° C. to about 300° C.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The reflowed photoresist layer <b>22</b> is removed by a process that simultaneously etches the photoresist layer <b>22</b> and the lower electrode <b>21</b>. The etching ratio of the photoresist layer <b>22</b> and the lower electrode <b>21</b> is about 1:1, such that the etched lower electrode <b>21</b> has a curved profile (e.g., curved corners or an arcuate surface) as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2C</figref>. Preferably, the etching process can be performed with a mixed gas of Cl<sub>2</sub>, BCl<sub>3</sub>, Ar and/or CHF<sub>3</sub>, under a pressure of from about 8 mTorr to about 13 mTorr, a power source from about 900 W to about 1,200 W, and/or a bias power from about 140 W to about 200 W. The flow rate of the gases Cl<sub>2</sub>, BCl<sub>3</sub>, Ar and/or CHF<sub>3 </sub>can be from about 60 sccm to about 90 sccm, from about 40 sccm to about 70 sccm, from about 30 sccm to about 50 sccm, and/or from about 2 sccm to about 5 sccm, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As the lower electrode <b>21</b> has curved corners, the deposition of an IMD (Inter Metal Dielectric) layer and an upper electrode is facilitated. Specifically, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2D</figref>, an insulating layer <b>23</b> having a high dielectric constant, and an upper metal layer <b>24</b>, are deposited on the substrate to cover the lower electrode <b>21</b>. Preferably, the insulating layer <b>23</b> is formed from TaO<sub>2</sub>, Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, and/or silicon nitride (SiN), and/or the upper metal layer <b>24</b> is formed from Ru, Pt, and/or TiN.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2E</figref>, the insulating layer <b>23</b> and the upper metal layer <b>24</b> are patterned to form an IMD layer <b>23</b><i>a </i>and an upper electrode <b>24</b><i>a</i>. It is to be understood that in the MIM structure capacitor <b>200</b> of the present invention, the IMD layer <b>23</b><i>a </i>and the upper electrode <b>24</b><i>a </i>can completely cover the underlying lower electrode <b>21</b> without leaving any exposed surfaces of the lower electrode <b>21</b>, as shown in the figure. Therefore, re-deposition of a lower electrode (such as the lower electrode <b>21</b>) that may occur during a conventional etching process of a dielectric layer and an upper metal layer can be prevented. Further, electric shorting can be prevented between the lower and upper electrodes <b>21</b> and <b>24</b>. Thus, the characteristics of the MIM structure capacitor <b>200</b> are improved as compared to a conventional MIM capacitor.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">While the invention has been shown and described with reference to certain preferred embodiments thereof, it will be understood by those skilled in the art that various changes in form and details may be made therein without departing from the spirit and scope of the invention as defined by the appended claims.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The present application incorporates by reference in its entirety Korean Patent Application No. P2004-50466, filed in the Korean Patent Office on Jun. 30, 2004.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A MIM capacitor comprising:
<claim-text>a lower electrode disposed on a semiconductor substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a dielectric layer disposed on the lower electrode to completely cover an exposed surface of the lower electrode; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an upper electrode disposed on the dielectric layer,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the dielectric layer and an upper layer has a curved profile following a topology of the lower electrode, and the lower electrode has a convex half-cylindrical profile and is located between the semiconductor substrate and the dielectric layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the dielectric layer comprises at least one of TaO.sub.2, Al.sub.2O3 and SiN.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein at least one of the lower and upper electrodes comprises a metal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein the lower and upper electrodes each comprise a metal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the lower electrode comprises is non-hollow.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The capacitor according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the lower electrode has an outer surface with the convex half cylindrical profile.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
