<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298163-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298163</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10834874</doc-number>
<date>20040430</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-162018</doc-number>
<date>20030606</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>315</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>31</main-group>
<subgroup>305</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>04</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324770</main-classification>
<further-classification>324758</further-classification>
<further-classification>250310</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">TFT array inspection device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6137300</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hayashida</name>
<date>20001000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324758</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6750926</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Ohgiichi et al.</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>349 40</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6759867</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Sohn</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324770</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6765203</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Abel</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>250310</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>6</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>324770</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>11</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>17</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040246018</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20041209</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Takada</last-name>
<first-name>Chikuya</first-name>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kanesaka</last-name>
<first-name>Manabu</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Shimadzu Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Kyoto</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Ha Tran</first-name>
<department>2829</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Chan</last-name>
<first-name>Emily Y</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A TFT array inspection device inspects a TFT array substrate having thin film transistors arranged in a matrix pattern. The TFT array inspection device includes a probe frame to be electrically connected to the TFT array substrate. The probe frame includes probe pins contacting array inspection electrodes to be connected to a driving electrode terminal provided in a TFT array on the TFT array substrate through wires. The probe pins are positioned at common locations relative to a layout of the TFT array substrate. Since the probe pins are located at common positions, it is possible to use a single common probe frame for the TFT array substrate with a different layout without providing or changing a prove frame corresponding to a different layout of the TFT array substrate.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="108.03mm" wi="131.66mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="115.15mm" wi="135.13mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="235.71mm" wi="154.43mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="157.48mm" wi="137.50mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="224.37mm" wi="153.84mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="254.00mm" wi="137.67mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="255.02mm" wi="191.35mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="188.38mm" wi="155.96mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="117.60mm" wi="169.25mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="192.02mm" wi="135.47mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="220.47mm" wi="146.30mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="186.01mm" wi="125.98mm" file="US07298163-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION AND RELATED ART STATEMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a thin film transistor (hereinafter referred to as TFT) array inspection device for inspecting a TFT array substrate used for a liquid crystal display, an organic EL display, and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A TFT array substrate is formed of thin film transistors arranged in a matrix pattern and a signal electrode for supplying a driving signal to the thin film transistors. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a view showing the TFT array substrate and a conventional TFT array inspection device. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, a TFT array substrate <b>12</b> includes a plurality of TFT arrays <b>12</b><i>a </i>on a substrate formed of glass and the like. Each of the TFT arrays <b>12</b><i>a </i>includes a plurality of thin film transistors (not shown) arranged in a matrix pattern. The thin film transistors are driven by a signal from scanning signal electrode terminals <b>12</b><i>b </i>and image signal electrode terminals <b>12</b><i>c. </i></p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">A TFT array inspection device <b>11</b> inspects the TFT arrays <b>12</b><i>a </i>on the TFT array substrate <b>12</b>. The TFT array inspection device <b>11</b> includes inspecting probe electrodes <b>11</b><i>b</i>-<b>1</b> and <b>11</b><i>b</i>-<b>2</b> electrically connected to the scanning signal electrode terminals <b>12</b><i>b </i>and the image signal electrode terminals <b>12</b><i>c</i>, and an inspecting circuit <b>11</b><i>c</i>. The inspecting circuit <b>11</b><i>c </i>includes voltage supply means and detection means. The voltage supply means applies a predetermined voltage, and the detection means detects an electric current to inspect a short circuit between a gate and a source, a point defect, a breaking, and the like. Japanese Patent Publication (Kokai) No. 2001-272643 has disclosed such a TFT array inspection device.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The TFT array is used as, for example, a liquid crystal panel. Various TFT arrays with various sizes and specifications are arranged on a. TFT array substrate. Accordingly, each of the TFT array substrates has different driving electrodes depending on a layout thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In the conventional TFT array inspection device, it is necessary to provide an inspecting probe electrode having a specific electrode arrangement according to a layout of the TFT array. It is also necessary to change the inspecting probe electrode according to the TFT array substrate to be inspected, thereby taking time for the inspection. Also, when the layout of the TFT array is changed, it is necessary to change the inspecting probe electrode of the TFT array inspection device, thereby increasing cost.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">As a substitute for the TFT array inspection device, there has been proposed an inspection method in which a probe frame is provided with probe pins contacting all of the electrodes of the TFT arrays arranged on the TFT array substrate. However, in such a probe frame, similar to the TFT array inspection device described above, it is still necessary to provide the probe frame corresponding to an arrangement of electrodes when the layout of the TFT array is changed.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In view of the problems described above, the present invention has been made, and an object of the present invention is to provide a TFT array inspection device using a common member without changing a member according to a different layout of the TFT array substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Further objects and advantages of the invention will be apparent from the following description of the invention.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In order to achieve the objects described above, according to an embodiment of the present invention, a TFT array inspection device is provided with a common probe frame corresponding to different layouts of the TFT array substrates. Accordingly, it is not necessary to change the probe frame according to a layout of a TFT array substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">More specifically, according to the embodiment of the present invention, the TFT array inspection device inspects a TFT array substrate having thin film transistors arranged in a matrix pattern. The TFT array inspection device includes a probe frame to be electrically connected to the TFT array substrate. The probe frame includes a probe pin contacting an array inspection electrode to be connected to a driving electrode terminal provided in a TFT array on the TFT array substrate through a wire. The probe pin is positioned at a common location relative to a layout of the TFT array substrate. Since the probe pin is located at a same position, it is possible to use a single common probe frame for the TFT array substrate with a different layout without providing or changing a prove frame corresponding to a different layout of the TFT array substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In the embodiment of the present invention, the TFT array inspection device may include connecting means for detachably connecting the probe frame and an external device so that the TFT array inspection device is electrically connected to the external device through the probe frame. The connecting means may include switching means for switching an arrangement of the connection between the probe pin and the external device.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Accordingly, the TFT array is electrically connected to the external device through the probe frame and the connecting means. A driving voltage is applied to the TFT array, and the external device detects a detection signal from the TFT array. The connecting means is freely removable, so that when the TFT array substrate to be inspected is changed, it is easy to switch the connection of the probe frame.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The switching means may include a connection switching connector or a switching element. The connection switching connector defines a connection between an electrode connected to the probe pin and an electrode connected to the external device according to a layout of the TFT array substrate. Through changing the connection switching connector, it is possible to obtain a desirable electrical connection between the TFT array substrate with a different layout and the external device.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In a configuration using the switching element, it is possible to switch a connection between an electrode connected to the probe pin and an electrode connected to the external device with the switching element through an external control signal. Accordingly, it is possible to obtain a desirable electrical connection between the TFT array substrate with a different layout and the external device.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The external device may include a power unit for supplying a voltage for driving the TFT array; detection means for detecting a signal of the TFT array; and inspection means for inspecting a short circuit, a point defect, a breakage, and the like of the TFT array based on a detection signal.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a view showing a TFT array inspection device according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded view showing structural components of the TFT array inspection device according to the embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>3</b>(<i>b</i>) are views showing the TFT array inspection device according to the embodiment of the present invention, wherein <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) is a view showing a state before connecting means are attached, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>b</i>) is a view showing a state that the connecting means are attached;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>4</b>(<i>b</i>) are plan views for explaining a TFT array substrate;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>5</b>(<i>b</i>) are views showing the TFT array substrate, a probe frame, the connecting means and a pallet;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6(</figref><i>a</i>) to <b>6</b>(<i>c</i>) are schematic views for explaining a connection between the connecting means and the probe frame;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>7</b>(<i>b</i>) are schematic views for explaining a connection of a switching connector, wherein <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>a</i>) shows a connected state in which the switching connector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>b</i>) is used, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>b</i>) shows a connected state in which the switching connector shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>c</i>) is used;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a schematic view for explaining a case when the connection of the connecting means is switched through an external signal;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a view showing a modified example of the probe frames according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a view showing another modified example of the probe frames according to the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a view showing the TFT array substrate and a conventional TFT array inspection device.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">Hereunder, embodiments of the present invention will be explained in detail with reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded view showing structural components of a TFT array inspection device according to an embodiment of the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>3</b>(<i>b</i>) are views showing the TFT array inspection device according to the embodiment of the present invention in a state that the TFT array inspection device is attached to TFT arrays. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>4</b>(<i>b</i>) are plan views for explaining a TFT array substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a TFT array inspection device <b>1</b> inspects a TFT array substrate <b>2</b> with TFT arrays <b>2</b><i>a </i>formed thereon. A layout of the TFT arrays <b>2</b><i>a </i>formed on the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> is configured according to, for example, a size or specifications of a liquid crystal panel. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>4</b>(<i>b</i>) show examples of the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>. The TFT array <b>2</b><i>a </i>on the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> is provided with thin film transistors arranged in a matrix pattern and signal electrode terminals (for example, scanning signal electrode terminals and image signal electrode terminals) for driving the thin film transistors. The TFT array substrate <b>2</b> is provided with array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b</i>. While the layout of the TFT array substrate is configured according to a size or specifications of each of the TFT arrays <b>2</b><i>a</i>, the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>have a common layout and common electrode positions relative to a different layout.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>are connected to each of the TFT arrays <b>2</b><i>a </i>through wires <b>2</b><i>c </i>with a pattern corresponding to each layout. Therefore, the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4(</figref><i>a</i>) have an arrangement of pins same as that of the array inspection electrode <b>2</b><i>b </i>shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4(</figref><i>b</i>) In the examples shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>4</b>(<i>b</i>), the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>are disposed along one side of the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>. The array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>may be disposed along two opposing sides, orthogonal sides, or a combination thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Hereinafter, the TFT array inspection device according to the embodiment of the present invention will be explained in a case that the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>are disposed along two opposing sides of the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The TFT array inspection device <b>1</b> includes probe frames <b>3</b> (<b>3</b>A and <b>3</b>B) and connecting means <b>4</b> (<b>4</b>A and <b>4</b>B). In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref>, <b>3</b>(<i>a</i>) and <b>3</b>(<i>b</i>), the probe frames <b>3</b> have probe pins electrically connected to the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>of the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>, and the number and an arrangement of the probe pins correspond to the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">As stated above, the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>have a common arrangement relative to the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> with a different layout. Accordingly, the probe frames <b>3</b> electrically connected to the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>can be used in common for the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> with a different layout. The probe frames <b>3</b> are provided with frame side connectors <b>3</b><i>a </i>connected to probe pins through wires in the probe frames for electrically connecting the connecting means <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">When the array inspection electrode <b>2</b><i>b </i>disposed on one side of the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> has an arrangement different from that of the array inspection electrode <b>2</b><i>b </i>disposed on the other side, the corresponding probe frames <b>3</b>A and <b>3</b>B have different structures. The probe pins are provided on bottom surfaces of the probe frames <b>3</b>, and are not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref>, <b>3</b>(<i>a</i>) and <b>3</b>(<i>b</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The connecting means <b>4</b> electrically connects between the probe frames <b>3</b> and an external device, and switches the electrical connection for connecting between the TFT array substrate with a different layout and the external device. The connecting means <b>4</b> switches the electrical connection through a structure using a switching connector or a switching element driven by an external signal. The connecting means <b>4</b> is connected to the frame side connectors <b>3</b><i>a </i>provided in the probe frames <b>3</b> to electrically connect the connecting means <b>4</b> to the probe frames <b>3</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The external device includes a power source (not shown) for supplying a driving signal to the TFT arrays <b>2</b><i>a </i>and an inspection device (not shown) for detecting an electric current in the TFT arrays <b>2</b><i>a </i>to inspect the arrays. The external device may include a component part electrically connecting with the inspection device. In the embodiment, the external device for electrically connecting with the power unit and the inspection device includes a pallet <b>5</b> and a stage <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The pallet <b>5</b> is a supporting member for supporting the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>, and the stage <b>6</b> is a supporting member for supporting the pallet <b>5</b> to be freely movable. The pallet <b>5</b> is provided with grooves for inserting a part of a transport device for transporting the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>. The pallet <b>5</b> includes pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>a </i>electrically connected to the connecting means <b>4</b> for electrically connecting with the probe frames <b>3</b> through the connecting means <b>4</b>, and also pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>b </i>for electrically connecting with the stage <b>6</b>. The pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>a </i>are connected to the pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>b </i>through wires provided in the pallet <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The stage <b>6</b> includes stage side connectors <b>6</b><i>a </i>electrically connected to the pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>b </i>for electrically connecting with the pallet <b>5</b>. The stage side connectors <b>6</b><i>a </i>can be connected to the power unit or the inspection device through a connector or a wire (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In addition, positions of the frame side connectors <b>3</b><i>a </i>on the probe frames <b>3</b> and positions of the pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>a </i>on the pallet <b>5</b> are arranged such that the connecting means <b>4</b> are connected to the two connectors when the probe frames <b>3</b> are attached. Also, positions of the pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>a </i>on the pallet <b>5</b> and positions of the stage side connectors <b>6</b><i>a </i>on the stage <b>6</b> are arranged such that the two connectors are connected when the pallet <b>5</b> is mounted on the stage <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In the structure described above, the pallet <b>5</b> with the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> mounted thereon is placed on the stage <b>6</b>. The probe frames <b>3</b> are placed on the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>of the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>. The connecting means <b>4</b> are disposed on the frame side connectors <b>3</b><i>a </i>of the probe frames <b>3</b> and the pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>a </i>of the pallet <b>5</b> side. Accordingly, the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> as an inspection subject is placed relative to the TFT array inspection device <b>1</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">When the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> is placed, the stage <b>6</b> is electrically connected to the pallet <b>5</b> through the stage side connectors <b>6</b><i>a </i>and the pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>b</i>, and the pallet <b>5</b> is electrically connected to the probe frames <b>3</b> through the connecting means <b>4</b> connecting between the pallet side connectors <b>5</b><i>a </i>and the frame side connectors <b>3</b><i>a</i>. Also, the probe frames <b>3</b> are electrically connected to the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> through the probe pins (not shown) of the probe frames <b>3</b> contacting the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">When the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>, i.e. the inspection subject, is changed, only the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> placed on the pallet <b>5</b> is changed and the probe frames <b>3</b> are continued to use without being changed. In addition, when the connection between the TFT array substrates and the external device is switched through the connecting means <b>4</b>, it is possible to use the connecting means <b>4</b> provided with a wiring corresponding to the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> to be inspected next. When the connection between the TFT array substrates and the external device is switched through the switching element in the connecting means <b>4</b>, it is not necessary to change the connecting means <b>4</b>. In this case, it is possible to switch the connection of the switching element via the control signal, so that the connecting means <b>4</b> corresponds to the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> to be inspected next.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) is a view showing a state before the connecting means <b>4</b> are attached, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3(</figref><i>b</i>) is a view showing a state that the connecting means <b>4</b> are attached. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>3</b>(<i>b</i>), the probe frames <b>3</b>A, i.e. one of the probe frames <b>3</b>, is shown such that the array inspection electrodes <b>2</b><i>b </i>of the TFT array substrates <b>2</b> located under the probe frames <b>3</b>A can be seen through.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">A process of connecting the TFT array substrates, the probe frames, and the connecting means will be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5(</figref><i>a</i>) through <b>8</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>5</b>(<i>b</i>) are views showing the TFT array substrates, the probe frame, the connecting means and the pallet. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6(</figref><i>a</i>) to <b>7</b>(<i>b</i>) are schematic views for explaining a connection between the connecting means and the probe frame.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5(</figref><i>a</i>) and <b>5</b>(<i>b</i>), the array inspection electrode <b>2</b><i>b </i>with the common pattern regardless of the layout of the TFT array <b>2</b><i>a </i>is disposed on the TFT array substrate <b>2</b> placed on the pallet <b>5</b>. The probe frame <b>3</b> is disposed on the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>, so that the probe pins of the probe frame <b>3</b> contact the array inspection electrode <b>2</b><i>b</i>. The probe pins of the probe frame <b>3</b> are arranged in a pattern corresponding to the array inspection electrode <b>2</b><i>b</i>, so that the common single probe frame <b>3</b> can be used regardless of a layout of the TFT array substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">After the probe frame <b>3</b> is placed, the connecting means <b>4</b> is connected to the frame side connector <b>3</b><i>a </i>provided in the probe frame <b>3</b> and the pallet side connector <b>5</b><i>a </i>provided in the pallet <b>5</b>. The connecting means <b>4</b> comprises a frame connector <b>4</b><i>a </i>connected to the frame side connector <b>3</b><i>a</i>; a pallet connector <b>4</b><i>b </i>connected to the pallet side connector <b>5</b><i>a</i>; and switching wires <b>4</b><i>c </i>connecting between the frame connector <b>4</b><i>a </i>and the pallet connector <b>4</b><i>b</i>. The switching wires <b>4</b><i>c </i>constitute the switching means for switching the connection between the frame connector <b>4</b><i>a </i>and the pallet connector <b>4</b><i>b</i>, so that the electrical connection between the TFT array substrate with the different layout and the external device is switched.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The connecting means is prepared beforehand according to the layout of the TFT array substrate, and the connecting means is selected according to the TFT array substrate to be inspected. Accordingly, it is possible to use a single probe frame even when the layout of the TFT array substrate is different.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>a</i>) shows a relationship between the frame side connector <b>3</b><i>a </i>and the pallet side connector <b>5</b><i>a</i>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6(</figref><i>b</i>) and <b>6</b>(<i>c</i>) show configurations of the switching connectors <b>4</b>A and <b>4</b>A′ with the switching wires <b>4</b><i>c </i>in different wiring patterns. The switching connector <b>4</b>A is an example of the connecting means <b>4</b>. When the switching connector <b>4</b>A is changed, it is possible to switch the connection between the TFT array substrate side and the pallet side. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>a</i>), among terminals of the frame side connector <b>3</b><i>a</i>, terminals <b>1</b> to <b>5</b> and <b>17</b> to <b>21</b> are connected to different terminals Ge, Go, D<b>1</b>, D<b>2</b> and C of the TFT array substrate through the wirings at the TFT array substrate side, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">When the terminals <b>1</b> to <b>5</b> are connected to the terminals Ge, Go, D<b>1</b>, D<b>2</b> and C of the pallet connector <b>5</b><i>a</i>, the switching connector <b>4</b>A shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>b</i>) is selected. The switching connector <b>4</b>A comprises the switching wires <b>4</b><i>c </i>corresponding to the terminals <b>1</b> to <b>5</b>. When the switching connector <b>4</b>A is used, the terminals <b>1</b> to <b>5</b> are connected to the corresponding terminals of the pallet connector <b>5</b><i>a</i>. Similarly, when the terminals <b>17</b> to <b>22</b> are connected to the terminals Ge, Go, D<b>1</b>, D<b>2</b> and C of the pallet connector <b>5</b><i>a</i>, the switching connector <b>4</b>A′ shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>c</i>) is selected. The connecting means <b>4</b> comprises the switching wires <b>4</b><i>c </i>corresponding to the terminals <b>17</b> to <b>22</b>. When the switching connector <b>4</b>A′ is used, the terminals <b>17</b> and <b>21</b> are connected to the corresponding terminals of the pallet connector <b>5</b><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>a</i>) shows the connected state in which the switching connector <b>4</b>A shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>b</i>) is used, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7(</figref><i>b</i>) shows the connected state in which the switching connector <b>4</b>A′ shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6(</figref><i>c</i>) is used.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">It is possible to electrically switch the connection between the TFT array substrate and the pallet through the external signal other than physically changing the connecting means <b>4</b> as described above. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a schematic view for explaining a case that the connecting means <b>4</b> switches the connection through the external signal. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the connecting means <b>4</b> comprises the switching means <b>4</b>B including the switching element. The switching element electrically switches the connection through the external signal (not shown). Accordingly, it is possible to switch the connection between the TFT array substrate side and the pallet side similar to the case shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6(</figref><i>a</i>) to <b>7</b>(<i>b</i>).</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">In the embodiments described above, the probe frames are disposed at one side or two opposing sides of the TFT array substrates. Alternatively, it is possible to dispose the probe frames at two orthogonal sides of the TFT array substrates or a combination thereof. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9 and 10</figref> are views for explaining other structural examples of the probe frames.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a view showing an example wherein the probe frames are disposed at two orthogonal positions on the TFT array substrate and at the positions crossing the TFT array substrate. The probe frames <b>3</b>A and <b>3</b>B are disposed at the two opposing sides relative to the TFT array substrate <b>2</b>. A probe frame <b>3</b>C is disposed at the position perpendicular to the sides. A probe frame <b>3</b>D is disposed at the position crossing the TFT array substrate. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a view showing a structural example wherein a probe frame <b>3</b>E crosses a periphery of the TFT array substrate and the TFT array substrate. In the structure wherein the electrodes for the array inspection are formed inside the TFT array substrates, the probe frame crossing the TFT array substrate is used for connecting electrically.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In the TFT array inspection device according to the embodiments of the present invention, the connecting means can be manually exchanged. It is also possible to automatically exchange the connecting means with a configuration including a mechanism for holding the connecting means to be exchangeable, a mechanism for selecting the connecting means corresponding to the TFT array substrate among a plurality of the connecting means; and a mechanism for conveying the selected connecting means to be exchanged.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In the embodiments of the present invention, it is possible to use a common probe frame even with a different layout. When the layout is changed, it is easy to change the wiring by exchanging the connecting means. In the embodiments of the present invention, it is possible to use a common probe frame even with a different TFT array substrate. Accordingly, it is possible to reduce the running cost of the TFT array inspection device and the inspection process.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">As described above, it is possible to use a common member without using a member corresponding to a different layout of the TFT array substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">While the invention has been explained with reference to the specific embodiments of the invention, the explanation is illustrative and the invention is limited only by the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A TFT array inspection device for inspecting a TFT array substrate having a TFT array arranged in a matrix pattern and driving electrode terminals, comprising:
<claim-text>array inspection electrodes disposed on the TFT array substrate and connected to the driving electrode terminals, said array inspection electrodes being arranged on said TFT array substrate commonly with other TFT array substrates regardless of layouts thereof,</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one probe frame electrically connected to the array inspection electrodes of the TFT array substrate,</claim-text>
<claim-text>probe pins disposed on the at least one probe frame for contacting the array inspection electrodes, said probe pins being arranged to correspond to an arrangement of the array inspection electrodes of the TFT array substrate, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>connecting means detachably attached to the at least one probe frame for connecting between the at least one probe frame and an external device, said connecting means having switching means for switching connections between the probe pins and the external device, said switching means including a connection switching connector having a wiring for connecting between the probe pins and the external device according to the layout of the TFT array substrate,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a plurality of connecting means different from each other, each having a wiring corresponding to the layout of the TFT array substrate to be inspected, is prepared, and the at least one probe frame is used commonly for the TFT array substrates with different layouts by selecting and changing to one of the plurality of connecting means.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A TFT array inspection device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a pallet for placing the TFT array substrate having a first connector connected to the connecting means, and a stage for placing the pallet having a second connector connected to the first connector and the external device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A TFT array inspection device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein one probe frame and one connecting means are connected together to form a pair, and another probe frame and another connecting means for forming a pair are arranged to inspect one TFT array substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A TFT array inspection device for inspecting a TFT array substrate having a TFT array arranged in a matrix pattern and driving electrode terminals, comprising:
<claim-text>array inspection electrodes disposed on the TFT array substrate and connected to the driving electrode terminals, said array inspection electrodes being arranged on said TFT array substrate commonly with other TFT array substrates regardless of layouts thereof,</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one probe frame electrically connected to the array inspection electrodes of the TFT array substrate,</claim-text>
<claim-text>probe pins disposed on the at least one probe frame for contacting the array inspection electrodes, said probe pins being arranged to correspond to an arrangement of the array inspection electrodes of the TFT array substrate, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>connecting means detachably attached to the at least one probe frame for connecting between the at least one probe frame and an external device, said connecting means having switching means for switching connections between the probe pins and the external device,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said switching means includes a switching element for switching connections between the probe pins and the external device through an external control signal.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A TFT array inspection device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, further comprising a pallet for placing the TFT array substrate having a first connector connected to the connecting means, and a stage for placing the pallet having a second connector connected to the first connector and the external device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A TFT array inspection device according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein one probe frame and one connecting means are connected together to form a pair, and another probe frame and another connecting means for forming a pair are arranged to inspect one TFT array substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
