<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297027-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297027</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11455768</doc-number>
<date>20060620</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>TW</country>
<doc-number>94215342 U</doc-number>
<date>20050905</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>648</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439608</main-classification>
<further-classification>439108</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Electrical connector</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6386924</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Long</name>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439701</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6619985</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ko</name>
<date>20030900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439607</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6835092</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Wan et al.</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>4395415</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6913488</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Motojima et al.</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439607</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>7</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439608</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439108</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070054552</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070308</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Liang</last-name>
<first-name>Shih-Chieh</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taoyuan</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Rosenberg, Klein &amp; Lee</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>P-Two Industries Inc.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taoyuan</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Truc</first-name>
<department>2833</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An electrical connector has a rectangular insulative housing, a plurality of conductive terminals and a grounding plate respectively received in the housing, and a shell covering the housing. Cavities are defined at both sides of the housing and through a front surface and a rear surface thereof. The grounding plate includes a connecting portion, a plurality of contact pins extending from an edge of the connecting portion, and locking portions respectively extending from opposing sides of the connecting portion. In assembly, the grounding plate is inserted into the housing, the locking portions being embedded in the cavities. The shell has rear portions at a rear thereof for covering rear of the cavities thereby fixing the locking portions when assembled. At least a projecting point is formed on the connecting portion and opposite to the contact pins, and reliably contacts the rear portions of the shell for grounding.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="156.55mm" wi="247.65mm" file="US07297027-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="116.59mm" wi="133.35mm" file="US07297027-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="249.85mm" wi="157.48mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297027-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="234.27mm" wi="141.14mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297027-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="214.80mm" wi="155.19mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297027-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="115.91mm" wi="110.49mm" file="US07297027-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="186.18mm" wi="147.40mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297027-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an electrical connector, and particularly to an electrical connector adapted for a display interface for low voltage differential signal.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">An electrical connector for display panel, which is generally called Low Voltage Differential Signal (LVDS) connector, is soldered on a circuit board and electrically couples to a flexible bus. This connector has low profile, and accordingly, the way to configure a shell, terminals and grounding members thereof is constrained. Moreover, it should be under consideration that retention force of the electrical connector and connection strength between parts thereof. In general, the electrical connector has a metal shell covering a housing thereof for enhancing strength. Besides, the metal shell contacts a grounding member for eliminating electromagnetic wave or static electricity.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a simplified and partial view of a conventional electrical connector. The conventional electrical connector comprises a housing <b>1</b>, terminals <b>2</b>, a grounding plate <b>3</b> and a shell <b>4</b>. A grounding spring <b>5</b> extends from a side of the grounding plate <b>3</b> and is exactly received in a recess <b>6</b> of the housing <b>1</b>. The grounding spring <b>5</b> extends resiliently beyond a side of the housing <b>1</b>, and in assembly, abuts against the shell <b>4</b> for electrically connecting the shell <b>4</b> and the grounding plate <b>3</b>. However, the grounding spring <b>5</b> can not contact the shell <b>4</b> if upward resiliency of the grounding spring <b>5</b> is too small. Otherwise, if the grounding plate <b>3</b> is not fixed reliably, it may be ejected in the case that a mating connector (not shown) mates therewith repeatedly. An electrical connector to overcome above defects is desired.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Accordingly, an object of the present invention is to provide an electrical connector which has enhanced structure and lengthened lifespan.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Another object of the present invention is to provide an electrical connector which has a shell effectively contacting a grounding plate for guarding from electromagnetic interference.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The electrical connector of the present invention comprises a rectangular insulative housing, a plurality of conductive terminals received in the housing, a grounding plate, and a shell covering the housing. The housing has a front surface and a rear surface opposite to each other. A plug opening extends through the front surface, and cavities are defined at both sides of the housing and through the front surface and the rear surface. The grounding plate includes a connecting portion, a plurality of contact pins extending from an edge of the connecting portion, and locking portions respectively extending from opposing sides of the connecting portion. In assembly, the grounding plate is inserted into the housing, the contact pins extending into the housing, and the locking portions being embedded in the cavities. The shell has rear portions at both sides of a rear thereof for covering rear of the cavities when assembled. At least a projecting point is formed on the connecting portion and opposite to the contact pins and reliably contacts the rear portions of the shell for grounding.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a simplified and partial view of a conventional electrical connector.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded view of an electrical connector of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a perspective view of the electrical connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is another perspective view of the electrical connector of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> from another aspect.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along the line A-A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross-sectional view taken along the line B-B in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 through 4</figref>, an electrical connector <b>100</b> in accordance with the present invention comprises an insulative housing <b>10</b>, a grounding plate <b>20</b>, a plurality of conductive terminals <b>30</b> received in the insulative frame <b>10</b>, and a shell <b>40</b> for shielding from electromagnetic interference. The housing <b>10</b> is elongated, rectangular and made of plastic, and has a front surface <b>11</b> and a rear surface <b>12</b> opposite to each other. A plug opening <b>15</b> is defined through the front surface <b>11</b> of the housing <b>10</b> for mating with a flexible bus (not shown). A plurality of plug grooves <b>16</b> is defined above/below the plug opening <b>15</b>, respectively. Cavities <b>17</b> are defined at both sides of the housing <b>10</b> and through the front surface <b>11</b> and the rear surface <b>12</b>. A plurality of recessed portions <b>131</b> and embedding grooves <b>132</b> are respectively formed on an upward surface (not labeled) and a downward surface (not labeled) of the housing <b>10</b>. Sliding blocks <b>18</b> are respectively formed on opposite sides of the housing <b>10</b>. The housing <b>10</b> further forms stop walls <b>171</b> along parts of front of the cavities <b>17</b> and adjacent both sides thereof for fixing the grounding plate <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The terminals <b>30</b> are assembled in the housing <b>10</b> individually. Each terminal <b>30</b> includes a contact end <b>31</b> at an end thereof, a soldering end <b>32</b> at an opposite end thereof, and a middle portion <b>33</b> between the contact end <b>31</b> and the soldering end <b>32</b>. During assembly, the terminals <b>30</b> are inserted into the rear surface <b>12</b> of the housing <b>10</b>. The contact ends <b>31</b> are received in the plug grooves <b>16</b> above the plug opening <b>15</b>. The middle portions <b>33</b> are interferentially fixed in the housing <b>10</b>. The soldering ends <b>32</b> extend out of the rear surface <b>12</b> of the housing <b>10</b> for electrically connecting with a circuit board (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The grounding plate <b>20</b> includes a connecting portion <b>21</b>, a plurality of contact pins <b>22</b> extending perpendicularly from an edge of the connecting portion <b>21</b>, and locking portions <b>23</b> respectively extending from opposing sides of the connecting portion <b>21</b>. Each locking portion <b>23</b> includes a base <b>231</b> extending horizontally from a side of the connecting portion <b>21</b>, and an extending portion <b>232</b> perpendicularly extending from the base <b>231</b>. The extending portion <b>232</b> defines a slot <b>233</b> therein for latching a mating connector (not shown). During assembly, the grounding plate <b>20</b> is inserted from the rear surface <b>12</b> of the housing <b>10</b>, and the contact pins <b>22</b> extend into the plug grooves <b>16</b> below the plug opening <b>15</b>. The contact pins <b>22</b> and the contact ends <b>31</b> of the terminals <b>30</b> correspond to each other, and cooperate to sandwich a flexible bus therebetween when the flexible bus (not shown) is inserted into the plug opening <b>15</b>. Meanwhile the locking portions <b>23</b> of the grounding plate <b>20</b> are embedded into the cavities <b>17</b> of the housing <b>10</b>. The bases <b>231</b> and the extending portions <b>232</b> of the locking portions <b>23</b> bias against inner walls of the cavities <b>17</b>, and are positioned by the stop walls <b>171</b> of the housing <b>10</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>. Soldering portions <b>25</b> extend from edges of the connecting portion <b>21</b> and opposite the contact pins <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">During assembly, the grounding plate <b>20</b> and the terminals <b>30</b> are assembled onto the housing <b>10</b>, thereafter the shell <b>40</b> is brought to cover the housing <b>10</b> from the rear surface <b>12</b> thereof. The shell <b>40</b> is made of metal and is shaped according to profile of the housing <b>10</b>. The shell <b>40</b> has an upper wall <b>41</b> and a lower wall <b>42</b> opposite to each other, and a pair of lateral walls <b>43</b> on both sides thereof. A plurality of spring sheets <b>411</b> and fixing sheets <b>412</b> extend from the upper wall <b>41</b> and the lower wall <b>42</b>. Each lateral wall <b>43</b> defines a slit <b>431</b> therein. When the shell <b>40</b> envelops the housing <b>10</b>, the spring sheets <b>411</b> abut against the recessed portions <b>131</b>, and the fixed sheets <b>412</b> are embedded into the embedding grooves <b>132</b>, whereby the shell <b>40</b> is positioned. At the same time, the sliding blocks <b>18</b> are respectively retained in the slits <b>431</b> of the shell <b>40</b> for improving retention.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>, the shell <b>40</b> has rear portions <b>44</b> at both sides of a rear thereof for covering rear of the cavities <b>17</b> when assembled. In assembly, the rear portions <b>44</b> abut the connecting portion <b>21</b> and the locking portions <b>23</b>, preventing the grounding plate <b>20</b> from ejecting backward owing to front external force. Moreover, the rear portions <b>44</b> cooperate with the stop walls <b>171</b> to fix the locking portions <b>23</b> inside the cavities <b>17</b>. In the event that a flexible bus (not labeled) is inserted, opposite sides of the flexible bus interferentially engage with the slots <b>233</b> of the locking portions <b>23</b>. Hence, no matter how the flexible bus plugs repeatedly, the locking portions <b>23</b> will not deflect, correspondingly lengthening the life of the electrical connector <b>100</b>. The soldering portions <b>25</b> of the grounding plate <b>20</b> and the soldering ends <b>32</b> of the terminals <b>30</b> extend outward from between the rear portions <b>44</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 6</figref>, at least a projecting points <b>211</b> is formed on the connecting portion <b>21</b> of the grounding plate <b>20</b> and opposite to the contact pins <b>22</b>, so as to form reliable contact between the grounding plate <b>20</b> and the shell <b>40</b>. In assembly, the rear portions <b>44</b> of the shell <b>40</b> reliably contact the projecting points <b>211</b> for making the shell <b>40</b> grounded. In another embodiment, the projecting points <b>211</b> are formed on sides of the locking portions <b>23</b> of the grounding plate <b>20</b> for making the shell <b>40</b> grounded.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">The locking portions <b>23</b> of the grounding plate <b>20</b> are held in the cavities <b>17</b> of the housing <b>10</b>, and are further fixed by the rear portions <b>44</b> of the shell <b>40</b>. The projecting points <b>211</b> of the grounding plate <b>20</b> further makes the grounding plate <b>20</b> reliably contact the shell <b>40</b>, simplifying manufacture and further ensuring interconnection between parts of the electrical connector <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">It is understood that the invention may be embodied in other forms without departing from the spirit thereof. Thus, the present examples and embodiments are to be considered in all respects as illustrative and not restrictive, and the invention is not to be limited to the details given herein.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An electrical connector comprising:
<claim-text>a rectangular insulative housing having a front surface and a rear surface opposite to each other, a plug opening extending through the front surface, cavities being defined at both sides of the housing and through the front surface and the rear surface;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of conductive terminals received in the housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a grounding plate including a connecting portion, a plurality of contact pins extending from an edge of the connecting portion, and locking portions respectively extending from opposing sides of the connecting portion, in assembly, the grounding plate being inserted into the housing, the contact pins extending into the housing, and the locking portions being embedded in the cavities; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shell covering the housing, and having rear portions at both sides of a rear thereof for covering rear of the cavities when assembled;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each locking portion includes a base and an extending portion perpendicularly extending from the base, the extending portion defining a slot therein for latching a mating connector.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The electrical connector as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the housing further forms stop walls along parts of front of the cavities for fixing the grounding plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The electrical connector as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein a plurality of recessed portions is respectively formed on an upward surface and a downward surface of the housing, and wherein the shell forms a plurality of spring sheets for abutting against the recessed portions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The electrical connector as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the a plurality of embedding grooves is formed on an upward surface and a downward surface of the housing, and wherein the shell forms a plurality of fixing sheets for being embedded into the embedding grooves.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The electrical connector as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein sliding blocks are respectively formed on opposite sides of the housing, and wherein the shell defines slits at both sides thereof, the sliding blocks being retained in the slits.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. An electrical connector comprising:
<claim-text>a rectangular insulative housing having a plug opening extending through a front surface thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of conductive terminals received in the housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a grounding plate mounted on the housing, and including a connecting portion, a plurality of contact pins, extending from an edge of the connecting portion, at least a projecting point being formed on the connecting portion and opposite to the contact pins the grounding plate including a locking portion having a base and an extending portion perpendicularly extending from the base, the extending portion defining a slot therein for latching a mating connector; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a shell covering the housing, and having rear portions at a rear thereof for contacting the projecting points in assembly.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The electrical connector as claimed in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein locking portions respectively extend from opposing sides of the connecting portion, and form projecting points on sides thereof for contacting rear portions of the shell.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
