<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299016-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299016</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11329245</doc-number>
<date>20060111</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>Q</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4551271</main-classification>
<further-classification>455108</further-classification>
<further-classification>4551861</further-classification>
<further-classification>4551832</further-classification>
<further-classification>455566</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Communication device with an adjustable brightness</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7079174</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Taniguchi et al.</name>
<date>20060700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>348 51</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0116163</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kim et al.</name>
<date>20040600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>4555751</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0033484</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Kung et al.</name>
<date>20060200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>323334</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2007/0024571</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Maniam et al.</name>
<date>20070200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345102</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>455 95</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>455 77</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>455108</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>455120</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4551271</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>455403</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>455566</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>455572</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4551591</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4551862</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4551584</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4551832</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>4551861</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345419</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345422</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345629</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362 29</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>362800</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3151693</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315362</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315294</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>315312</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070159419</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070712</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Liu</last-name>
<first-name>Chien-Hung</first-name>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Bacon &amp; Thomas, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Inventec Corporation</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Taipei</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Philogene</last-name>
<first-name>Haissa</first-name>
<department>2821</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention discloses a communication device with an adjustable brightness that includes a control circuit coupled to a modulating unit, and the modulating unit includes a tuning button disposed on the communication device that allows user to make adjustments or controls by the tuning button to produce a first set value, and the modulating unit converts the power received by a power supply circuit of the communication device into a corresponding operating voltage according to the first set value and sends the operating voltage to a light emitting unit of the communication device for projecting a light source according to the magnitude of the operating voltage, so as to adjust and change the brightness of the light emitting unit, and achieve the effects of saving power and extending the life of the light emitting units.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="134.79mm" wi="208.28mm" file="US07299016-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="231.90mm" wi="157.56mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299016-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="177.21mm" wi="151.55mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07299016-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a communication device with an adjustable brightness, and more particularly to a communication device capable of adjusting the brightness of its light source according to the environment.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">If a traditional mobile phone is powered on and set to a using mode such as dialing a call or inputting a short message, a plurality of light emitting devices such as a light emitting diode (LED) installed in the mobile phone will obtain power. After the light emitting components have obtain power to produce a light, the light is projected to a keyboard and a screen of the mobile phone to illuminate the keyboard and the screen, so that a mobile phone user can clearly see the words, icons, and the like on the keyboard and the screen while the user is dialing a call, receiving a short message, or playing a game.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">However, the design of the light emitting components on the mobile phone produces a light source with a constant brightness only, regardless of the environment, so that if the mobile phone is used in an environment with strong sunlight, the light emitting component still produces the light source with a constant brightness. Such arrangement not only wastes power, but also reduces the life of the light emitting components. Furthermore, if the mobile phone is used at nighttime, the light emitting component still produces a light source with the constant brightness, and such bright light will affect other people. Therefore, finding a way of designing a communication device with an adjustable brightness is an important subject that demands immediate attention and feasible solutions.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In view of the shortcomings of the prior art mobile phones, the inventor of the present invention based on years of experience to conduct extensive researches and experiments, and finally invented a communication device with an adjustable brightness.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Therefore, it is a primary objective of the present invention to provide a communication device with an adjustable brightness that includes a control circuit coupled to a modulating unit, wherein the modulating unit further includes a tuning button exposed from the communication device for allowing users to make adjustments or controls by the tuning button to produce a corresponding first set value, and the modulating unit converts the power received by a power supply circuit of the communication device into a corresponding operating voltage according to the first set value and sends the operating voltage to a light emitting unit of the communication device for projecting a light source according to the magnitude of the operating voltage, so as to adjust and control the tuning button, quickly change the brightness of the light emitting unit, and achieve the effects of saving power, extending the life of the light emitting units, and not disturbing other people.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The above and other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will become apparent from the following detailed description taken with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic circuit diagram of a communication device of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of a communication device of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> for the communication device with an adjustable brightness, the communication device <b>10</b> comprises a control circuit <b>20</b>, a power supply circuit <b>50</b>, a modulating unit <b>30</b>, and a light emitting unit <b>40</b>, wherein the control circuit <b>20</b> and the communication device <b>10</b> include an electronic component and an electronic circuit electrically coupled with each other, so that the communication device <b>10</b> can be operated normally. The control circuit <b>20</b> can produce a corresponding light emitting signal according to the using status of the communication device (such as dialing a call), and the power supply circuit <b>50</b> is separately and electrically coupled to each electronic component and electronic circuit in the control circuit <b>20</b> and the communication device <b>10</b>, and the power supply circuit <b>50</b> can provide a power supply to be used by the communication device <b>10</b>. The modulating unit <b>30</b> and the control circuit <b>20</b> are electrically coupled with each other, and the modulating unit <b>30</b> can receive the light emitting signal produced by the control circuit <b>20</b>. The modulate circuit is coupled to the power supply circuit <b>50</b> for receiving the power supply produced by the power supply circuit <b>50</b>, and the modulating unit <b>30</b> can produce a corresponding operating voltage according to the light emitting signal.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the modulating unit <b>30</b> includes a tuning button <b>35</b> such as a resistance knob or a section switch, and the tuning button <b>35</b> is exposed from the communication device <b>10</b> and provided for users to make adjustments and controls, so as to produce a corresponding first set value, and the modulating unit <b>30</b> can change the magnitude of the operating voltage according to the first set value, and the light emitting unit <b>40</b> is electrically coupled to the modulating unit <b>30</b>. The light emitting unit <b>40</b> can receive an operating voltage produced by the modulating unit <b>30</b> and produce a light source with a different brightness according to the operating voltage and project the light outward. Users can quickly change the brightness of the light protected from the light emitting unit <b>40</b> to achieve the effects of saving power, extending the life of the light emitting unit <b>40</b>, and not disturbing other people.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In the present invention as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the communication device <b>10</b> further comprises an input circuit <b>60</b>, a display circuit <b>65</b>, a memory circuit <b>70</b>, a wireless circuit <b>80</b>, and a sound circuit <b>90</b>, wherein the input circuit <b>60</b> and the control circuit <b>20</b> are electrically coupled with each other, and the input circuit <b>60</b> includes a plurality of press buttons <b>61</b>, and one of the press buttons <b>61</b> can be pressed to produce a corresponding input signal and send the input signal to the control circuit <b>20</b>. The control circuit <b>20</b> analyzes and decodes the input signal into the corresponding text, number, or function, and the display circuit <b>65</b> is electrically coupled with the control circuit <b>120</b>, and the display circuit <b>65</b> includes a display device <b>66</b>, and the display circuit <b>65</b> can produce corresponding information such as a text, a number, or a figure on the display device <b>66</b> according to the display signal produced by the control circuit <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the memory circuit <b>70</b> is used to store the operating system and application programs required for the normal operation of the communication device <b>10</b> and carry out the operations of the control circuit <b>20</b>. The wireless circuit <b>80</b> and the control circuit <b>20</b> are electrically coupled with each other, and the wireless circuit <b>80</b> is connected to another communication device <b>10</b> in a wireless manner, so that the two communication devices <b>10</b> can send voices, texts, and graphic data with each other. The sound circuit <b>90</b> and the control circuit <b>20</b> are electrically coupled with each other, and the sound circuit <b>90</b> can receive an analog sound signal from the outside and convert the analog sound signal into a digital voice signal to be transmitted to the control circuit <b>20</b>. The sound circuit <b>90</b> also can receive a digital voice signal from the control circuit <b>20</b>. After the sound circuit <b>90</b> converts the digital voice signal into an analog sound signal, the analog sound signal can be played.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In the present invention as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, the light emitting unit <b>40</b> projects a light source in the directions of the press buttons <b>61</b>, the display device <b>66</b>, and/or the tuning button <b>35</b>, such that when the light source is projected to the press buttons <b>61</b>, the display device <b>66</b>, and/or the tuning button <b>35</b>, the press buttons <b>61</b>, the display device <b>66</b>, and/or the tuning button <b>35</b> can be illuminated. If a light source is projected onto the press buttons <b>61</b> and the display device <b>66</b>, users can see the text, number, and graphic information on the illuminated press buttons <b>61</b> and display device <b>66</b> of the communication device <b>10</b>. A light source is projected onto the tuning button <b>35</b> to facilitate users to make adjustments and controls.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> for the preferred embodiment of the present invention, the light emitting signal produced by the control circuit <b>20</b> can record a second set value, so that the modulate circuit receives a light emitting signal from the control circuit <b>20</b>. After the light emitting signal is analyzed and decoded into the second set value, the modulating unit <b>30</b> produces a corresponding operating voltage to be used by the light emitting unit <b>40</b> according to the analysis and comparison between the first and second set values. For example, the second set value is a maximum critical voltage which could be a default setting set by the manufacturer of the communication device or set by the user, in order to limit the brightness of the light source projected by the light emitting unit <b>40</b>. If the modulating unit <b>30</b> determines that the first set value is smaller than the second set value, the modulating unit <b>30</b> will produce a corresponding operating voltage according to the first set value. If the first set value is larger than the second set value, the modulating unit <b>30</b> will produce a corresponding operating voltage according to the second set value to achieve the purpose of limiting the brightness of the light emitting unit <b>40</b>. In addition, the second set value can automatically change the brightness according to the current time (such as daytime or nighttime) of using the communication device <b>10</b>, so that the modulating unit <b>30</b> can produce a smaller second set value for the daytime to limit the brightness of the light emitting unit <b>40</b> or produces a larger second set value for the nighttime to increase the brightness of the light emitting unit <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In the preferred embodiment of the present invention as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, the communication device <b>10</b> includes a built-in brightness adjusting procedure <b>21</b>, and the control circuit <b>20</b> can receive the first set value from the modulating unit <b>30</b>, such that after the control circuit <b>20</b> has received the first set value, an adjust signal with a corresponding magnitude will be produced according to the magnitude of the first set value. The brightness adjusting procedure <b>21</b> receives the adjust signal and produces a brightness signal of a corresponding magnitude according to the adjust signal and sends the brightness signal to the display circuit <b>65</b>. The display circuit <b>65</b> such as a liquid crystal display device (an LCD) adjusts the backlight brightness of the display device <b>66</b> according to the magnitude of the brightness signal, so that when a user uses the communication device <b>10</b> in different environments, the backlight brightness can be adjusted quickly to achieve the effect of providing the best display status.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">While the invention herein disclosed has been described by means of specific embodiments, numerous modifications and variations could be made thereto by those skilled in the art without departing from the scope and spirit of the invention set forth in the claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A communication device with an adjustable brightness, comprising:
<claim-text>a control circuit, for producing a light emitting signal according to using status of said communication device;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power supply circuit, electrically coupled to said control circuit for supplying a power required by the normal operation of said control circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a modulating unit for producing a first set value, electrically coupled to said control circuit for receiving said light emitting signal, and being coupled to said power supply circuit for receiving a power supply produced by said power supply circuit, producing a corresponding operating voltage according to said light emitting signal, and changing the magnitude of said operating voltage according to said first set value;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a light emitting unit, electrically coupled to said modulating unit for receiving an operating voltage produced by said modulating unit and producing a light source of a different brightness according to the magnitude of said operating voltage;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an input circuit, electrically coupled to said control circuit and including a plurality of press buttons for producing an input signal and sending said input signal to said control circuit for analyzing and decoding said input signal into a corresponding text, number, or function; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a display circuit, electrically coupled to said control circuit and including a display device for displaying a corresponding text, number, or graphic data on said display device according to a display signal produced by said control circuit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The communication device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said modulating unit comprises a tuning button exposed from said communication device for producing said first set value of different magnitudes.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The communication device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said light emitting signal records a second set value, such that said modulating unit produces a corresponding operating voltage according to a result of the comparison between said first and second set values.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The communication device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said second set value is a maximum critical voltage.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The communication device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein said communication device includes a built-in brightness adjusting procedure for receiving an adjust signal produced by said control circuit according to said first set value and producing a corresponding brightness signal according to said adjust signal, and sending said brightness signal to said display circuit, such that said display circuit adjusts the backlight brightness of said display device according to the magnitude of said brightness signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The communication device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said light emitting unit faces said input circuit and/or said display circuit for producing a light source to be projected onto said press buttons and said display device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The communication device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said light emitting unit faces said input circuit and/or said display circuit for producing a light source to be projected onto said press buttons and said display device.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A communication device with an adjustable brightness, comprising:
<claim-text>a modulating unit, for producing a first set value;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a control circuit, electrically coupled to said modulating unit and including a built-in brightness adjusting procedure for receiving said first set value to produce a corresponding adjust signal and producing a corresponding brightness signal according to said adjust signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a display circuit, including a display device and electrically coupled to said control circuit for receiving said brightness signal and adjusting the backlight brightness of said display device according to said brightness signal;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a power supply circuit, electrically coupled to said control circuit for supplying a power required by the normal operation of said control circuit; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an input circuit, including a plurality of press buttons and electrically coupled to said control circuit for producing an input signal and sending said input signal to said control circuit for analyzing and decoding said input signal into a corresponding text, number, or function.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The communication device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, wherein said modulating unit includes a tuning button exposed from said communication device for producing said first set value of different magnitudes.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
