<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298254-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298254</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11083383</doc-number>
<date>20050316</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>130</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>08</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340531</main-classification>
<further-classification>340541</further-classification>
<further-classification>348152</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Alarm system employing single transmission line</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5202661</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Everett et al.</name>
<date>19930400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340522</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6081193</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Trucchi et al.</name>
<date>20000600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340541</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6433683</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Robinson</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340540</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7068166</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Shibata et al.</name>
<date>20060600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340541</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0267605</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Lee et al.</name>
<date>20051200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>700 19</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>21</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340531</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340541</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3405452</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340565</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3405682</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>340937</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348152</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348159</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>348180</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060220832</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061005</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tracy</last-name>
<first-name>Larry</first-name>
<address>
<city>Auburn</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Watanabe</last-name>
<first-name>Akira</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama Kanagawa Prefecture</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Horie</last-name>
<first-name>Ichirou</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama Kanagawa Prefecture</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>DLA Piper US LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Inet Consulting Limited Company</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Phung T.</first-name>
<department>2612</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">In the present invention an intrusion detection system comprises a detection element configured to detect an intrusion in a location, and to transmit an intrusion signal upon detection of the intrusion. The system further comprises a monitoring device configured to capture images of the location upon the detection of the intrusion, and to transmit image signals representing the captured images. A single transmission line is in electrical communication with the detection element and the monitoring device, wherein the transmission line is configured to carry both the intrusion signals and the image signals.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="77.81mm" wi="170.52mm" file="US07298254-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="250.36mm" wi="176.95mm" file="US07298254-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="178.39mm" wi="137.08mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298254-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="169.76mm" wi="121.41mm" file="US07298254-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="185.42mm" wi="116.76mm" file="US07298254-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="198.20mm" wi="139.11mm" file="US07298254-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates generally to alarm systems. More specifically, this invention relates to alarm systems employing a single transmission line carrying signals from both sensing elements and monitoring devices.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Conventional alarm systems, such as passive infrared (PIR) intrusion detectors, see extensive use for detecting and deterring intrusions such as break-ins or trespasses. One such alarm system is shown in block diagram form in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Here, an alarm system <b>10</b> has a sensing element <b>20</b> for detecting intrusions. The sensing element <b>20</b> is connected to an alarm indicator <b>30</b>, typically by a pair of wires <b>40</b>. The alarm system <b>10</b> also commonly has a camera <b>50</b> connected to a monitor <b>60</b>, typically by a coaxial cable <b>70</b>. In operation, the sensing element <b>20</b> and camera <b>50</b> are placed in proximity to the location at which intrusions are to be detected/prevented. The sensing element <b>20</b> detects intrusions upon this location, while the camera <b>50</b> captures images of the location to provide a visual record of any such intrusion. Upon detecting an intrusion, the sensing element <b>20</b> transmits a signal to the alarm indicator <b>30</b> across the wire <b>40</b>, indicating that an intrusion has occurred. The alarm indicator <b>30</b> then initiates an alarm, such as an audible or visual signal that alerts people to the intrusion. The camera <b>50</b> provides positive confirmation if the sensing element did not trigger a false alarm. Thus, the image captured by the camera <b>50</b> is transmitted across the coaxial cable <b>70</b> and displayed on the monitor <b>60</b>. In this conventional system, the alarm indicator <b>30</b> alerts people, spurring them to activate the camera <b>50</b> and/or watch the monitor <b>60</b> to determine more information about the intrusion. The use of the camera <b>50</b> reduces incidents of false alarm.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">While often effective in detecting and monitoring intrusions, conventional alarm systems <b>10</b> suffer from certain drawbacks. Often, the sensing element <b>20</b> and camera <b>50</b> are located at or near the area to be monitored, while the alarm indicator <b>30</b> and monitor <b>60</b> are placed at a remote area. Accordingly, alarm systems such as alarm system <b>10</b> require two transmission lines, i.e. wires <b>40</b> and coaxial cable <b>70</b>, to be extended between these areas. The use of two such cables instead of one consumes extra space and adds cost. Also, as these two areas can be far apart, additional effort and expense are required to install two lines instead of one. In addition, where a sensing element <b>20</b> with the associated alarm indicator <b>30</b> is already installed, retrofitting such a site would be expensive.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In the prior art, it is also known to use a plurality of cameras connected via a single co-axial cable to a plurality of monitors. Thus the cameras share their signals on the single co-axial cable. However, none of the cameras share their signals with the output of a sensing element which does not output a video frequency signal.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Accordingly, it is desirable to provide an alarm system that employs a single transmission line capable of carrying signals from both sensing element <b>20</b> and monitoring devices such as camera <b>70</b>. The use of a single transmission line eliminates the need for a second line, reducing overall system cost and effort in installation, and permits greater number of existing alarm sensors <b>20</b> to be retrofitted with cameras <b>70</b> to reduce false alarms.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">The invention can be implemented in numerous ways, including as a method, system, and device. Various embodiments of the invention are discussed below.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In the present invention an intrusion detection system comprises a detection element configured to detect an intrusion in a location, and to transmit an intrusion signal upon detection of the intrusion. The system further comprises a monitoring device configured to capture images of the location upon the detection of the intrusion, and to transmit image signals representing the captured images. Finally the system comprises a transmission line in electrical communication with the detection element and the monitoring device, the transmission line configured to carry the intrusion signals and the image signals.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Other aspects and advantages of the invention will become apparent from the following detailed description taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings which illustrate, by way of example, the principles of the invention</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">For a better understanding of the invention, reference should be made to the following detailed description taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a block diagram of a conventional alarm system employing two transmission lines.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a block diagram of an alarm system constructed in accordance with embodiments of the invention, and employing a single transmission line.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a schematic of a combiner circuit for combining signals onto a single transmission line in accordance with embodiments of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a schematic of a separator circuit for directing signals from the single transmission line to different components of the alarm system.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref> illustrate diagrammatic open top, closed side, and closed top views, respectively, of a housing containing a sensing element and camera, for use in embodiments of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A-6B</figref> illustrate top and side views, respectively, of the fields of view of the sensing element and camera from within the housing of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Like reference numerals refer to corresponding parts throughout the drawings.</p>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In one sense, the invention relates to an improved alarm system that utilizes a single transmission line instead of the dual transmission lines often required in conventional alarm systems. Alarm systems often have sensing elements that detect intrusions, and monitoring devices such as cameras for confirming the alarm detection by capturing a visual record of the intrusion. Instead of employing separate transmission lines for each element or device, a combiner circuit transmits signals from the sensing elements and the monitoring devices on the same transmission line. At the other end of this transmission line, a separator circuit receives these signals and, upon detecting a signal from the sensing elements, transmits an alarm signal to the components of the alarm system that initiate an alarm. The separator circuit also routes the camera signals to those components of the alarm system that record/display images from the camera.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">By combining signals from the sensing elements and camera, then separating the signals downstream and sending them to their appropriate destinations, the combiner and separator circuits allow for a conventional single transmission line, such as a single cable comprising of four wires (two to carry signal, and two to carry power), to be used. In contrast to the dual transmission lines required by many conventional systems, the use of a single transmission line allows for more inexpensive alarm systems that are also easier and quicker to install. Finally, the cost of retrofitting an existing alarm sensor with an additional camera is greatly reduced.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a block diagram of a single-transmission-line alarm system constructed in accordance with embodiments of the invention. The alarm system <b>100</b> employs a sensing element <b>110</b> to detect intrusion, and a camera <b>120</b> to monitor and/or record details of the intrusion. As above, the sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b> are often placed in proximity to the location that is to be monitored for intrusion, while an alarm indicator <b>130</b> and monitor <b>140</b> are placed in a different location. A single transmission line <b>150</b> extends between the sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b> at one location, and the alarm indicator <b>130</b> and monitor <b>140</b> at another location. This single transmission line <b>150</b> carries signals from both the sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b>. That is, the sensing element <b>110</b> transmits an intrusion detection signal when it detects an intrusion in the area it is monitoring. Similarly, the camera <b>120</b> transmits video signals, or other electronic image signals, that provides details of the intrusion. Unlike the conventional alarm system <b>10</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, this transmission line <b>150</b> is set up to carry both the intrusion signals from sensing elements <b>110</b>, and the video or other image signals from the camera <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In order to carry signals from both a sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b> on the same line, transmission line <b>150</b> includes a combiner circuit <b>160</b> for combining signals from both these elements onto the same line, as well a separator circuit <b>170</b> for directing different components of the combined signal to different destinations. In operation then, the combiner circuit <b>160</b> combines signals from the sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b> onto the same transmission line <b>150</b>. These combined signals travel downstream along the transmission line <b>150</b> to the separator circuit <b>170</b>, which directs the video or image signals to the monitor <b>140</b>, and transmits alarm signals to the alarm indicator <b>130</b>. In this manner, different signals from different sources of an alarm system (i.e., sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b>) are combined onto a single transmission line <b>150</b>, where they are later separated and routed to different destinations (i.e., the alarm indicator <b>130</b> and monitor <b>140</b>). Such a configuration allows this single transmission line to take the place of the dual transmission lines <b>40</b>, <b>70</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, yielding an alarm system that is cheaper and more easily installed than conventional alarm systems.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates details of the combiner circuit <b>160</b>. In this circuit, the camera <b>120</b> generates video or image signals that are amplified by the amplifier <b>200</b> and transmitted along the wire pair <b>210</b>, where they are combined with signals from the sensing element <b>110</b> along the wire pair <b>220</b>. The components are known components commonly employed in current alarm systems. For example, the amplifier <b>200</b> is a known component that typically employs a 6 dB amplifier coupled with a 75Ω driver to amplify image signals from the camera <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In addition, one of skill will realize that the invention does not limit itself to the use of these specific components, but rather employs them as an example of the more general concept of combining separate signals from any sensing elements and any monitoring devices onto any single transmission line. Accordingly, the sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b> can be any devices used in alarm systems to detect and monitor intrusions. For instance, the sensing element <b>110</b> can be a passive infrared (PIR) detector capable of detecting infrared radiation given off by potential intruders. However, the sensing element <b>110</b> can also be a microwave detector, a photo beam detector, a glass break sensor, a door contact sensor, or any other sensing element capable of being employed to detect an intrusion. Likewise, the camera <b>120</b> is commonly a video camera for capturing video images of intruders, but it can also be any device for monitoring the location of a potential intrusion, such as a still-frame camera or any other audio/video recording device. In addition, the combiner circuit of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> combines signals from both the sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b> onto a single line <b>220</b>. This line is typically a four wire cable (in which two lines carry power, and two lines carry signal), but can be any wire or other electrical transmission line capable of carrying signals from both a sensing element and a monitoring element of an alarm system.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The combined signals are transmitted along the transmission line <b>220</b> (i.e., the transmission line <b>150</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) where they are detected and processed by the separator circuit <b>170</b>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates further details of the separator circuit <b>170</b>. Signals transmitted along the transmission line <b>220</b> are received at terminal <b>300</b>, where they are routed to an alarm indicator terminal <b>310</b> and a video terminal <b>320</b>. More specifically, intrusion detection signals sent from the sensing element <b>110</b> are amplified and routed to the alarm indicator terminal <b>310</b>, then on to the alarm indicator <b>130</b>. Conversely, video signals from the camera <b>120</b> are routed to the video terminal <b>320</b> and on to the monitor <b>140</b>. In embodiments employing intrusion detection signals that are of greater magnitude than image signals, one of skill will observe that the reference voltage V<sub>ref </sub>input to the operational amplifier <b>330</b> can be set sufficiently high that only the presence of the intrusion detection signal, and not the image signals by themselves, will trigger the operational amplifier <b>330</b> to output a positive voltage. This voltage, in turn, induces an emitter-base current i sufficient to trigger the transistor <b>340</b> to pass a current that toggles the switch <b>350</b>, triggering the alarm indicator <b>130</b> to signal an alarm alerting the presence of an intrusion.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">While the intrusion detection signal acts to generate a signal that toggles the switch <b>350</b>, the image signals are amplified by amplifier <b>360</b> (similar to the amplifier <b>200</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) and output to the video terminal <b>320</b>. As these video or image signals can be superposed with intrusion detection signals, embodiments of the invention may also require known filters for attenuating the intrusion detection signals. Alternatively, the monitor <b>140</b> or other such monitoring device may be designed to filter or otherwise effectively ignore intrusion detection signals in known fashion.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">As previously mentioned, the sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b> are often co-located. As a result, some embodiments of the invention integrate both these components within a single housing. This single housing produces alarm systems that are particularly easy to install and use, as such alarm systems include both a single transmission line and a single housing. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref> illustrate various views of one such housing configuration. Here, a housing <b>400</b> includes a cover <b>410</b> that is a rigid protective cover with windows <b>420</b>. The housing <b>400</b> also has a base portion <b>430</b> that can be attached to a surface, and that is configured to support the sensing element <b>110</b> and camera <b>120</b> within. It may be desirable to provide light emitting diode (LED) lights <b>440</b> for illuminating the area monitored by the camera <b>120</b>. As noted above, the sensing element <b>110</b> can be any sensor capable of detecting an intrusion. Here, it is shown as a pyroelectric sensing element for sensing infrared radiation emitted by an intruder. Also, the camera <b>120</b> can be any imaging device, but here is shown as a complementary metal oxide semiconductor (CMOS) solid-state camera. The operation of the pyroelectric sensing element and CMOS camera are known.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref>, the cover <b>410</b> can be opened (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>) to allow access to the sensing element <b>110</b>, camera <b>120</b>, and lights <b>440</b> for repair or maintenance, and can be closed (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5B-5C</figref>) to protect these components during operation. When the cover <b>410</b> is closed, the windows <b>420</b> allow light in for the camera <b>120</b>, and allow light from the lights <b>440</b> out, so as to illuminate the location to be monitored. The illumination is turned on by the sensing element <b>110</b> upon sensing an intrusion, but only if a photocell (not shown) indicates that the ambient light is insufficient for the camera <b>20</b> to capture the image of the area. A lens <b>450</b> can also be incorporated into the cover <b>410</b> to allow a field of view for the sensing element <b>110</b>. This lens <b>450</b> can be a simple opening, or an optic lens, such as a fresnel lens, that focuses light upon the sensing element <b>110</b> in specified ways. Thus, the housing <b>400</b> containing lights <b>440</b>, camera <b>120</b> and sensing element <b>110</b> reflects a unique packaging of elements.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In embodiments employing a lens such as a fresnel lens, light paths to/from the sensing element <b>110</b> are modified so as to provide a field of view that facilitates the ability of the sensing element <b>110</b> to detect intrusion. More specifically, the lens <b>450</b> allows the sensing element <b>110</b> to better detect intrusion across a field of view. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A-6B</figref> illustrate top and side views, respectively, of the field of view of the camera <b>120</b> and sensing element <b>110</b> from within the housing <b>400</b>. As shown, the windows <b>420</b> allow the camera <b>120</b> to detect and capture images of any object within its image area. Also, the fresnel lens <b>450</b> focuses light from the detection areas shown, so as to facilitate detection of an intrusion when the intruder traverses from one detection area to an adjacent detection area. Thus, in known fashion, the sensing element <b>110</b> detects motion, and thus an intrusion, when an object moves from one detection area to another.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">One of skill will observe that the invention is not limited to embodiments employing housings, but rather merely discloses sensing elements and monitoring devices. Similarly, housings of the invention are not limited to single-housing configuration, nor to the configuration shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A-5C</figref>. Rather, the invention can include any housing having any configuration for supporting and/or protecting one or more components of an alarm system.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">The foregoing description, for purposes of explanation, used specific nomenclature to provide a thorough understanding of the invention. However, it will be apparent to one skilled in the art that the specific details are not required in order to practice the invention. Thus, the foregoing descriptions of specific embodiments of the present invention are presented for purposes of illustration and description. They are not intended to be exhaustive or to limit the invention to the precise forms disclosed. Many modifications and variations are possible in view of the above teachings. For example, alarm systems constructed according to the invention can employ any type and number of sensing element and any type of monitoring device. Similarly, the signals from these sensing elements and devices can be combined for transmission on any type of transmission line. The embodiments were chosen and described in order to best explain the principles of the invention and its practical applications, to thereby enable others skilled in the art to best utilize the invention and various embodiments with various modifications as are suited to the particular use contemplated.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An intrusion detection system comprising:
<claim-text>a detection element configured to detect an intrusion into a location, and to transmit an intrusion signal upon detection of the intrusion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a monitoring device configured to capture images of the location upon the detection of the intrusion, and to transmit image signals representing the captured images; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transmission line in electrical communication with the detection element and the monitoring device, the transmission line configured to carry the intrusion signals and the image signals;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the transmission line is a four wire transmission line.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The intrusion detection system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the detection element is a PIR detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The intrusion detection system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the detection element is a microwave detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The intrusion detection system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the detection element is a photo beam detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The intrusion detection system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the detection element is a glass break sensor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The intrusion detection system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the detection element is a door contact sensor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The intrusion detection system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the monitoring device is a video camera.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. An intrusion detection system comprising:
<claim-text>a detection element configured to detect an intrusion into a location, and to transmit an intrusion signal upon detection of the intrusion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a monitoring device configured to capture images of the location upon the detection of the intrusion, and to transmit image signals representing the captured images;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a transmission line in electrical communication with the detection element and the monitoring device, the transmission line configured to carry the intrusion signals and the image signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a combiner circuit in electrical communication with the transmission line and configured to combine the intrusion signal and the image signals so as to emit a combined signal to the transmission line; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a separator circuit in electrical communication with the transmission line and the combiner circuit;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the separator circuit is configured to receive the combined signal, and to transmit an alarm signal to a first signal receiving device, the alarm signal corresponding to the intrusion signal of the combined signal; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the separator circuit is further configured to transmit the image signals of the combined signal to a second signal receiving device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The intrusion detection system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the first signal receiving device is an alarm indicator configured to emit an indication of an alarm upon receiving the alarm signal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The intrusion detection system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref> wherein the second signal receiving device is a monitor configured to display the captured images upon receiving the image signals.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A transmission system for use in an intrusion detection system, comprising;
<claim-text>an electrical transmission line configured to be placed in simultaneous electrical communication with an intrusion detection element for detecting an intrusion, and an intrusion monitoring device for viewing details of the intrusion, wherein the electrical transmission line is further configured to be placed in simultaneous electrical communication with an alarm indicating device for initiating an alarm in response to receiving an alarm signal, and a display device for displaying images corresponding to the image signals;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a combiner circuit in electrical communication with the electrical transmission line, the combiner circuit configured to combine an intrusion signal received from the detection element with image signals received from the monitoring device, so as to transmit a combined signal along the electrical transmission line; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a separator circuit in electrical communication with the electrical transmission line, the separator circuit configured to receive the combined signal, to generate the alarm signal in response to the combined signal, to transmit the alarm signal along the electrical transmission line to the alarm indicating device, and to transmit the image signals of the combined signal along the electrical transmission line to the monitoring device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A transmission system for use in an intrusion detection system, comprising;
<claim-text>an electrical transmission line configured to be placed in simultaneous electrical communication with an intrusion detection element for detecting an intrusion, and an intrusion monitoring device for viewing details of the intrusion; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a combiner circuit in electrical communication with the electrical transmission line, the combiner circuit configured to combine an intrusion signal received from the detection element with image signals received from the monitoring device, so as to transmit a combined signal along the electrical transmission line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the electrical transmission line is a four wire cable.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the electrical transmission line is further configured to be placed in simultaneous electrical communication with an alarm indicating device for initiating an alarm in response to receiving an alarm signal, and a display device for displaying images corresponding to the image signals.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the display device is a video camera.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The transmission system of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref> wherein the intrusion detection element is a PIR sensor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method of detecting an intrusion, comprising:
<claim-text>generating an intrusion detection signal upon detecting an intrusion; transmitting the intrusion detection signal alone an electrical transmission line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating image signals corresponding to images of details of the intrusion; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the image signals along the electrical transmission line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the transmitting the intrusion detection signal further comprises transmitting the intrusion detection signal along a four wire cable, and wherein the transmitting the image signals further comprises transmitting the image signals along the four wire cable.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>receiving the intrusion detection signal and the image signals from the electrical transmission line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating an alarm signal in response to the receiving of the intrusion detection signal, the alarm signal configured to initiate an alarm;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the alarm signal to an alarm indicator; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>transmitting the image signals to a display device.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref> further comprising:
<claim-text>receiving the intrusion detection signal and the image signals from the electrical transmission line;</claim-text>
<claim-text>generating an alarm signal in response to the receiving of the intrusion detection signal, the alarm signal configured to initiate an alarm.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A unitary intrusion detection device comprising:
<claim-text>a housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a detection element, in said housing, configured to detect an intrusion into a location, and to transmit an intrusion signal upon detection of the intrusion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a monitoring device, in said housing, configured to capture images of the location upon the detection of the intrusion, and to transmit image signals representing the captured images;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an illumination element, in said housing, configured to illuminate the location; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a combiner circuit including a first input for receiving the intrusion signal, a second input for receiving the image signals, an output arranged to be electrically connected to an electrical transmission line, and processing circuitry configured to create a combined signal and transmit the combined signal to the output, the processing circuitry creating a combined signal representative of both the intrusion signal and the image signal, and configuring the combined signal for transmission over a single four wire cable transmission line.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the detection element is a PIR sensor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. The device of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00019">claim 19</claim-ref> wherein the detection element is a photo beam detector.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
