<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297227-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297227</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11333384</doc-number>
<date>20060118</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-347940</doc-number>
<date>20021129</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>D</section>
<class>21</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>11</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>162138</main-classification>
<further-classification>429129</further-classification>
<further-classification>429247</further-classification>
<further-classification>131365</further-classification>
<further-classification>131247</further-classification>
<further-classification>425294</further-classification>
<further-classification>425363</further-classification>
<further-classification>361502</further-classification>
<further-classification>361324</further-classification>
<further-classification>264105</further-classification>
<further-classification>264104</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Method of making sheet electrode for electric double layer capacitor and roller rolling machine suitable for use therein</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>59-036063</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19840200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>61-055047</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19860300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2-235320</doc-number>
<date>19900900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>04-064210</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19920200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>05-228537</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19930900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>07-081820</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19950300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-288852</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>19991000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2000-150321</doc-number>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-068539</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20020300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2002-149911</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20020500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>2</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>162138</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>252567</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>429129</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>429247</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>131365</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361502</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361324</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>264105</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>264104</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425294</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>425363</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<division>
<relation>
<parent-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10724360</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20031201</date>
</document-id>
<parent-grant-document>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7077932</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
</document-id>
</parent-grant-document>
</parent-doc>
<child-doc>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11333384</doc-number>
</document-id>
</child-doc>
</relation>
</division>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060115550</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060601</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Ozaki</last-name>
<first-name>Kouki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Aichi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Tsutsui</last-name>
<first-name>Masanori</first-name>
<address>
<city>Aichi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Iwaida</last-name>
<first-name>Manabu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Saitama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Oyama</last-name>
<first-name>Shigeki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Saitama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Murakami</last-name>
<first-name>Kenichi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Saitama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Browdy and Neimark, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Daido Metal Company Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Aichi</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Honda Motor Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Tokyo</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Halpern</last-name>
<first-name>Mark</first-name>
<department>1731</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A sheet electrode with a predetermined thickness for an electric double layer capacitor is made by carrying out a roller rolling step in which a long sheet intermediate is made from a material containing a carbonaceous powder, a conductive assistant and a binder and thereafter. The sheet intermediate is passed between a pair of rolling rollers to be wound up by a winding section while being drawn out of a drawing section. The roller rolling step includes drawing the sheet intermediate out of the drawing section under a predetermined tension applied to the sheet intermediate, and controlling a widthwise position of the sheet intermediate immediately before the rolling rollers by an edge position controller, and winding the sheet intermediate rolled by the rollers onto a winding section while the winding section is applying a predetermined pressure to a rolling side drive roller located adjacent to the winding section and rotated at a predetermined speed.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="116.67mm" wi="222.25mm" file="US07297227-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="209.30mm" wi="117.77mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297227-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="222.76mm" wi="132.84mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297227-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS-REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present application is a divisional of parent application Ser. No. 10/724,360, filed Dec. 1, 2003 now U.S. Pat. No. 7,077,932, and claiming priority from Japanese application 2002-347940 filed Nov. 29, 2002. The entire contents of these applications are hereby incorporated by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">This invention relates to a method of making a sheet electrode for an electric double layer capacitor by rolling a sheet intermediate using rollers and a roller rolling machine suitable for use in the method.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Electric double layer capacitors have a large capacity and an excellent charge and discharge cycle property. Therefore, their application to various appliances has been examined. The application includes backup power supplies for various electronic devices and batteries for means of transportation such as automobiles.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The above-mentioned electric double layer capacitors include a cylindrical type. In the cylindrical electric double layer capacitor, a pair of positive and negative electrodes each comprise a sheet electrode (polarizable electrode) held on a collecting electrode such as aluminum foil. The paired electrodes are wound into a coil with a separator interposed therebetween. The wound paired electrodes are accommodated in a cylindrical case while being impregnated with electrolyte.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The aforesaid sheet electrode is obtained by kneading carbon powder such as activated carbon, conductive assistant such as carbon black, a binder such as fluorocarbon resin, a binding assistant comprising a liquid lubricant such as alcohol, thereby obtaining a kneaded material. The kneaded material is formed into the aforesaid sheet electrode. JP-A-2000-150321 discloses rolling the above-mentioned kneaded material with use of rollers. Furthermore, JP-A-2-235320 discloses another rolling method with use of rollers. The kneaded material is rolled by rollers to be formed into a preparatory intermediate having a thickness of 1 mm. The preparatory intermediate is dried so that the liquid lubricant is eliminated. Thereafter, the preparatory intermediate is re-rolled by the rollers to be formed into a sheet electrode having a thickness of 0.25 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A long continuous sheet electrode is required in order that a cylindrical electric double layer capacitor with a large capacity as described above may be made. Furthermore, the sheet electrode is desired to have a sufficiently small thickness and a sufficient accuracy. However, the material comprising activated carbon as a main component has a low strength and accordingly, ends of the sheet electrode are easy to be broken or cracked. Thus, it is difficult to make a sufficiently thin and long sheet electrode by rolling. The above-cited JP-A-2-235320 further discloses that an end of the preparatory intermediate is placed on an end of another intermediate so that the rolled sheet electrode is rendered longer. However, this manner complicates the rolling.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Therefore, an object of the present invention is to provide a method of stably making a sufficiently thin and long sheet electrode for the electric double layer capacitor by roller rolling.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Another object of the invention is to provide a roller rolling apparatus suitable for use in the method.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The inventors repeated trial and error in order to desirably carry out the roller rolling to stably manufacture a long sheet electrode with a small thickness but without breakage and crack together with study of materials. As a result, the inventors invented a method which is suitable for roller rolling.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present invention provides a method of making a sheet electrode with a predetermined thickness for an electric double layer capacitor by carrying out a roller rolling process in which a long sheet intermediate is made from a material containing a carbonaceous powder, a conductive assistant and a binder and thereafter, the sheet intermediate is passed between a pair of rolling rollers to be wound up by a winding section while being drawn out of a drawing section. The roller rolling process includes drawing the sheet intermediate out of the drawing section under a predetermined tension applied to the sheet intermediate, and controlling a widthwise position of the sheet intermediate immediately before the rolling rollers by an edge position controller, and winding the sheet intermediate rolled by the rollers onto a winding section while the winding section is applying a predetermined pressure to a rolling side drive roller located adjacent to the winding section and rotated at a predetermined speed.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In the above-described method, the sheet intermediate is drawn from the drawing section under the predetermined tension applied thereto. Consequently, the sheet intermediate can be fed continuously to the rolling roller side while being prevented from occurrence of crack or the like due to excessively large or small tension. Furthermore, the drawn sheet intermediate is passed between the rolling rollers to be rolled while the widthwise position of the intermediate is controlled by the edge position controller. Consequently, the sheet intermediate can be rolled stably while the edge of the intermediate can be prevented from being bent thereby to be partially overlapped and from occurrence of breakage, crack or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">On the other hand, in the winding section, the winding roller is not directly driven to wind the sheet electrode, but the sheet electrode is wound up on the winding roller while the winding roller is pressed against a winding side drive roller by a predetermined pressure. Accordingly, even when a diameter of a roll of wound sheet electrode varies or gradually increases, a predetermined winding speed can be maintained or the sheet electrode can be wound under a predetermined tension applied thereto. Thus, the sheet electrode can be wound stably while crack, tear or the like can be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Thus, although a material (sheet intermediate) containing a carbonaceous powder such as activated carbon as a main composition has a low strength or is brittle, the rolling can be carried out stably and consequently, a continuous long sheet electrode having a sufficient thickness and accuracy can be manufactured stably.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">When previously made from a forming material, a long sheet intermediate can be made into a sufficiently thin sheet electrode in the subsequent roller rolling step. An experimental apparatus made by the inventors shows that a sheet electrode having suitable dimensions was obtained when a sheet intermediate having a thickness of about 200 μm was rolled two or three times into the sheet electrode with a thickness of 160 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Activated carbon is primarily used as the carbonaceous powder made into a forming material. However, a carbon nanotube or fibrous carbon maybe used as the carbonaceous powder, instead. Carbon black is primarily used as the conductive assistant. However, a fine particle of high conductive metal may be used as the conductive assistant, instead. A fluororesin powder such as polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE) can be used as the binder.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In making the forming material, the above-noted components are desirably mixed at a suitable mixing ratio, kneaded and then pulverized to be granulated so as to have a suitable particle size distribution. Subsequently, a suitable amount of binding assistant is added so that a forming material suitable for the previous forming can be obtained. The binding assistant may include alcohol such as isopropyl alcohol, ether, ketone or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The present invention also provides a roller rolling machine rolling the aforesaid sheet intermediate into a sheet electrode with a predetermined thickness for an electric double layer capacitor. The apparatus comprises a tension control device controlling a tension of the sheet intermediate drawn out of the drawing section so that the tension is constant, an edge position control device controlling a widthwise position of the sheet intermediate located immediately before the rolling rollers, a winding side drive roller located adjacent to the winding section so as to be rotated at a predetermined speed, and a pressing element applying a predetermined pressure to the winding side drive roller so that the winding section is pressed against the drive roller.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Although a material (sheet intermediate) containing a carbonaceous powder such as activated carbon as a main composition has a low strength or is brittle as described above, the rolling can be carried out stably and consequently, a continuous long sheet electrode having a sufficient thickness and accuracy can be manufactured stably. Thus, the apparatus is suitable for carrying out the above-described method.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Other objects, features and advantages of the present invention will become clear upon reviewing the following description of the embodiment, made with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> schematically illustrates an overall process of manufacturing the sheet electrode in accordance with an embodiment of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic front view of the construction of the roller rolling machine in accordance with the embodiment of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">An embodiment of the present invention will be described with reference to the drawings. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, an overall process of manufacturing a sheet electrode for an electric double layer capacitor is schematically shown. In the embodiment, sheet electrodes manufactured by the method of the present invention are bonded to both sides of a long aluminum foil serving as a collector electrode respectively, whereby an electrode sheet is manufactured. The electrode sheet is then dried into a product. The embodiment covers as far as the drying process. The aforesaid electrode sheet has a length of some hundreds meters. The electrode sheet is used, for example, as a material for a cylindrical electric double layer capacitor of large capacity type. In the following description, a polarizable electrode of the cylindrical double layer capacitor will be referred to as “sheet electrode.” The aluminum foil having both sides to which the sheet electrodes are bonded respectively will be referred to as “electrode sheet.”</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Manufacturing the electrode sheet includes a measuring process P<b>1</b>, a mixing process P<b>2</b>, a kneading process P<b>3</b>, a crushing process P<b>4</b>, a calendering process P<b>5</b>, a roller rolling process P<b>6</b>, a laminating process P<b>7</b> and a drying process P<b>8</b> all of which are carried out sequentially. Each process will be described in brief.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Firstly, materials used for manufacture of the sheet electrode are each measured in the measuring process P<b>1</b>. The materials include activated carbon serving as a carbonaceous powder, fine powder of carbon black serving as an electrically conductive assistant, and PTFE powder serving as a binder. The activated carbon, carbon black and PTFE are in the ratio of 8:1:1, for example. Furthermore, isopropyl alcohol (hereinafter, “IPA”) is used as a binder assistant in the embodiment.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In the mixing process P<b>2</b>, the activated carbon and carbon black are mixed together using a mixer. In the mixing, measured activated carbon and carbon black are put into a container of the mixer. An agitating blade is rotated for a predetermined period of time so that fine powder of carbon black is distributed uniformly among the activated carbon particles. Furthermore, PTFE and IPA are put into the container, and the agitating blade is rotated for the mixing purpose. As a result, the activated carbon and the carbon black are mixed further uniformly so that fine powder of carbon black is distributed uniformly among the activated carbon particles and so that PTFE is fiberized thereby to entwine the activated carbon and carbon black.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">In the kneading process P<b>3</b>, a mixture obtained in the mixing process P<b>2</b> is kneaded by a kneader. A container of the kneader is filled with the mixture and then closed by a cover. A blade is then driven while the mixture is pressurized. Temperatures of the container, the cover and the blade of the kneader are controlled so as to be maintained at about 90° C., for example. Furthermore, the hardness of a kneaded substance is also controlled. Consequently, PTFE is further fiberized to further entwine the activated carbon and the carbon black, whereupon the kneaded substance presents a state just like a lump of rubber.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">In the crushing process P<b>4</b>, the kneaded substance obtained in the kneading process P<b>3</b> is crushed into fine grain (crushed grain). In this step, the kneaded substance is put into a container of a crushing machine and a crushing blade is rotated so that the kneaded substance is crushed.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In the calendering process P<b>5</b>, a long sheet intermediate is previously made from a forming material comprising the aforesaid crushed grain. The forming material is put into a hopper of a calendering machine. The forming material fed out of the output section of the hopper is made by two calender rolls into a continuous plate-shape. The obtained sheet intermediate is wound up by a winding roller. The obtained sheet intermediate has the thickness of about 200 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In the subsequent roller rolling process P<b>6</b>, the aforesaid sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is continuously rolled by a roller rolling machine <b>26</b> in accordance with the present invention, whereby a long sheet electrode <b>27</b> with a predetermined thickness (160 μm, for example) is manufactured. In the embodiment, the roller rolling process is repeatedly carried out a plurality of times (two or three times). In the final process, opposite edges of the sheet electrode <b>27</b> are cut off so that the sheet electrode has a predetermined width. This process is also referred to as “slitting process.” The roller rolling process P<b>6</b> and the roller rolling machine <b>26</b> will be described in detail later.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In the laminating process P<b>7</b>, two sheets of aluminum foil serving as collector electrodes are laminated onto both sides of the sheet electrode <b>27</b> by a laminator, whereby an electrode sheet is formed. In the subsequent drying process P<b>8</b>, a roll of wound electrode sheet is drawn out to be passed through a drying chamber for the drying purpose. In this case, hot air produced by a heater is supplied into the drying chamber. IPA and most of water contained in the sheet electrode <b>27</b> are eliminated in the drying process. Vacuum drying may also be carried out, if required.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The roller rolling process P<b>6</b> and the roller rolling machine <b>26</b> will now be described in detail with particular reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> schematically illustrates the construction of the roller rolling machine <b>26</b> in accordance with the embodiment of the invention. The roller rolling machine <b>26</b> includes a drawing section <b>41</b> constituting a left-hand end thereof as viewed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. A bobbin <b>41</b> of a rolled sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is set in the drawing section <b>41</b>. The drawing section <b>41</b> is provided with a tension controller <b>42</b> serving as a tension controlling unit as will be described in detail later. The roller rolling of the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is repeatedly carried out a plurality of times so that a sheet electrode <b>27</b> is manufactured. Although the sheet electrode <b>27</b> is obtained after execution of a final roller rolling, any intermediate product under rolling process will also be referred to as the “sheet intermediate <b>22</b>” when such an intermediate product need not be distinguished from the sheet intermediate.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The sheet intermediate <b>22</b> drawn from the drawing section <b>41</b> is caught on a guide roller <b>43</b> and thereafter passes through two tracking rollers <b>45</b> and <b>46</b> of an edge position controller <b>44</b> which will be referred to as “EPC.” The sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is introduced via a guide roller <b>47</b> between a pair of upper and lower rolling rollers <b>48</b> and <b>49</b>. The rolling rollers <b>48</b> and <b>49</b> are rotated by electric motors (not shown) in the directions of arrows A and B at predetermined speeds respectively, so that the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is passed between the rollers <b>48</b> and <b>49</b> thereby to be rolled.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">An article rolled by the rolling rollers <b>48</b> and <b>49</b> or the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> passes guide rollers <b>50</b> and <b>51</b> in turn and further passes a driving roller <b>52</b> provided at the winding side to be rotated by an electric motor or the like, whereupon the sheet intermediate is wound onto a winding bobbin <b>54</b> of a winding section <b>53</b>. In this case, the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is rolled up by touch roll. Furthermore, a cutting blade <b>62</b> constituting a slitting unit is provided near the driving roller <b>52</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The tension controller <b>42</b> comprises a proximity switch <b>56</b> detecting rotation of a shaft of the drawing section <b>41</b> in which the bobbin <b>40</b> is to be set, a powder brake <b>57</b> braking the shaft of the drawing section, an input section <b>58</b> operated by an operator so that various set values such as tension, material thickness, initial winding diameter and the like are supplied into the tension controller, and a control section <b>59</b> controlling the powder brake <b>57</b> on the basis of the aforesaid set values and detection by the proximity switch <b>56</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The control section <b>59</b> obtains, by calculation, a rotational speed of the bobbin <b>40</b> from a detection signal delivered by the proximity switch <b>56</b>. The control section <b>59</b> further obtains, by calculation, a current winding diameter from the calculated current rotational speed, the aforesaid initial winding diameter, and the aforesaid material thickness. Based on the obtained current winding diameter, the control section <b>59</b> obtains a braking force for achieving the set tension and controls the powder brake <b>57</b> so that the obtained braking force is applied to the shaft. Consequently, the tension controller <b>42</b> controls the tension of the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> drawn out of the drawing section <b>41</b> is maintained at a predetermined value.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The two parallel tracking rolls <b>45</b> and <b>46</b> of EPC <b>44</b> are supported on a moving frame, which is rockable about the center of the in-feed side tracking roll <b>45</b>. An edge sensor <b>60</b> is provided in order to detect an edge (widthwise end) of the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> at the delivery side (at the side of the rolling rolls <b>48</b> and <b>49</b>). Based on the result of detection by the edge sensor <b>60</b>, the control section <b>59</b> controls a rocking position of the moving frame, whereby meander of the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is corrected. Thus, the widthwise position of the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> (a biting position and angle of the sheet intermediate relative to the rolling rollers <b>48</b> and <b>49</b>) is controlled immediately before the rolling rollers <b>48</b> and <b>49</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In the winding section <b>53</b>, the rolled sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is wound onto the winding side driving roller <b>52</b> provided adjacent to the winding section <b>53</b> while being pressed by a predetermined pressure onto the winding bobbin <b>54</b> in a direction of void arrow G in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. After having passed between the rolling rollers <b>48</b> and <b>49</b>, the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is caught on the driving roller <b>52</b> so as to adhere to an approximately upper half circumference of the roller, thereafter being wound onto the bobbin <b>54</b> at its lower side.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">When the driving roller <b>52</b> is rotated in the direction of arrow C at a predetermined speed while the rolled sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is pressed against the driving roller <b>52</b> by a predetermined pressure, the bobbin <b>54</b> is rotated in the direction of arrow D so that the sheet electrode <b>27</b> is wound at a predetermined speed.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A slitting apparatus <b>61</b> serving as a slitting unit is provided over the driving roller <b>52</b> for cutting both widthwise ends of the sheet electrode <b>27</b> to be wound so that the sheet electrode has a predetermined width. When a slitting process is carried out with the roller rolling process, the slitting apparatus <b>61</b> is positioned so that an edge of a cutting blade <b>62</b> is pressed against the upper half part of the roller <b>52</b> to which the sheet electrode <b>27</b> is adherent. As a result, both widthwise ends of the sheet electrode <b>27</b> are cut at a location immediately before being wound on the bobbin <b>54</b> after the final roller rolling.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">More specifically, the sheet electrode <b>27</b> obtained by the roller rolling sometimes has an irregular width and differences in the thickness in the widthwise ends thereof (a low density part) or cracks. Accordingly, it is preferred that both widthwise ends of the sheet electrode <b>27</b> are cut so that the sheet electrode has a predetermined width. The slitting process using a cutting blade <b>62</b> is carried out for the aforesaid purposes. When the cutting blade <b>62</b> is pressed against the sheet electrode <b>27</b> wound on the drive roller <b>52</b> to be cut, the stability of the sheet electrode <b>27</b> during the cutting can be improved such that the sheet electrode can smoothly be cut. Consequently, a dimensional accuracy can be improved, and an occurrence of crack at a cut portion can be prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In the roller rolling process P<b>6</b>, roller rolling is carried out for the long sheet intermediate <b>22</b> formed at the calendering process P<b>5</b>, twice using the above-described roller rolling machine <b>26</b>. More specifically, in the first rolling, the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is set in the drawing section <b>41</b> and is caused to pass through rollers sequentially as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. The sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is then passed between the paired rolling rollers <b>48</b> and <b>49</b> to be rolled, thereafter being continuously wound up onto the winding section <b>53</b> as an intermediate rolled product.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In this case, the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is drawn out from the drawing section <b>41</b> while being tensioned by the tension controller <b>42</b>. As a result, crack or the like due to an excessively large or small tension can be prevented when the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is continuously fed to the rolling rollers side. Furthermore, the drawn sheet intermediate <b>22</b> is passed between the rolling rollers <b>48</b> and <b>49</b> while the widthwise position thereof is under control by EPC <b>44</b>. Consequently, the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> can be rolled stably while the edge of the intermediate can be prevented from being bent thereby to be partially overlapped and from occurrence of breakage, crack or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In the winding section <b>53</b>, the winding bobbin <b>54</b> is not directly driven to wind the sheet electrode, but the sheet electrode (rolled intermediate) is wound up on the winding bobbin <b>54</b> while the winding bobbin is pressed against a winding side drive roller <b>52</b> by a predetermined pressure (touch roll). Accordingly, even when a diameter of a roll of wound sheet electrode varies or gradually increases, a predetermined winding speed can be maintained or the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> or the sheet electrode <b>27</b> can be wound under a predetermined tension applied thereto. Thus, the sheet intermediate or the sheet electrode can be wound stably while crack, tear or the like can be prevented. In the first rolling, the cutting blade <b>62</b> is located at a retreated position from the contact of the drive roller <b>52</b> and accordingly the slitting process is not carried out.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Upon completion of the first rolling, an obtained intermediate rolled product is set in the drawing section <b>41</b> so that a second rolling is carried out in the same manner as the first rolling. In the second rolling, the cutting blade <b>62</b> of the slitting apparatus <b>61</b> is set at a predetermined position, and the slitting step is executed in which both edges of the sheet electrode <b>27</b> are cut off so that a predetermined width of the sheet is obtained. Consequently, an obtained long sheet electrode <b>27</b> has a predetermined thickness (160 μm, for example) and a predetermined width (120 mm, for example).</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Thus, in spite of a low strength (high brittleness) of the material comprising activated carbon as a main component the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> can be rolled stably while crack, tear or the like is prevented. Consequently, a continuous long sheet electrode <b>27</b> having a sufficient thickness and accuracy can be manufactured stably. In the embodiment, the sheet intermediate <b>22</b> having a thickness of 200 μm can be formed into the sheet electrode having a thickness of 160 μm as the result of execution of the first and second rolling steps.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">As obvious from the foregoing description of the embodiment, the long sheet electrode <b>27</b> for the electric double layer capacitor has a sufficient thickness and accuracy and can be manufactured stably. Additionally, the roller rolling machine <b>26</b> employed in the embodiment is suitable for execution of the above-described manufacturing method.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The roller rolling is repeated twice in the foregoing embodiment so that the obtained sheet electrode <b>27</b> has a desired thickness. The roller rolling may be carried out only once or three times or more. Furthermore, the slitting apparatus <b>61</b> is constructed so that the cutting blade is pressed against the drive roller <b>52</b>. However, the cutting blade may be pressed against another guide roller provided at the winding side. Furthermore, an intended end can be achieved even when the slitting apparatus <b>61</b> is provided integrally on the roller rolling machine <b>26</b>. Alternatively, a slitting apparatus having a different construction may be provided, instead. Thus, the construction of the roller rolling machine <b>26</b> may be changed. For example, the arrangement of the tension controller <b>42</b> or EPC <b>44</b> may be modified. Furthermore, various types of components may be combined or blended together regarding the forming material. Additionally, the processes other than the roller rolling process P<b>6</b> are mere examples and may be partially changed or eliminated.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The foregoing description and drawings are merely illustrative of the principles of the present invention and are not to be construed in a limiting sense. Various changes and modifications will become apparent to those of ordinary skill in the art. All such changes and modifications are seen to fall within the scope of the invention as defined by the appended claims.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Thus the expressions “means to . . . ” and “means for . . . ”, or any method step language, as may be found in the specification above and/or in the claims below, followed by a functional statement, are intended to define and cover whatever structural, physical, chemical or electrical element or structure, or whatever method step, which may now or in the future exist which carries out the recited function, whether or not precisely equivalent to the embodiment or embodiments disclosed in the specification above, i.e., other means or steps for carrying out the same functions can be used; and it is intended that such expressions be given their broadest interpretation.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A roller rolling machine making a sheet electrode with a predetermined thickness for an electric double layer capacitor by carrying out a rolling step, said machine comprising:
<claim-text>(a) A pair of rolling rollers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(b) a winding section for winding up the rollers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(c) a drawing section for drawing out the rollers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(d) a tension control device for controlling tension of a sheet drawn out of the drawing section so that the tension on the sheet is constant;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(e) an edge position control device for controlling a widthwise position of the sheet, said edge position control device being located immediately before the rolling rollers;</claim-text>
<claim-text>(f) a winding side drive roller located adjacent to the winding section so as to be rotated at a predetermined speed; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>(g) a pressing element for applying a predetermined pressure to a drive roller on the winding side so that the winding section is pressed against the winding side drive roller.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The roller rolling machine according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a slitting unit for slitting both widthwise ends of the rolled sheet so that the sheet has a predetermined width, wherein the rolled sheet is caught on and adhered to the drive roller and the slitting unit includes a slitting blade pressed against the drive roller, the slitting blade being displaceable between a retreated position from the drive roller and a position where the slitting blade is pressed against the drive roller.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
