<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298246-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298246</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11106746</doc-number>
<date>20050415</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>242</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>60</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>25</main-group>
<subgroup>10</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>04</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3404261</main-classification>
<further-classification>34042616</further-classification>
<further-classification>34042618</further-classification>
<further-classification>34042627</further-classification>
<further-classification>340566</further-classification>
<further-classification>381 56</further-classification>
<further-classification>381 86</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Vehicle security monitoring device</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5335264</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Namekawa</name>
<date>19940800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5623245</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Gilmore</name>
<date>19970400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5812054</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Cohen</name>
<date>19980900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5838227</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Murray</name>
<date>19981100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6107914</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Greene</name>
<date>20000800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6259362</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lin</name>
<date>20010700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6337621</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ogino et al.</name>
<date>20020100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6433683</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Robinson</name>
<date>20020800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>340540</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6480098</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Flick</name>
<date>20021100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6563421</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Wheeler</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>34053914</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0130765</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Flick</name>
<date>20020900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0016834</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Blanco et al.</name>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>381 91</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>22</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>3404261</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>4</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60562400</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20040415</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Schmitt</last-name>
<first-name>William J.</first-name>
<address>
<street>11900 Grason La.</street>
<city>Bowie</city>
<state>MD</state>
<postcode>20715</postcode>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Reed Smith LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Crosland</last-name>
<first-name>Donnie L.</first-name>
<department>2612</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A vehicle security monitoring device monitors sound or movement within a vehicle to determine an abnormal condition such as intrusion of a thief. Upon determination, the device transmits sound picked up within the vehicle to a portable monitor unit carried by the owner of the vehicle using a dedicated link without using any communications network. The transmitted sound allows the owner to distinguish between an actual intrusion and false alarm. Upon verification of an actual intrusion, the portable monitor unit allows the owner to send various instructions to prevent theft of any valuables in the vehicle or theft of the vehicle itself. The instructions may include playing of warning messages, activation of a siren and disabling of the vehicle.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="86.78mm" wi="211.33mm" file="US07298246-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="218.02mm" wi="113.45mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298246-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="220.81mm" wi="147.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298246-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="148.59mm" wi="150.03mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298246-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="250.19mm" wi="170.01mm" file="US07298246-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority to U.S. provisional application No. 60/562,400, filed Apr. 15, 2004, which is incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to an electronic vehicle security system, and more particularly, a vehicle monitoring device to deter theft of valuables in the vehicle or theft of the vehicle itself.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Anti-theft devices which prevent auto theft are conventionally known. A thief may attempt to steal a vehicle or valuables in the vehicle that has been installed with such an anti-theft device by opening a door of the vehicle, opening a trunk, or by breaking a window. Sensors such as motion detectors, vibration detectors, sound detectors, shock sensors, pressure sensors and mechanical switches are used to detect such an intrusion. Upon detection of the intrusion, the anti-theft device actuates a siren and flashes the vehicle headlamps to ward off the thief.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">However, the sensors in the anti-theft devices are prone to false actuations. For example, a shock sensor may be actuated by force applied from the outside or a sound sensor may be actuated by excessive external noise without any thief being present. False alarms inconvenience the owner who has to return to the vehicle to turn off the alarm as well as the neighbors who must endure the siren noise until the owner turns off the alarm. On the other hand, when the vehicle is actually being stolen, it may be sometimes dangerous for the owner to approach the vehicle alone. In both cases, the owner will want to ascertain the status of the vehicle before approaching the vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">U.S. Pat. No. 5,335,264 to Namekawa discloses a vehicle security system including a vehicle mounted unit, a vehicle mounted cellular telephone unit and a hand-held remote unit, which is incorporated herein by reference. When the vehicle unit detects an abnormal condition, it sends an alarm signal to the remote unit and turns on the cellular telephone within the vehicle so that it is ready to receive a call, presumably the owner who has received the alarm signal through the remote unit. When the telephone call is received and an “inside sound receiving code” is also received, the vehicle unit connects the cellular telephone's microphone to the transmitter so that the sound within the vehicle can be monitored through the owner's cellular telephone.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">However, a problem with the Namekawa system is that it relies on a public cellular telephone network. That means that the system will not operate if either the cellular telephone in the vehicle or the owner's cellular telephone is outside of the telephone service area. Another problem with the Namekawa system is that once intrusion has been detected, no action may be taken if the owner's remote control unit does not receive the indication of intrusion detection. For example, the remote control unit may have been intentionally turned off by the owner or the battery may have died. In that case, there is nothing to prevent the intruder from stealing the vehicle or any component of the vehicle. Moreover, even if the owner verifies an actual intrusion through the sound monitoring, the Namekawa system does not provide any way to prevent the theft.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Therefore, it is desirable to provide improved anti-theft system that does not rely on connection to a telephone network. It is also desirable to provide the system with an ability to prevent the theft once intrusion has been verified.</p>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE DISCLOSURE</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">According to one aspect of the invention, a vehicle security monitoring device is provided. The device includes a vehicle unit located in a vehicle and a portable monitor unit designed to be carried by an owner of the vehicle. A controller of the vehicle unit is capable of determining an abnormal condition of the vehicle such as an intrusion by a thief. Upon determination of such condition, the controller connects a microphone located in the vehicle to a transceiver to transmit the sound coming from the vehicle. A transceiver of the portable unit is designed to communicate directly with the vehicle unit transceiver without using a communications network to receive the transmitted sound signal. By not relying on any communications network, the vehicle security monitoring device of the present invention can work in areas where there is no public or third party communications network or where the network is down for any reason. Also, the transmitted sound allows the owner to distinguish between an actual intrusion and false alarm.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">In another aspect of the invention, the controller in the vehicle unit uses the microphone output to detect the abnormal condition. For example, the abnormal condition may be determined when the level of sound picked up by the microphone increases above a selected threshold level.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In another aspect of the invention, the controller in the vehicle unit uses an output of a movement sensor that detects movement of an object inside the vehicle to detect the abnormal condition. Alternatively, a combination of the microphone output and the movement sensor output can be used to determine the abnormal condition.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">In another aspect of the invention, the vehicle unit includes a memory storing an audio data that contains a voice announcement that warns an intruder. Upon determination of the abnormal condition or the vehicle, the controller is capable of playing the stored audio data through a speaker.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In another aspect of the invention, the controller can activate a siren in the vehicle when the sound level from the microphone does not decrease after the stored audio data has been played at least one.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">In another aspect of the present invention, the vehicle unit and the portable monitor unit are in regular communication with each other. However, if the vehicle unit loses communication with the portable monitor unit, the vehicle unit can be placed in an unattended mode. The vehicle unit can also be placed into the unattended mode if it receives an instruction from the portable monitoring unit to do so.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In another aspect of the present invention, the portable monitor unit activates a visual or audio alert when the portable monitor unit goes out of communication range with the vehicle unit.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a vehicle security monitoring device according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a schematic diagram of a vehicle unit according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a schematic diagram of a portable monitor unit according to the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a flowchart of a security monitoring and theft prevention process according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The present invention will now be described more fully hereinafter with reference to the accompanying drawings. This invention may, however, be embodied in many different forms and should not be construed as limited to the embodiments set forth herein. Rather, these embodiments are provided so that this disclosure will be thorough and complete, and will fully convey the scope of the invention to those skilled in the art. Like numbers refer to similar elements throughout.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a vehicle security monitoring device <b>2</b> according to the present invention. The device <b>2</b> includes a vehicle unit <b>10</b> mounted inside a vehicle <b>4</b> and a portable monitor unit <b>50</b> to be carried by a vehicle owner that communicates with the vehicle unit. The portable unit <b>50</b> is typically powered by a battery (not shown) while the vehicle unit <b>10</b> is typically powered from the vehicle's battery although the vehicle unit also has an internal backup battery (not shown) in case power is interrupted.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> is a schematic diagram of the vehicle unit <b>10</b> according to the present invention. A transmitter <b>12</b> and receiver <b>14</b> are both connected to an antenna <b>16</b> for direct communication with the portable monitor unit <b>50</b>. A controller <b>18</b>, which includes a processor circuit, controls all of the functions of the vehicle unit <b>10</b> such as sensor monitoring and detection of any abnormal conditions, communication with the portable monitor unit <b>50</b>, activation of any alarm conditions and the like. A memory <b>20</b> coupled to the controller <b>18</b> stores software programs or code to be executed by the controller. The memory <b>20</b> also stores digital audio data (stored as a file) that contain voice announcements that warn an intruder. The digital audio files may be in various encoding formats such as “mp3”, “.wav” or the like. An I/O interface <b>22</b> connected to the controller <b>18</b> controls signals coming from the various input devices and signals going to the various output devices. As most of the input and output devices work with analog signals, part of the I/O interface's job is to convert the signals into digital signals that can be worked on by the controller <b>18</b>. The output devices connected to the I/O interface <b>22</b> include a speaker <b>24</b> used to play the digital audio files, siren <b>26</b> and head lights <b>28</b> for alerting the owner and others that the vehicle is being burglarized, and a kill switch <b>30</b> to kill the vehicle engine. The input devices connected to the I/O interface <b>22</b> include a microphone <b>32</b> for picking up sound generated in an area in and near the vehicle, a video camera <b>34</b> mounted within the vehicle <b>4</b> to pick up images within and near the vehicle, motion sensor <b>36</b> to detect movement of the vehicle <b>4</b>, movement sensor <b>38</b> (such as an infrared sensor) that senses any movement of any object within the vehicle, and any other input device <b>40</b> such as a door switch that can be used to sense intrusion or unauthorized entry into the vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> is a schematic diagram of the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> according to the present invention. The portable monitor unit <b>50</b> is a dedicated unit that is specially designed to work with the vehicle unit <b>10</b>. “Dedicated” means that the portable unit <b>50</b> is adapted to communicate with the vehicle unit <b>10</b> without any additional communication unit such as a repeater or telephone switching communications network. A transmitter <b>52</b> and receiver <b>54</b> are both connected to an antenna <b>56</b> for direct communication with the vehicle unit <b>10</b>. Because the communication link between the vehicle unit and the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> is a direct link and the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> is a dedicated hardware unit, any communication between the two units does not go through any communications network such as the telephone network. As a result, the vehicle security monitoring device <b>2</b> according to the present invention advantageously works in all areas regardless of whether the portable monitor unit or the vehicle <b>4</b> is outside of the communications network service area.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">A controller <b>58</b>, which includes a processor circuit, controls all of the functions of the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> such as communication with the vehicle unit <b>50</b>, activation of any intrusion alert devices such as a vibrator <b>65</b> or light (not shown). A memory <b>60</b> coupled to the controller <b>58</b> stores software programs or code to be executed by the controller <b>58</b>. The memory <b>60</b> also is capable of storing video images transmitted from the video camera <b>34</b> installed in the vehicle <b>4</b>. An I/O interface <b>62</b> connects a microphone <b>64</b>, vibrator <b>65</b> and speaker <b>66</b> to the controller <b>18</b>. The speaker <b>66</b> plays the sound picked up by the microphone <b>32</b> and transmitted by the transmitter <b>12</b> of the vehicle unit <b>10</b>. The microphone <b>64</b> can be used to pick up the owner's voice to be transmitted to the vehicle unit <b>50</b> through the transmitter <b>52</b>. The receiver <b>14</b> in the vehicle unit <b>10</b> receives the voice and plays it through the speaker <b>24</b>. This feature may be more effective in deterring theft because unlike the prerecorded audio messages, the live voice of the owner indicates to the intruder that the owner is aware of the intrusion and that he will actively attempt to interfere with the theft.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The vehicle unit <b>10</b> is always in communication with the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> to ensure that commands/instructions and alert conditions can be sent to and from each other. For example, in the embodiment shown, a “link-up” feature is implemented wherein the vehicle unit <b>10</b> and the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> exchanged idle data every 30 seconds. In addition, the vehicle unit <b>10</b> transmits a status signal every 5 seconds to which no response is necessary from the portable monitor unit <b>50</b>. If the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> were to lose communication, e.g., if the monitor unit fails to receive either the 5 second signal or the 30 second signal, the controller <b>58</b> in the monitor unit <b>50</b> is designed to send a beeping sound through the speaker <b>66</b>. The controller also activates the vibrator <b>65</b> connected to the I/O interface <b>62</b> to warn the owner that the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> has lost communication with the vehicle unit <b>10</b>. The vibrator <b>65</b> may be, for example, a piezoelectric vibrator as is well known in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">An operation of the vehicle security monitoring device <b>2</b> will now be explained with reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> illustrates a flowchart of a security monitoring and theft prevention process stored in the memory <b>20</b> and executed by the controller <b>18</b>. In block <b>100</b>, which comprises steps <b>102</b>, <b>104</b> and <b>106</b>, the controller <b>18</b> constantly monitors all the input devices to determine whether an abnormal condition has occurred. In step <b>102</b>, the movement sensor <b>38</b> is monitored to see whether there is any movement of any object (especially of a person) inside the vehicle <b>4</b>. In step <b>104</b>, the motion sensor <b>36</b> is monitored to see whether the vehicle <b>4</b> has experienced any movement as in the case of someone entering the vehicle or the vehicle being hit by another vehicle. In step <b>106</b>, the controller <b>18</b> monitors the sound level coming from the microphone <b>32</b> to see whether a predetermined sound threshold level has been exceeded. For example, the controller <b>18</b> can monitor the highest level of sound or an average sound level picked up by the microphone <b>32</b> within a predetermined time period. If any of the three conditions in steps <b>102</b>-<b>106</b> is met, then the controller <b>18</b> determines that an abnormal condition has been detected.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">If the controller <b>18</b> determines that no abnormal condition has been detected, then decision block <b>108</b> is executed. In block <b>108</b>, the controller <b>18</b> determines whether any remote command instruction from the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> has been received through the receiver <b>14</b>. If yes, block <b>110</b> executes the received command and returns to block <b>100</b>. The instructions from the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> includes “activate/deactivate unattended mode”, “start/stop playing audio file”, “activate/deactivate kill switch”, “activate/deactivate siren”, “activate/deactivate video camera”, and “reset abnormal condition” among others.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">If the controller <b>18</b> determines that an abnormal condition has been detected in block <b>100</b>, then control passes to block <b>112</b>. In block <b>112</b>, the controller <b>18</b> automatically connects the microphone <b>32</b> to the transmitter <b>12</b> to continuously transmit a sound signal containing the sound coming from within the vehicle <b>4</b>. If a video camera <b>34</b> has been installed, it is also automatically connected to the transmitter to transmit a video signal containing images of the vehicle inside. The video images may assist the owner in determining an actual intrusion from a false alarm. They may also assist law enforcement officers in ascertaining the identity of the intruder assuming that the images are recorded by the portable monitor unit <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In block <b>114</b>, the controller <b>18</b> transmits a status signal that indicates detection of the abnormal condition so that the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> could alert the owner appropriately. When the controller <b>58</b> in the monitor unit <b>50</b> receives the status signal, it briefly sends a distinct beeping sound through the speaker <b>66</b> and/or activates the vibrator <b>65</b> to alert the owner.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In decision block <b>116</b>, the controller <b>18</b> determines whether the vehicle unit <b>10</b> is in an attended mode or unattended mode. In the embodiment shown, the vehicle unit <b>10</b> can be placed in the unattended mode in several different ways. In one way, the owner of the vehicle <b>4</b> can manually send an “activate unattended mode” instruction through the portable monitor unit <b>50</b>. In another way, if the vehicle unit <b>10</b> loses communication with the portable monitor unit <b>50</b>, the controller <b>18</b> automatically places the vehicle unit <b>10</b> into the unattended mode.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">If determined to be in the attended mode, the controller <b>18</b> executes block <b>108</b>. As described above, in blocks <b>108</b>-<b>110</b>, the controller <b>18</b> executes any remote command instructions received from the portable monitor unit <b>50</b> an returns to block <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Although not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, in case the vehicle unit <b>10</b> is in the attended mode, but has not received any instruction from the portable unit <b>50</b> for a predetermined time period (e.g., 30 seconds) after the abnormal condition detection signal in block <b>114</b> has been sent, the vehicle unit <b>10</b> automatically goes into the unattended mode regardless of whether the vehicle unit is in communication with the portable unit <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In decision block <b>116</b>, if the vehicle unit <b>10</b> is determined to be in the unattended mode, block <b>118</b> is executed. In block <b>118</b>, the contoller <b>18</b> activates the kill switch <b>30</b> to disable the vehicle <b>4</b>. In block <b>120</b>, the controller <b>18</b> retrieves a selected digital audio file stored in the memory <b>20</b> and the retrieved audio file is played through the speaker <b>24</b> at a selected volume. The stored digital audio file is typically an encoded “.wav” or “.mp3” file or the like, and contains a voice announcement that warns intruder to leave the vehicle <b>4</b>. After the file is played, the controller <b>18</b> in block <b>122</b> determines whether the abnormal condition has stopped. For example, the controller monitors the movement sensor <b>38</b> to see if the movement has stopped or monitors the sound level of the microphone <b>32</b> to see if the level has decreased below a predetermined level.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">If the abnormal condition still persists, then the controller <b>18</b> executes block <b>124</b>. In block <b>124</b>, the digital audio file is played through the speaker <b>24</b> at a higher volume that at block <b>120</b>. In block <b>126</b>, the controller again determines whether the abnormal condition has stopped. If the abnormal condition still persists, then the controller <b>18</b> executes block <b>128</b>. In block <b>128</b>, the controller <b>18</b> activates the siren <b>26</b> in an attempt to scare away the intruder from the vehicle <b>4</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Advantageously, the vehicle unit <b>10</b> communicates directly with the portable unit <b>50</b> without using any repeater or telephone network to ensure that the system will continue to operate without relying on the communications network. Once intrusion has been detected, the present system allows the owner to remotely send instructions to the vehicle unit such as activating a warning message, siren and kill switch, to prevent theft of the vehicle or loss of valuables in the vehicle. Even if the owner is not in a position to remotely respond through the portable monitor unit <b>50</b>, the vehicle is smart enough to automatically place itself into an unattended mode to automatically execute theft prevention steps of <b>118</b>-<b>128</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The foregoing specific embodiments represent just some of the ways of practicing the present invention. Many other embodiments are possible within the spirit of the invention. Accordingly, the scope of the invention is not limited to the foregoing specification, but instead is given by the appended claims along with their full range of equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A vehicle security monitoring device comprising:
<claim-text>a vehicle unit located in a vehicle and including:
<claim-text>a first transceiver;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a microphone operable to pick up sound coming from the vehicle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller coupled to the first transceiver and the microphone, and operable to determine an abnormal condition of the vehicle, the controller further operable to automatically connect the microphone to the first transceiver to transmit a sound signal containing the sound coming from the vehicle upon determination of the abnormal condition;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a portable monitor unit including a second transceiver adapted to directly communicate with the first transceiver of the vehicle unit without using a communications network, wherein the second transceiver directly receives the transmitted sound signal from the vehicle unit without the transmitted sound signal being routed through the communications network.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the controller determines the abnormal condition based on an output of the microphone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the controller determines the abnormal condition based on whether the level of sound picked up by the microphone increases above a selected threshold level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a movement sensor that detects movement of an object inside the vehicle, the controller determining the abnormal condition based on an output of the movement sensor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a movement sensor that detects movement of an object inside the vehicle, the controller determining the abnormal condition based on both an output of the movement sensor and an output of the microphone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the vehicle unit further includes a memory coupled to the controller and storing an audio data that contains a voice announcement that warns an intruder; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the controller plays the stored audio data through a speaker upon determination of the abnormal condition.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the controller replays the stored audio data at a higher volume when the sound level from the microphone does not decrease after the stored audio data has been played at least once.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the controller activates a siren in the vehicle when the sound level from the microphone does not decrease after the stored audio data has been played at least one.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a video camera connected to the controller, the controller operable to transmit through the first transceiver a video signal containing images within the vehicle to the portable monitoring unit in response to determination of the abnormal condition.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the controller places the vehicle unit in an unattended mode if communication is lost with the portable monitor unit or the controller receives an instruction from the portable monitoring unit instructing the vehicle unit to enter the unattended mode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the vehicle unit further includes a memory coupled to the controller and storing an audio data that contains a voice announcement that warns an intruder; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the controller plays the stored audio data through a speaker upon receiving an instruction from the portable monitoring unit instructing the vehicle unit to play the stored audio data.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein in the unattended mode, the controller automatically activates a siren after the abnormal condition has been determined.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the portable monitor unit activates a visual or audio alert when the portable monitor unit goes out of communication range with the vehicle unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the vehicle unit is connected to a speaker;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the portable monitor unit includes a microphone adapted to output a user sound signal containing the sound of a user to be transmitted through the second transceiver, wherein the controller receives the transmitted user sound signal for play back through the speaker.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the controller determines the abnormal condition based on an output of the microphone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the controller determines the abnormal condition based on whether the level of sound picked up by the microphone increases above a selected threshold level.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a movement sensor that detects movement of an object inside the vehicle, the controller determining the abnormal condition based on an output of the movement sensor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a movement sensor that detects movement of an object inside the vehicle, the controller determining the abnormal condition based on both an output of the movement sensor and an output of the microphone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the controller activates a siren in the vehicle when the sound level from the microphone does not decrease after the stored audio data has been played at least one.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the controller places the vehicle unit in an unattended mode if communication is lost with the portable monitor unit or the controller receives an instruction from the portable monitoring unit instructing the vehicle unit to enter the unattended mode.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A vehicle security monitoring device comprising:
<claim-text>a vehicle unit located in a vehicle and including:
<claim-text>a first transceiver;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a microphone operable to pick up sound coming from the vehicle;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a memory storing an audio data containing a voice announcement that warns an intruder; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a controller coupled to the first transceiver, the microphone and the memory, and operable to determine an abnormal condition of the vehicle, the controller further operable to:
<claim-text>automatically connect the microphone to the first transceiver to transmit a sound signal containing the sound coming from the vehicle upon determination of the abnormal condition; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>play the stored audio data through a speaker upon determination of the abnormal condition;</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>a portable monitor unit including a second transceiver adapted to directly communicate with the first transceiver of the vehicle unit without using a communications network.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00022" num="00022">
<claim-text>22. The vehicle security monitoring system according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00021">claim 21</claim-ref>, wherein the portable monitor unit includes a microphone adapted to output a user sound signal containing the sound of a user to be transmitted through the second transceiver, wherein the controller receives the transmitted user sound signal for play back through the speaker.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
