<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297023-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297023</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11180833</doc-number>
<date>20050713</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>9</main-group>
<subgroup>05</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439578</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e43">Coaxial cable connector with improved weather seal</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3461409</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Miller</name>
<date>19690800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3579282</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Couper</name>
<date>19710500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4047291</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Spinner</name>
<date>19770900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5401173</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Grandchamp et al.</name>
<date>19950300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5576675</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Oldfield</name>
<date>19961100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5662336</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Hayashi et al.</name>
<date>19970900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5720487</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Kato</name>
<date>19980200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5997350</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Burris et al.</name>
<date>19991200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6530807</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Rodrigues et al.</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6650209</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Plummer et al.</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6716061</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Pitschi et al.</name>
<date>20040400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6764329</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Noguchi et al.</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6767247</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Rodrigues et al.</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6773303</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lin</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00015">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6783394</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Holliday</name>
<date>20040800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439578</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00016">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6790083</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Chen</name>
<date>20040900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00017">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6830479</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Holliday</name>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00018">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6848939</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Stirling</name>
<date>20050200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00019">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0003706</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Montena</name>
<date>20050100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>14</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439578</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439584</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439585</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>7</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070015406</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070118</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chawgo</last-name>
<first-name>Shawn</first-name>
<address>
<city>Liverpool</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Pastel</last-name>
<first-name>Christopher R.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Pastel Law Firm</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>John Mezza Lingua Associates, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>East Syracuse</city>
<state>NY</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Hammond</last-name>
<first-name>Briggitte R.</first-name>
<department>2833</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A coaxial cable connector includes an internal compression ring that provides a weather seal for a wide range of coaxial cable diameter sizes. The compression ring includes a flexing portion with a defined recessed section designed to flex outwardly when in contact with a wide diameter coaxial cable. With larger cables, the wall flexes more, while with smaller cables the wall flexes less, if at all, providing a seal in all cases.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="153.84mm" wi="236.14mm" file="US07297023-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="166.45mm" wi="128.44mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297023-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="153.08mm" wi="149.69mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297023-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="214.04mm" wi="122.77mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297023-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="234.78mm" wi="155.96mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297023-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="236.64mm" wi="154.86mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297023-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="212.01mm" wi="166.88mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297023-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This invention relates generally to a connector for terminating a coaxial cable. More specifically, the present invention relates to a coaxial cable connector with an internal compression ring structure that provides a weather seal for a wide range of coaxial cable diameter sizes.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">A number of connectors are available to terminate a coaxial cable so as to connect the cable to various electronic devices, such as switches, distribution boxes, manifolds, and electronic devices. In a typical coaxial cable network, a “drop” cable is used to carry the signal, which may include analog or digital TV signal, internet signal, security monitoring signal, etc., from the rigid coaxial cable near the road to the end user's home. The connector in many cases has to be installed outside of the end user's home so that the servicing and installation personnel can perform troubleshooting as well as connecting and disconnecting the signal without entering the end user's premises. The connector can thereby be exposed to weather elements, including periods of high moisture, temperature fluctuations, rain, snow, etc. The drop cable typically has an elongated copper or a copper clad steel center conductor, surrounded by a dielectric in turn surrounded by a conducting braid and/or foil which is used as a shield, which is in turn surrounded by a polymer-based insulating jacket, typically made of PVC or PE. The two most common sizes of this cable currently in use are series <b>59</b> and series <b>6</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The cables in each series vary greatly in size due to manufacturing tolerances, jacket type, and braid content. For example, cable types known as “Tri Shield” and “Quad Shield” which utilize second layers of foil and/or braided shield are increasingly used. This presents a challenge for connector manufacturers because the connectors must provide a watertight seal when installed on the cable. Since the size of the cables within each series varies, most manufacturers offer several connectors per series. This presents another problem because the connectors must be properly matched to the cable in order to ensure a proper seal. This situation is highly inconvenient for installation technicians, representing an undesirable additional cost due to the necessity of holding an extensive inventory of connectors which needs to be maintained, the increased possibility of erroneous mixing-up of connectors of different sizes, and the likelihood of installation mistakes.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Due to the above factors, the critical step of sealing the connection is often not achieved causing a non-hermetic seal and thereby a leak between the cable and the connector. The signal quality is then compromised at the subscriber's location due to parasite electrical pathways between the center conductor and the shielding formed by moisture, as well as the oxidation and corrosion of the internal connector components and of the center conductor, with consequent deterioration of the quality of the connection.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Both crimping and crimpless compression and sealing connectors were developed in an attempt to address the above issues. However, these connectors were not able to address both tight weather seal requirements and the suitability of one connector for use on cables of different sizes. The complexity of design and number of required parts makes some of these connectors impractical and expensive to manufacture. In addition, the procedures required to assemble these connectors in the field, often in inclement weather conditions, are complicated.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">U.S. Pat. No. 6,767,247 shows a coaxial connector having a detachable locking sleeve attachably coupled to the connector's body. The locking sleeve is a cylindrical member formed of resilient material, which includes a flared rearward end through which a cable may be inserted. The locking sleeve is intended to be detachable and reattachable to the connector's body in a snap engagement and secures the cable within the connector's body.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">U.S. Pat. No. 6,848,939 shows a coaxial cable connector with a deformable inner collar or bushing that permits the connector to be attached and sealed to cables of various sizes. The bushing is made of a deformable insulating material.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">U.S. Patent application 2005/0003706 discloses a compression connector for a coaxial cable which radially compresses the cable in a tight frictional engagement.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Briefly stated, a coaxial cable connector includes an internal compression ring that provides a weather seal for a wide range of coaxial cable diameter sizes. The compression ring includes a flexing portion with a defined recessed section which is designed to flex outwardly when in contact with a wide diameter coaxial cable. With larger cables, the wall flexes more, while with smaller cables the wall flexes less, if at all, providing a seal in all cases.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">According to an embodiment of the invention, a compression connector for mounting upon an end of a coaxial cable, where the cable has a center conductor, a dielectric insulator surrounding the center conductor, a conductive shield surrounding the dielectric insulator, and an outer protective insulating jacket, includes a main body defining an internal cavity; a compression ring connected to one end of the main body; the compression ring having an annular recess in an outer circumference thereof forming a flexible wall area of the compression ring; and the annular recess forming a flexing space between the flexible wall area of the compression ring and the main body.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to an embodiment of the invention, a compression connector for mounting upon an end of a coaxial cable, the cable having a center conductor, a dielectric insulator surrounding the center conductor, a conductive shield surrounding the dielectric insulator, and an outer protective insulating jacket, includes a main body defining an internal cavity; a compression ring connected to one end of the main body; the compression ring including flexing means for flexing outwardly towards the main body when a coaxial cable is inserted into the connector and the compression ring is fully inserted into the main body.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">According to an embodiment of the invention, a method of manufacturing a compression connector for a coaxial cable includes the steps of making a main body; making a threaded nut body connected to the main body at a first end thereof; making a compression ring connected to the main body at a second end thereof; and forming an annular groove in an outer portion of the compression ring, thereby forming a flexible wall area in the compression ring.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a longitudinal section of a compression connector in an uncompressed state according to an embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows the longitudinal section of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with a compression ring in a final compressed state.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows the longitudinal section of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> with the compression ring attached and a coaxial cable being inserted into the connector.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref> show the longitudinal sections of the fully assembled connector in a final compressed state with the coaxial cable fully inserted in the connector and with the compression ring in the final fully inserted position.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> shows a sectional view of the compression ring according to an embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shows a sectional view showing the flexing of the compression ring according to an embodiment of the invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a connector <b>5</b> according to an embodiment of the present invention is shown prior to the insertion of a coaxial cable <b>80</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). Connector <b>5</b> includes a main body <b>20</b>, a compression ring <b>10</b> connected to main body <b>20</b>, a threaded nut <b>72</b> for interconnecting connector <b>20</b> to a mating connector or port (not shown), an O-ring or gasket <b>70</b> which seals the connection between nut <b>72</b> and main body <b>20</b>, and an internal post <b>36</b>. Internal post <b>36</b>, nut <b>72</b>, and O-ring <b>70</b> are of conventional construction for use in this type of coaxial cable connector. O-ring <b>70</b> is preferably made of easily compressible sealing material, such as rubber, plastic, or similar gasket material. Internal post <b>36</b> preferably includes an integrally formed flange <b>74</b> and a stem <b>32</b>. Stem <b>32</b> is preferably terminated with a tapered end <b>30</b> which preferably also includes a barb <b>34</b>. The diameter of barb <b>34</b> is enlarged compared to the diameter of stem <b>32</b>. Internal post <b>36</b> preferably has a bore of a diameter suitable to receive a dielectric insulator <b>84</b> of coaxial cable <b>80</b>. Main body <b>20</b> provides an enclosure for receiving coaxial cable <b>80</b> as well as for mounting nut <b>72</b>, internal post <b>36</b>, O-ring <b>70</b>, and compression ring <b>10</b>. Nut <b>72</b> is preferably rotatably mounted on main body <b>20</b> and on internal post flange <b>74</b>. Main body <b>20</b> also includes a cylindrical wall <b>50</b> concentric to internal post <b>36</b>, defining an annular channel between them which is dimensioned to receive a jacket <b>88</b> and a shield <b>86</b> of coaxial cable <b>80</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Compression ring <b>10</b> is preferably initially mounted on and engaged with main body <b>20</b> preferably utilizing a circumferential tooth <b>16</b> and a groove <b>14</b> connection, with tooth <b>16</b> provided on compression ring <b>10</b> and groove <b>14</b> provided on main body <b>20</b>. Compression ring <b>10</b> is preferably slidably attached to connector main body <b>20</b> and is capable of being moved further into main body <b>20</b> when driven forward by a compression tool (not shown) to disengage circumferential tooth <b>16</b> and groove <b>14</b> connection and move into main body <b>20</b> until an outer portion <b>12</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> contacts main body <b>20</b>, as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, connector <b>5</b> is shown in its fully assembled final position, but with coaxial cable <b>80</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) not shown. Compression ring <b>10</b> is in its compressed position. As compression ring <b>10</b> is compressed, the forward movement disengages circumferential tooth <b>16</b> from groove <b>14</b> and then moves compression ring <b>10</b> into main body <b>20</b> until outer portion <b>12</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> contacts main body <b>20</b>. A recessed section <b>40</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> defines a flexing space <b>42</b> between a recessed area wall <b>60</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> and cylindrical inner wall <b>50</b> of main body <b>20</b>. Flexing space <b>42</b> is the area within which recess wall <b>60</b> moves when a large diameter cable is inserted into connector <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the initial phase of coaxial cable <b>80</b> and connector <b>5</b> assembly is shown. Coaxial cable <b>80</b>, which is shown partially inserted into the connector <b>5</b>, includes an elongated center conductor <b>82</b>, formed of electrically conductive material, dielectric insulator <b>84</b> formed of insulating material such as suitable plastic, surrounding the center conductor, metallic shield <b>86</b> in the form of a braid or a foil or other suitable conductive material which surrounds the dielectric insulator, and an insulating jacket <b>88</b> covering metallic shield <b>86</b>. Coaxial cable <b>80</b> is shown with the end of cable <b>80</b> already prepped in the specified (conventional) manner for termination, which preferably includes stripping off jacket <b>88</b>, partially removing dielectric insulator <b>84</b>, folding back or partially or completely removing shield <b>86</b>, and exposing center conductor <b>82</b>, dielectric insulator <b>84</b>, and shield <b>86</b> in the usual manner. Prepped end of coaxial cable <b>80</b> is axially inserted into compression ring <b>10</b> and into main body <b>20</b> of connector <b>5</b>, with dielectric insulator <b>84</b> and center conductor <b>82</b> entering internal post <b>36</b> bore whereas tapered end <b>30</b> slides beneath shield <b>86</b> and jacket <b>88</b> of coaxial cable <b>80</b>. Barb <b>34</b> on internal post <b>36</b> resists the removal of coaxial cable <b>80</b> from connector <b>5</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>, connector <b>5</b> is shown in its fully assembled compressed position, with cable <b>80</b> inserted. The preferred arrangement of connector <b>5</b> and coaxial cable <b>80</b> is shown after cable <b>80</b> has been fully inserted into connector <b>5</b> with central conductor <b>82</b> preferably extending into nut <b>72</b> for further coupling to a mating connector or port (not shown). Coaxial cable <b>80</b> is engaged by internal post stem <b>32</b> tapered end <b>30</b> and by barb <b>34</b> of internal post <b>36</b>. After cable <b>80</b> is fully inserted into connector <b>5</b>, compression ring <b>10</b> is driven forward by a tool (not shown) until outer portion <b>12</b> contacts main body <b>20</b> of connector <b>5</b>. Coaxial cable <b>80</b> contacts compression ring <b>10</b> in a protruding area <b>90</b> and exerts an outward pressure onto compression ring <b>10</b> wall in this area. The outward flexing of recessed area wall <b>60</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> is shown with reference numeral <b>92</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">As further illustrated by <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4 and 5</figref>, shield <b>86</b> and jacket <b>88</b> of coaxial cable <b>80</b> are compressed between internal post <b>36</b> and protruding area <b>90</b> of compression ring <b>10</b>, allowing recessed area wall <b>60</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> to flex outwardly into flexing space <b>42</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). With a larger diameter cable <b>80</b>, recessed area wall <b>60</b> flexes more and with smaller diameter cable <b>80</b> recessed area wall <b>60</b> flexes less, if at all, providing a weather seal in both cases. If recessed area wall <b>60</b> were not allowed to flex, compression ring <b>10</b> would not seal on a large range of coaxial cables <b>80</b>. Once cable <b>80</b> is inserted and connector <b>5</b> is in final compressed state, the seal is ensured by compression of cable <b>80</b> by compression ring <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the mechanism of the formation of the seal between coaxial cable <b>80</b> and compression ring <b>10</b> is shown in further detail. The engagement of tapered end <b>30</b> and barb <b>34</b> of internal post stem <b>32</b> with coaxial cable <b>80</b> can result in an additional increase of the local diameter of cable <b>80</b> and formation of a bulge <b>94</b> on coaxial cable <b>80</b>. Because recessed area <b>40</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> is situated opposite bulge <b>94</b>, recessed area wall <b>60</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> is able to flex outwardly. Bulge <b>94</b> improves the seal contact between coaxial cable <b>80</b> and compression ring <b>10</b>, resulting in a better seal.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1</figref>, <b>6</b>, and <b>7</b>, compression ring <b>10</b> is a hollow, substantially cylindrical member which has defined recessed section <b>40</b>. Recessed section <b>40</b> is essentially a large groove on the outside of the cylindrical member located roughly in the middle of the axial dimension of ring <b>10</b>. Opposite recessed section <b>40</b> is protruding area <b>90</b> on the inside of the cylinder. Low thickness recess wall <b>60</b> is formed between recessed section <b>40</b> and protruding area <b>90</b> substantially in the middle of compression ring <b>10</b>. Outer portion <b>12</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> preferably has a larger diameter than an inner diameter of cylindrical inner wall <b>50</b> of main body <b>20</b>. Compression ring <b>10</b> is sized so as to be suitable for slidable insertion into main body <b>20</b>. Recess wall <b>60</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> is weakened due to its lessened thickness and is able to flex outwardly to a flexed position as indicated by dashed lines <b>92</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">As it is clear from the above description and accompanying drawings, compression ring <b>10</b> provides a weather seal for a wide range of coaxial cable <b>80</b> diameter sizes and types. Compression ring <b>10</b> has defined recessed section <b>40</b> which is designed to flex outwardly. Flexing space <b>42</b> between recessed area <b>40</b> of compression ring <b>10</b> and main body <b>20</b> is able to accept the flexing of recessed area wall <b>60</b> of compression ring <b>10</b>. With larger diameter cables <b>80</b>, recessed area wall <b>60</b> flexes more, and with smaller cables <b>80</b> recessed area wall flexes less, if at all, providing a reliable and tight weather seal in both cases. If recessed area wall didn't flex, compression ring would not seal over a large range of cable <b>80</b> sizes and diameters, but would be capable of only sealing cables <b>80</b> with sizes exactly fitting a given size of compression ring <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">While the present invention has been particularly shown and described with reference to the preferred mode as illustrated in the description and drawings, it will be understood by one skilled in the art that various changes in detail may be effected therein without departing from the spirit and scope of the present invention as defined by the claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>I claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A compression connector connectable to one of a plurality of coaxial cables having different sized outer diameters, each cable having a center conductor, a dielectric insulator surrounding the center conductor, a conductive shield surrounding the dielectric insulator, and an outer protective insulating jacket, the compression connector comprising:
<claim-text>a main body defining an internal cavity;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a compression ring connected to one end of the main body;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the compression ring having an annular recess in an outer circumference thereof defining a flexible wall area of the compression ring; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the annular recess forming a flexing space between the flexible wall area of the compression ring and the main body;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the flexible wall area has a flexing range between a first position corresponding to a smallest outer diameter of the plurality of coaxial cables and a second position corresponding to a largest outer diameter of the plurality of coaxial cables;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the flexing range of the flexible wall area effective for permitting any one of the plurality of coaxial cables having different sized outer diameters;</claim-text>
<claim-text>such that when the coaxial cable is fully secured in the compression connector, the flexible wall area is within the flexing range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> further comprising an internal post mounted inside the main body, the internal post having a cross-section such that the internal post is effective for passing between the dielectric insulator and the outer protective insulating jacket of the coaxial cable inserted into the main body through the compression ring.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the flexible wall area flexes outwardly into the flexing space when the compression ring is inserted into the main body after a coaxial cable is inserted into the connector.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the compression ring has a first inner diameter at a first end, the first end being the end through which an inserted coaxial cable passes when inserted into the connector; and the flexible wall area of the compression ring has a second inner diameter, smaller than the first inner diameter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the compression ring is made of metal, metallic alloy, composite, or plastic.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A compression connector connectable to one of a plurality of coaxial cables having different sized outer diameters, each cable having a center conductor, a dielectric insulator surrounding the center conductor, a conductive shield surrounding the dielectric insulator, and an outer protective insulating jacket, the compression connector comprising:
<claim-text>a main body defining an internal cavity;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a compression ring connected to one end of the main body;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the compression ring including flexing means for flexing outwardly towards the main body when a coaxial cable is inserted into the connector and the compression ring is fully inserted into the main body,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the flexing means includes a flexing range between a first position corresponding to a smallest outer diameter of the plurality of coaxial cables and a second position corresponding to a largest outer diameter of the plurality of coaxial cables;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the flexing range of the flexing means effective for permitting any one of the plurality of coaxial cables having different sized outer diameters;</claim-text>
<claim-text>such that when the coaxial cable is fully secured in the compression connector, at least a portion of the flexing means is within the flexing range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> further comprising an internal post mounted inside the main body, the internal post having a cross-section such that the internal post is effective for passing between the dielectric insulator and the outer protective insulating jacket of the coaxial cable inserted into the main body through the compression ring.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the flexing means is made of metal, metallic alloy, composite, or plastic.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A compression connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the flexing means includes an annular recess in an outer circumference thereof forming a flexible wall area of the compression ring; and the annular recess forms a flexing space between the flexible wall area of the compression ring and the main body.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref> wherein the compression ring has a first inner diameter at a first end, the first end being the end through which the inserted coaxial cable passes when inserted into the connector; and the flexible wall area of the compression ring has a second inner diameter, smaller than the first inner diameter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method of manufacturing a compression connector connectable to one of a plurality of coaxial cables having different sized outer diameters, comprising the steps of:
<claim-text>making a main body;</claim-text>
<claim-text>making a threaded nut body connected to the main body at a first end thereof;</claim-text>
<claim-text>making a compression ring connected to the main body at a second end thereof; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming an annular groove in an outer portion of the compression ring, thereby defining a flexible wall area in the compression ring,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the flexible wall area has a flexing range between a first position corresponding to a smallest outer diameter of the plurality of coaxial cables and a second position corresponding to a largest outer diameter of the plurality of coaxial cables; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the flexing range of the flexible wall area is effective for permitting any one of the plurality of coaxial cables having different sized outer diameters;</claim-text>
<claim-text>such that when the coaxial cable is fully secured in the compression connector, the flexible wall area is within the flexing range.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the flexible wall area has an inner diameter greater than or equal to an outer diameter of the coaxial cable.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00012">claim 12</claim-ref>, wherein the compression ring has a first inner diameter at an end through which an inserted coaxial cable passes when inserted into the connector; and the flexible wall area of the compression ring has a second inner diameter, smaller than the first inner diameter.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A connector according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00013">claim 13</claim-ref> further comprising the step of mounting an internal post inside the main body, the internal post having a cross-section such that the internal post is effective for passing between the dielectric insulator and the outer protective insulating jacket of the coaxial cable inserted into the main body through the compression ring.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
