<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297950-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297950</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11241953</doc-number>
<date>20051004</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2004-0085576</doc-number>
<date>20041026</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>N</subclass>
<main-group>23</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>21</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>250311</main-classification>
<further-classification>438 33</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Transmission electron microscope specimen and method of manufacturing the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5892225</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Okihara</name>
<date>19990400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>250311</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6184064</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Jiang et al.</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438113</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6538254</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Tomimatsu et al.</name>
<date>20030300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>25044211</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-042215</doc-number>
<date>20040200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>100209658</doc-number>
<date>19990400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>100214551</doc-number>
<date>19990500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>100253320</doc-number>
<date>20000100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>1020030043233</doc-number>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438460</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438 33</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>250311</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>250442</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>977881</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>9</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>17</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060097168</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060511</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lee</last-name>
<first-name>Myoung-Rack</first-name>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kim</last-name>
<first-name>Jung-Sun</first-name>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Volentine &amp; Whitt, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Samsung Electronics Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Gyeonggi-do</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Epps</last-name>
<first-name>Georgia</first-name>
<department>2878</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>LeGasse, Jr.</last-name>
<first-name>Francis M.</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A transmission electron microscope (TEM) specimen and a method of manufacturing the specimen are provided. The specimen comprises an analysis point. The specimen is formed by forming a dimple at a surface portion of the preliminary specimen, and ion milling the preliminary specimen having the dimple.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="144.10mm" wi="115.49mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="239.69mm" wi="129.46mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="236.64mm" wi="125.22mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="239.18mm" wi="129.12mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="256.71mm" wi="119.80mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="250.11mm" wi="135.38mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="250.11mm" wi="141.56mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="235.71mm" wi="138.09mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="240.88mm" wi="135.72mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="114.64mm" wi="141.14mm" file="US07297950-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Embodiments of the invention relate to a transmission electron microscope (TEM) specimen and a method of manufacturing the specimen. More particularly, embodiments of the invention relate to a method of forming a dimple on a TEM specimen and a method of manufacturing the specimen.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">This application claims priority to Korean Patent Application No. 2004-85576, filed on Oct. 26, 2004, the subject matter of which is hereby incorporated by reference in its entirety.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In general, manufacturing a semiconductor device comprises several processes, such as a diffusion process, an oxidation process, a sputtering process, etc. These processes are performed repeatedly on a semiconductor substrate to stack layers on the substrate. A layer may be, for example, a metal layer such as an aluminum layer, a titanium layer, tungsten layer, etc., or an insulation layer such as a nitride layer, an oxide layer, etc. As semiconductor devices have become more highly integrated and their components have become increasingly smaller, the process of manufacturing a semiconductor device has become more complex.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">When any one of the layers formed on a semiconductor substrate is defective (e.g., abnormally formed), the semiconductor device will typically fail to operate properly. In such circumstances, it is necessary to accurately and effectively analyze the defective layer, or at least determine whether the layer is defective or not. A TEM is often used to analyze a potentially defective layer. Conventional TEMs focus an electron beam on a specimen under examination to analyze a potentially effective layer in the specimen. An image of the layer under examination is obtained from the irradiating electron beam. More particularly, an electron diffraction pattern is obtained as the irradiating electron beam is diffracted by the constituent components of the layer being examined. In this manner, the conventional TEM analyzes the crystalline structure of the layer based on the resulting electron diffraction pattern.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">To analyze a layer using a TEM, a suitable specimen must be properly prepared. There are many conventional methods and constituent processing steps involved in the preparation of a TEM specimen. Argon ion milling, chemical polishing, chemical etching, using a cleavage system, and electro polishing—all or individually applied to a specimen in accordance with the material properties of its stacked layers and the nature of the analysis point under examination—are typical method steps adapted to the preparation of a TEM specimen. Argon ion milling has been widely employed in the preparation of TEM specimens adapted to the examination of stacked layers formed on a semiconductor substrate and the interfaces between the stacked layers.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">As noted above, a TEM obtains information about a specimen from an image generated by the transmission of an accelerated electron beam through the specimen. Thus, the specimen must be relatively thin, at least in the portion being specifically examined by the electron beam. In addition, the specimen must be prepared without scratches or contaminants. Thus, various methods have been studied to effectively prepare TEM specimens.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">For example, one method of manufacturing a specimen for TEM examination is disclosed in Korean Patent No. 209658. According to the method disclosed in Korean Patent No. 209658, a rotational angle of the specimen is adjusted in accordance with a difference between average atomic weights for each of stacked layers or the difference between sputtering speeds used to fabricate each of the stacked layers. This ion milling process produces a specimen having a more uniform thickness, and may be completed in a relatively short time.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Another method of manufacturing a planar wafer specimen for testing is also disclosed in Korean Patent No. 253320. According to the method disclosed in Korean Patent No. 253320, marks on the planar specimen are used (e.g., visualized) in order to analyze the cross sectional state and surface state of a specific region in the wafer specimen (e.g., a specific layer formed on the wafer as captured within the specimen).</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">One conventional method of manufacturing a specimen comprises; a cutting process, a bonding process, a slicing process, a punching process, a grinding process, a dimpling process and an ion-milling process. In the cutting process, first and second preliminary specimens and first, second, third, and fourth dummy wafers are prepared. In the bonding process, a first face of the first preliminary specimen is formed on a first face of the second preliminary specimen. The first and second dummy wafers and the third and fourth dummy wafers are formed on second faces of the first and second preliminary specimens, respectively, to form a stacked specimen. The second faces of the first and second preliminary specimens are opposite the first faces of the first and second preliminary specimens, respectively. In the slicing process, the stacked specimen is cut using a diamond saw to form a rectangular specimen having a thickness of about 0.5 mm to about 1 mm. In the punching process, the rectangular specimen is punched to form a circular specimen having a diameter of about 3 mm. In the grinding process, both circular faces of the circular specimen are ground using a grinder or a polisher to form a final specimen having a thickness of no more than about 100 μm. In the dimpling process, a dimple is formed at a central portion of the final specimen so that the thickness of the central portion of the final specimen is no more than about 1 μm. In the ion-milling process, both sides of the final specimen are sputtered with argon ions to form a hole through the central portion of the final specimen, thereby completing the formation of the final specimen. The final specimen is held by a holder adapted for use with a TEM and is placed on a corresponding support. The hole of the final specimen is then visualized and analyzed.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Figure (FIG.) <b>1</b> is a cross sectional view illustrating a conventional TEM specimen.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a first grinding region <b>20</b>, a second grinding region <b>30</b>, a third grinding region <b>40</b> and an ion-milling region <b>50</b> are formed concentrically around a central portion of a cross section of a specimen <b>10</b>. Here, first grinding region <b>20</b> has a first diameter longer than a second diameter of second grinding region <b>30</b>. The second diameter of second grinding region <b>30</b> is longer than a third diameter of third grinding region <b>40</b>. Ion-milling region <b>50</b> has a fourth diameter shorter than the third diameter of third grinding region <b>40</b>, and ion-milling region <b>50</b> is a hole used in observing specimen <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A conventional method of forming a dimple on a preliminary specimen is described in relation to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 to 4</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a central portion of a cross section of a preliminary specimen <b>10</b>′, formed by stacking wafers, is ground using a bronze wheel to form first circular grinding region <b>20</b> having the first diameter. Here, the formation of the first grinding region <b>20</b> is carried out until red light is observed in a transmission scope.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the central portion of preliminary specimen <b>10</b>′ is ground using a coarse wheel to form second grinding region <b>30</b> having the second diameter. Second grinding region <b>30</b> is concentric with first grinding region <b>20</b>. Here, the formation of second grinding region <b>30</b> is carried out until orange light is observed in the transmission scope.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the central portion of preliminary specimen <b>10</b>′ is repeatedly ground using a fine wheel to form third grinding region <b>40</b> having the third diameter. Third grinding region <b>40</b> is concentric with first and second grinding regions <b>20</b> and <b>30</b>. Here, the formation of third grinding region <b>40</b> is carried out until yellow light or white light is observed in the transmission scope.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a transmission scope picture illustrating a conventional specimen having a dimple.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, the red light serving as reference light in forming first grinding region <b>20</b> is exhibited in a first region I corresponding to an edge region of specimen <b>10</b>. The yellow light serving as reference light in forming third grinding region <b>40</b> is exhibited in a third region III corresponding to a central region of specimen <b>10</b>. The orange light serving as reference light in forming second grinding region <b>30</b> is exhibited in a second region II between first region I and third region III.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">To analyze the cross section of specimen <b>10</b> using a TEM, a central portion of third grinding region <b>40</b>, which is the thinnest portion of preliminary specimen <b>10</b>′, is aligned with a central portion of preliminary specimen <b>10</b>′ in forming the dimple. Here, an analysis region of specimen <b>10</b> has an allowable diameter of about 30 μm to about 50 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">However, when the central portion of third grinding region <b>40</b> is not aligned with the central portion of preliminary specimen <b>10</b>′, the diameter of the analysis region of specimen <b>10</b> is smaller than the allowable diameter. Also, when hole <b>50</b> has a relatively large diameter, the analysis region in third grinding region <b>40</b> has a relatively small area.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In one embodiment, the invention provides a TEM specimen comprising an analysis region comprising an analysis point, and a peripheral region enclosing the analysis region. The analysis region comprises a dimple region, and an ion-milling region, located at a central portion of the dimple region, comprising two separate holes having the analysis point between them.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In another embodiment, the invention provides a method of manufacturing a TEM specimen comprising preparing a preliminary specimen, and forming a specimen by forming a dimple region on a surface portion of the preliminary specimen, and ion milling the preliminary specimen having the dimple region to form an ion-milling region comprising two separate holes having an analysis point between them.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Exemplary embodiments will be described with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which like reference symbols indicate like components. In the drawings:</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross sectional view illustrating a conventional TEM specimen;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 to 4</figref> are cross sectional views illustrating a conventional method of forming a dimple on a TEM specimen;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a picture illustrating a ground state of a specimen during formation of a dimple using a conventional method;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross sectional view illustrating a TEM specimen in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 to 10</figref> are flow charts illustrating a method of manufacturing the specimen of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a picture illustrating a ground state of a specimen during formation of a dimple using a method that is in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the invention; and,</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12 to 17</figref> illustrate a method of manufacturing the specimen of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the invention, wherein <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a plain view and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 13 to 17</figref> are cross sectional views.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF EXEMPLARY EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">It will be understood that when an element or layer is referred to as being “on” another element or layer, it can be directly on the other element or layer, or intervening elements or layers may be present.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a cross sectional view illustrating a TEM specimen in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a specimen <b>100</b> is in the shape of a disk, wherein the disk has a diameter of about 3 mm and a thickness of about 70 μm. An analysis region <b>106</b>, formed on specimen <b>100</b>, is centered at the center point of specimen <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">A peripheral region <b>108</b> corresponds to the entire region of specimen <b>100</b> surrounding analysis region <b>106</b>. Peripheral region <b>108</b> is formed along an outer boundary of analysis region <b>106</b> and encloses analysis region <b>106</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Analysis region <b>106</b> comprises a dimple region <b>109</b>, and an ion-milling region <b>150</b> positioned at a central portion of dimple region <b>109</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Dimple region <b>109</b> further comprises a first grinding region <b>120</b>, a second grinding region <b>130</b> and a third grinding region <b>140</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">An analyzing direction is a direction from the analysis point toward the edge of a specimen or a preliminary specimen that is substantially parallel to the faces of the wafers used in the formation of the specimen or preliminary specimen. There are necessarily two analyzing directions, wherein a first analyzing direction is opposite a second analyzing direction. A line of analysis is a line that extends away from the analysis point of a specimen or a preliminary specimen in both of the analyzing directions.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">First grinding region <b>120</b> has a first area, a first length substantially along the line of analysis, and a first width smaller than the first length that is substantially perpendicular to the line of analysis. In this exemplary embodiment, first grinding region <b>120</b>, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, has an overlapping circular shape.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">As used herein, an overlapping circular shape is the shape of two partially overlapping circular shapes, as shown, for example, by first grinding region <b>120</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. The two overlapping circular shapes may overlap in the analyzing directions and/or with respect to the analysis point.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Alternatively, first grinding region <b>120</b> may have an elliptical shape, having its major axis substantially along the line of analysis. First grinding region <b>120</b> may also have another shape, having a first length substantially along the line of analysis and a first width substantially perpendicular to the line of analysis.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Second grinding region <b>130</b> has a second area smaller than the first area of first grinding region <b>120</b>, a second length substantially along the line of analysis, and a second width smaller than the second length that is substantially perpendicular to the line of analysis. In this exemplary embodiment, second grinding region <b>130</b> has an elliptical shape. Alternatively, second grinding region <b>130</b> may have an overlapping circular shape.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Third grinding region <b>140</b> has a third area smaller than the second area of second grinding region <b>130</b>, a third length substantially along the line of analysis, and a third width smaller than the third length that is substantially perpendicular to the line of analysis. Here, the third length of third grinding region <b>140</b> may be about 50 μm to about 150 μm. In this exemplary embodiment, third grinding region <b>140</b> has an elliptical shape. Alternatively, third grinding region <b>140</b> may have an overlapping circular shape.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Ion-milling region <b>150</b> comprises two separate holes that are within third grinding region <b>140</b> and have an analysis point between them. Specimen <b>100</b> is analyzed using the two holes.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">In accordance with this exemplary embodiment, specimen <b>100</b> has a relatively large analysis area.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Hereinafter, a method of manufacturing specimen <b>100</b> will be described in detail.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 to 10</figref> are flow charts illustrating a method of manufacturing specimen <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a flow chart illustrating a method of manufacturing the specimen, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a flow chart illustrating a method of forming a preliminary specimen, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is flow chart illustrating a method of forming a specimen from a preliminary specimen, and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a flow chart illustrating a method of forming a dimple on a preliminary specimen.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a picture illustrating a ground state of a specimen during formation of a dimple using a method that is in accordance with an exemplary embodiment of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12 to 17</figref> illustrate a method of manufacturing specimen <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 12 and 13</figref> illustrate a method of forming the preliminary specimen, where <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a plain view and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a cross sectional view. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 14 to 17</figref> are cross sectional views illustrating a method of forming the specimen.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, a method of manufacturing specimen <b>100</b> for the TEM comprises preparing a preliminary specimen <b>110</b> (<b>300</b>) and forming a specimen <b>100</b> (<b>400</b>) by grinding preliminary specimen <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Hereinafter, preparing preliminary specimen <b>110</b> (<b>300</b>) will be described in detail.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 12</figref>, first and second separated specimens <b>101</b><i>a </i>and <b>101</b><i>b</i>, and first, second, third, and fourth dummy wafers <b>102</b><i>a</i>, <b>102</b><i>b</i>, <b>102</b><i>c </i>and <b>102</b><i>d </i>are formed through a cutting process (<b>310</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In particular, a patterned wafer, such as a semiconductor substrate on which a pattern to be analyzed is formed, is prepared. A cross section of the pattern on the semiconductor substrate is observed using an electron microscope to determine the analysis point of the pattern. The semiconductor substrate is then cut using a dicing saw to form first and second separated specimens <b>101</b><i>a </i>and <b>101</b><i>b </i>each having an area of about 4 mm×about 5 mm. In addition, wafers are cut to form first, second, third, and fourth dummy wafers <b>102</b><i>a</i>, <b>102</b><i>b</i>, <b>102</b><i>c </i>and <b>102</b><i>d</i>, each of which has an area substantially the same as that of first and second separated specimen <b>101</b><i>a </i>or <b>101</b><i>b. </i></p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">Then, to form a stacked specimen <b>103</b>, first and second dummy wafers <b>102</b><i>a </i>and <b>102</b><i>b </i>are formed on first separated specimen <b>101</b><i>a</i>, and third and fourth dummy wafers <b>102</b><i>c </i>and <b>102</b><i>d </i>are formed on second separated specimen <b>101</b><i>b </i>(<b>320</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In detail, a first face of first separated specimen <b>101</b><i>a </i>is formed on a first face of second separated specimen <b>10</b><i>b</i>. First and second dummy wafers <b>102</b><i>a </i>and <b>102</b><i>b </i>are each formed on a second face of first separated specimen <b>101</b><i>a</i>, which is opposite the first face of first separated specimen <b>101</b><i>a</i>, using a G1-epoxy resin. Third and fourth dummy wafers <b>102</b><i>c </i>and <b>102</b><i>d </i>are each formed on a second face of second separated specimen <b>101</b><i>b</i>, which is opposite the first face of second separated specimen <b>101</b><i>b</i>, using a G1-epoxy resin, thereby forming stacked specimen <b>103</b>. Stacked specimen <b>103</b> is then compressed using a compressor to spread the G-epoxy resin widely and thinly. Next, stacked specimen <b>103</b> is heated to a temperature of about 145° C., thereby completing the construction of stacked specimen <b>103</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 13</figref>, stacked specimen <b>103</b> is sliced in a direction substantially perpendicular to the faces of the wafers using a diamond cutter to form a sliced specimen <b>104</b> (<b>330</b>) having a thickness of about 0.5 mm to about 1 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">Sliced specimen <b>104</b> is then punched to form a circular specimen <b>105</b> (<b>340</b>) having a diameter of about 3 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Next, both circular faces of circular specimen <b>105</b> are ground, using a grinder or a polisher, to form preliminary specimen <b>110</b> (<b>350</b>) having a thickness of about 70 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Hereinafter, a method of forming specimen <b>100</b> from preliminary specimen <b>110</b> is described in detail.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>, forming specimen <b>100</b> (<b>400</b>) comprises, referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, forming a dimple on preliminary specimen <b>110</b> (<b>410</b>), and then ion milling preliminary specimen <b>110</b> (<b>420</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Forming a dimple on preliminary specimen <b>110</b> (<b>410</b>) comprises, referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10 and 14</figref>, forming the first grinding region (<b>411</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">In particular, preliminary specimen <b>110</b> is ground in the analyzing directions from the analysis point to form first grinding region <b>120</b>. First grinding region <b>120</b> has the first area, the first length substantially along the line of analysis, and the first width smaller than the first length that is substantially perpendicular to the line of analysis. In this exemplary embodiment, first grinding region <b>120</b> has an overlapping circular shape, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">Alternatively, first grinding region <b>120</b> may have an elliptical shape having its major axis substantially along the line of analysis. Peripheral region <b>108</b> corresponds to the entire region of preliminary specimen <b>110</b> surrounding first grinding region <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The thickness of preliminary specimen <b>110</b> at the dimple is not more than about 1 μm. This reduced thickness at the dimple is formed by polishing a cross section of the specimen using a chemical mechanical polishing (CMP) process. The process for forming the dimple is carried out using various abrasives in a series of steps. The abrasive used to form each grinding region may vary in accordance with the desired thickness of that grinding region.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Preliminary specimen <b>110</b> is ground using a dual grinding wheel to form first grinding region <b>120</b> (<b>411</b>) having a thickness of about 10 μm to about 20 μm. The thickness of a grinding region, as used herein, means the thickness of the specimen or preliminary specimen at that grinding region, excluding the portion of that grinding region that contains other grinding regions or an ion-milling region.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">Here, when first grinding region <b>120</b> has a thickness of below about 10 μm, red light is observed in first grinding region <b>120</b> using a transmission scope. Thus, to form first grinding region <b>120</b>, preliminary specimen <b>110</b> is ground until red light is observed.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>, the red light exhibited in an edge region IV of preliminary specimen <b>110</b> serves as a reference in forming first grinding region <b>120</b>. The yellow light exhibited in a central region VI of preliminary specimen <b>110</b> serves as a reference in forming third grinding region <b>140</b>. The orange light exhibited in an interface region V between edge region IV and central region VI serves as a reference in forming second grinding region <b>130</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Since the process for forming first grinding region <b>120</b> is a fundamental process in forming the dimple, the process for forming first grinding region <b>120</b> need not be precise, and thus diamond particles may be used in forming first grinding region <b>120</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">The method of forming the dimple further comprises grinding first grinding region <b>120</b> to form second grinding region <b>130</b> (<b>412</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10 and 15</figref>, first grinding region <b>120</b> is ground with respect to the analysis point to form second grinding region <b>130</b> having an elliptical shape that has the second area smaller than the first area of first grinding region <b>120</b>. The major axis of second grinding region <b>130</b> is substantially along the line of analysis of preliminary specimen <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">In this exemplary embodiment, first grinding region <b>120</b> is ground using an abrasive comprising about 80% by weight of diamond paste and about 20% by weight of aluminum oxide to form second grinding region <b>130</b> having a thickness of about 2 μm to about 3 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">The abrasive used to form second grinding region <b>130</b> is different from that used to form first grinding region <b>120</b>, since the thickness of second grinding region <b>130</b> is more precisely controlled than the thickness of first grinding region <b>120</b>. When, in the process of grinding first grinding region <b>120</b>, orange light is observed in fifth region V of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> using a transmission scope, second grinding region <b>130</b> has a thickness of about 2 μm to about 3 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">The process for forming second grinding region <b>130</b> is referred to as a coarse process. The process of forming second grinding region <b>130</b> is coarser than the process of forming third grinding region <b>140</b>, and preliminary specimen <b>110</b> is planarized by the coarse process to expand an area to be analyzed by the TEM.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">The method of forming the dimple further comprises grinding second grinding region <b>130</b> to form third grinding region <b>140</b> (<b>413</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 10 and 16</figref>, second grinding region <b>130</b> is ground with respect to the analysis point to form third grinding region <b>140</b> having an elliptical shape that has the third area smaller than the second area of second grinding region <b>130</b>. The major axis of third grinding region <b>140</b> is substantially along the line of analysis of preliminary specimen <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">In this exemplary embodiment, second grinding region <b>130</b> is ground using an abrasive comprising aluminum oxide to form third grinding region <b>140</b> having a thickness of no more than about 1 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">The abrasive used to form third grinding region <b>140</b> is different from that used to form second grinding region <b>130</b>, since the thickness of third grinding region <b>140</b> is more precisely controlled than the thickness of second grinding region <b>130</b>. When, in grinding second grinding region <b>130</b>, yellow light or white light is observed in sixth region VI of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> using a transmission scope, third grinding region <b>140</b> has a thickness of no more than about 1 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">Here, to prepare the TEM specimen for analysis, a coarse surface of second grinding region <b>130</b> having fine scratches is minutely polished using aluminum oxide to form third grinding region <b>140</b> having the dimple. The major axis of third grinding region <b>140</b> has a length of about 50 μm to about 150 μm.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">First, second and third grinding regions <b>120</b>, <b>130</b> and <b>140</b> together form dimple region <b>109</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 9 and 17</figref>, an ion-milling process is performed on preliminary specimen <b>110</b> to complete specimen <b>100</b> having ion-milling region <b>150</b> (<b>420</b>).</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081">In detail, third grinding region <b>140</b> is sputtered using argon ions to form two holes corresponding to ion-milling region <b>150</b>. The holes are arranged along the line of analysis.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">As a result, dimple region <b>109</b> including first, second, and third grinding regions <b>120</b>, <b>130</b>, and <b>140</b> and ion-milling region <b>150</b> together form analysis region <b>106</b>, thereby completing specimen <b>100</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">Specimen <b>100</b> is then placed on a table. Electrons are transmitted through the holes of ion milling region <b>150</b> to test specimen <b>100</b>. Third grinding region <b>140</b> of specimen <b>100</b> is mainly observed. Analysis region <b>106</b> of specimen <b>100</b>, in accordance with an exemplary embodiment, has a width of about 50 μm to about 150 μm, which is generally wider than the width of 30 μm to about 50 μm of the conventional specimen.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">A specimen in accordance with exemplary embodiments of the invention has a relatively large analysis region. Thus, even if the dimple region is not aligned with the center point of the specimen, or the holes have very large diameters, the specimen may still be readily analyzed.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">Although exemplary embodiments of the invention have been described, it will be apparent to those of ordinary skill in the art that modifications and variations can be made while remaining within the scope of the invention as set forth in the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of manufacturing a transmission electron microscope (TEM) specimen, comprising:
<claim-text>preparing a preliminary specimen; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a specimen by forming a dimple region on a surface portion of the preliminary specimen, and ion milling the preliminary specimen having the dimple region to form an ion-milling region within the dimple region,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein preparing the preliminary specimen comprises:</claim-text>
<claim-text>cutting a first and a second patterned wafer,</claim-text>
<claim-text>cutting a first, a second, a third, and a fourth dummy wafer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming the first face of the first patterned wafer on the first face of the second patterned wafer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming the first, second, third, and fourth dummy wafers on second faces opposite the first faces of first and second patterned wafers to form a stacked specimen;</claim-text>
<claim-text>slicing the stacked specimen in a direction substantially perpendicular to the first faces of the first and second patterned wafers to form a sliced specimen;</claim-text>
<claim-text>punching the sliced specimen to form a circular specimen; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>grinding the circular specimen to form the preliminary specimen.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein forming the dimple region comprises:
<claim-text>grinding the preliminary specimen to form a first grinding region having a first area, a first length, and a first width smaller than the first length;</claim-text>
<claim-text>grinding the first grinding region to form a second grinding region having a second area smaller than the first area, a second length, and, a second width smaller than the second length; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>grinding the second grinding region to form a third grinding region having a third area smaller than the second area, a third length, and a third width smaller than the third length,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the first, second, and third lengths are substantially along a line of analysis, and each of the first, second, and third widths are substantially perpendicular to the line of analysis.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein each of the first, second and third grinding regions has an elliptical shape or an overlapping circular shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the third length of the third grinding region is about 50 μm to about 150 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the first grinding region has a thickness of about 10 μm to about 20 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the second grinding region has a thickness of about 2 μm to about 3 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the third grinding region has a thickness of no more than about 1 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the ion-milling region comprises two separate holes having an analysis point between them.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A method of manufacturing a transmission electron microscope (TEM) specimen, comprising:
<claim-text>preparing a preliminary specimen; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a specimen by forming a dimple region on a surface portion of the preliminary specimen, and ion milling the preliminary specimen having the dimple region to form an ion-milling region within the dimple region,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein preparing the preliminary specimen comprises:
<claim-text>cutting a first and a second patterned wafer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a stacked specimen, wherein forming the stacked specimen comprises forming the first face of the first patterned wafer on the first face of the second patterned wafer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>slicing the stacked specimen in a direction substantially perpendicular to the first faces of the first and second patterned wafers to form a sliced specimen;</claim-text>
<claim-text>punching the sliced specimen to form a circular specimen; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>grinding the circular specimen to form the preliminary specimen.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein forming the dimple region comprises:
<claim-text>grinding the preliminary specimen to form a first grinding region having a first area, a first length, and a first width smaller than the first length;</claim-text>
<claim-text>grinding the first grinding region to form a second grinding region having a second area smaller than the first area, a second length, and a second width smaller than the second length; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>grinding the second grinding region to form a third grinding region having a third area smaller than the second area, a third length, and a third width smaller than the third length,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the first, second, and third lengths are substantially along a line of analysis, and each of the first, second, and third widths are substantially perpendicular to the line of analysis.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein each of the first, second and third grinding regions has an elliptical shape or an overlapping circular shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the third length of the third grinding region is about 50 μm to about 150 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the first grinding region has a thickness of about 10 μm to about 20 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the second grinding region has a thickness of about 2 μm to about 3 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the third grinding region has a thickness of no more than about 1 μm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method of manufacturing a transmission electron microscope (TEM) specimen, comprising:
<claim-text>preparing a preliminary specimen;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein preparing the preliminary specimen comprises:
<claim-text>cutting a first and a second patterned wafer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a stacked specimen, wherein forming the stacked specimen comprises forming the first face of the first patterned wafer on the first face of the second patterned wafer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>slicing the stacked specimen in a direction substantially perpendicular to the first faces of the first and second patterned wafers to form a sliced specimen;</claim-text>
<claim-text>punching the sliced specimen to form a circular specimen; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>grinding the circular specimen to form the preliminary specimen; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a specimen by forming a dimple region on a surface portion of the preliminary specimen, and ion milling the preliminary specimen having the dimple region to form an ion-milling region within the dimple region,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein:</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming the dimple region comprises grinding the preliminary specimen to form a first grinding region having a first area, a first length, a first width smaller than the first length, and an overlapping circular shape;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first length is substantially along a line of analysis; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>the first width is substantially perpendicular to the line of analysis.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein the ion-milling region comprises two separate holes having an analysis point between them.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein forming the dimple region further comprises:
<claim-text>grinding the first grinding region to form a second grinding region having a second area smaller than the first area, a second length, and a second width smaller than the second length; and,</claim-text>
<claim-text>grinding the second grinding region to form a third grinding region having a third area smaller than the second area, a third length, and a third width smaller than the third length,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each of the second and third lengths are substantially along the line of analysis, and each of the second and third widths are substantially perpendicular to the line of analysis.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00016">claim 16</claim-ref>, wherein each of the second and third grinding regions has an elliptical shape or an overlapping circular shape.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
