<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07299310-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07299310</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10986556</doc-number>
<date>20041110</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>103 53 345</doc-number>
<date>20031114</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>602</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>12</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710 71</main-classification>
<further-classification>710305</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Connection module for the connection of a sensor to a fieldbus</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6571132</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Davis et al.</name>
<date>20030500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>700  2</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6889282</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Schollenberger</name>
<date>20050500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710305</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7024508</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Gros et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710305</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0040881</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Steger</name>
<date>20030200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0015630</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Boolos et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710300</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0139265</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hocker et al.</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>710305</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>196 46 219</doc-number>
<date>19971200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>299 07 909</doc-number>
<date>19990800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>299 03 260</doc-number>
<date>20000500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>101 31 094</doc-number>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>102 23 724</doc-number>
<date>20030100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>DE</country>
<doc-number>101 61 401</doc-number>
<date>20030600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO 03/054573</doc-number>
<date>20030700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>21</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710 69</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710 70</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>710 71</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>1</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>2</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050108442</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050519</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Aschenbrenner</last-name>
<first-name>Johannes</first-name>
<address>
<city>Emmendingen</city>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>DE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>DE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Harness, Dickey &amp; Pierce, P.L.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sick AG</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Waldkirch</city>
<country>DE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Kindred</last-name>
<first-name>Alford</first-name>
<department>2181</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Unelus</last-name>
<first-name>Ernest</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The invention relates to a connection module for the connection of a sensor, in particular of an optoelectronic sensor, to a fieldbus, comprising a sensor interface for the connection of the connection module to an interface of a sensor, a serial bus interface for the connection of the connection module to an interface of a fieldbus and a gateway circuit which is connected to the bus interface and to the sensor interface in order to convert data received at the bus interface into a data format of a connected sensor and vice versa. The sensor interface of the connection module is made as a parallel interface. At least one I/O circuit is integrated into the connection module and is connected to the bus interface and to the sensor interface. The invention further relates to a method for the connection of a sensor to a fieldbus via a connection module.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="115.23mm" wi="160.27mm" file="US07299310-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="209.80mm" wi="161.63mm" file="US07299310-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The invention relates to a connection module for the connection of a sensor, in particular of an optoelectronic sensor, to a fieldbus, comprising a sensor interface for the connection of the connection module to an interface of a sensor, a serial bus interface for the connection of the connection module to an interface of a fieldbus and a gateway circuit which is connected to the bus interface and to the sensor interface in order to convert data received at the bus interface into a data format of a connected sensor and to output them at the sensor interface and to convert data received at the sensor interface into a data format of the fieldbus and to output them at the bus interface.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The background of the invention is the networking of sensors, for example of one-dimensional or two-dimensional optical code readers or of laser measuring systems, via a digital fieldbus, for example of the type Profibus or DeviceNet. It is known for this purpose to provide the sensors with their own fieldbus interface which permits a connection of the sensor to the fieldbus and communication between the sensor and the fieldbus. A fieldbus interface integrated in the sensor, however, makes the actual sensor module undesirably expensive and undesirably voluminous for some applications. The relevant sensor is moreover admittedly adapted to a specific fieldbus; but the sensor can no longer easily be used for other fieldbus types.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Alternatively to its own fieldbus sensor, it is known to provide the relevant sensor with a connection module which has a sensor interface which permits a connection to a serial interface of the sensor. The connection module is connected to a so-called gateway circuit which translates the data exchanged at the sensor interface of the connection module into the format of the fieldbus and vice versa and which is connected for this purpose via a bus interface to the fieldbus. The connection module and the gateway circuit thus serve for the adaptation of both the hardware (respective interface) and the data formats (bus protocol) between the fieldbus and the sensor, with the gateway circuit usually adapting a serial sensor interface to a specific fieldbus type. To configure the sensor for the fieldbus and to permit communication with the fieldbus, the user must parameterize two devices, namely the sensor and the interposed gateway circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Known connection modules have proven to be insufficient, in particular with optoelectronic sensors, since these have digital switch inputs and outputs in addition to a serial data interface and since additional circuits are therefore required to bring about the desired adaptation to a specific fieldbus. With the known connection modules, the parameterization, i.e. the adaptation of the gateway circuit to the fieldbus addressing and the fieldbus protocol is moreover undesirably complex since two devices (sensor and gateway circuit) have to be addressed.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">It is therefore an object of the invention to facilitate the embedding and the replacement of connection modules and sensors in a sensor network connected via a fieldbus.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">This object is satisfied by a connection module having the features of claim <b>1</b> and in particular in that the sensor interface is made as a parallel interface with a serial data interface and at least one separate switch input/output parallel to it; and in that an I/O circuit, which is connected to the bus interface and to the sensor interface, is integrated into the connection module in order to convert switching data received serially at the bus interface into switching signals and to output them at the parallel switch input/output of the sensor interface and in order to convert switching signals received in parallel manner at the switch input/output into switching data and to output them at the bus interface.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">This connection module is therefore characterized in that the sensor interface is made as a parallel interface which has, in addition to the usual serial data interface, at least one parallel switch input and/or output parallel thereto. The connection module is furthermore provided with a so-called I/O circuit. This translates switching data which are contained in the serial data word (string) received at the bus interface of the connection module into digital switching signals which can be transmitted directly to a connected sensor via the parallel switch input/output. In the reverse direction, the I/O circuit integrated into the connection module also provides a conversion of digital switching signals received by a connected sensor at the parallel switch input/output of the sensor interface into a data word which can be output at the (single) serial bus interface together with the sensor data received at the serial data interface. The gateway circuit likewise included in the connection module provides the required conversion of the serial sensor data which are exchanged between the bus interface and the serial data interface of the sensor interface.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Since the connection module is fitted with one or more additional parallel switch inputs/outputs and since at least one I/O circuit is integrated into the connection module, the necessity of separate I/O modules which have to be connected, parallel to a conventional connection module, to the digital switch inputs/outputs of the sensor, on the one hand, and to the fieldbus via its own fieldbus interface, on the other hand, is dispensed with. The necessity is furthermore dispensed with of configuring such additional I/O modules for the specifically used fieldbus. In accordance with the invention, the sensor is therefore connected to the fieldbus via one single connection module with an integrated gateway circuit and an integrated I/O circuit. The switching signals of the sensor can in this manner be taken directly into account and used in the process mapping of the control so that the control of the switch inputs/outputs of the sensor are considerably simplified.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The device effort is substantially reduced since only one single connection module is required to connect the respective sensor to the fieldbus even if the sensor has one or more switch inputs/outputs, as is typically the case with optoelectronic sensors.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Since the I/O circuit is integrated into the connection module, a connection between the switch inputs/outputs of the sensor and the I/O circuit is possible especially easily via very short leads.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Any required replacement of the connection module or of the connected sensor is also possible in a simple manner since no additional separate I/O modules have to be taken into account for the parameterization required for this purpose of the replaced device.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In accordance with an advantageous embodiment of the connection module, the at least one I/O circuit is integrated into the gateway circuit, i.e. the I/O circuit is part of the gateway circuit. In this case, the necessity is even dispensed with of making the I/O circuit as a separate circuit unit or circuit board; the conversion of the serial switching data into parallel switching signals—and vice versa—rather takes place by a common gateway-I/O circuit. The connection of the I/O circuit to the bus interface and to the sensor case takes place in this case via the actual gateway circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">It is furthermore of advantage for the gateway circuit to be made as a unit which can be replaced by the user, in particular as a card (insertion card) which can additionally be secured by screws. A unit which replaceable by the user is generally to be understood in connection with the invention as a unit which can be replaced either without tools or with a simple tool (such as a screwdriver, for example), and in any case without solder processes. A separate I/O circuit or a combined gateway-I/O circuit can also be made as a unit replaceable by the user. In these cases, the connection module can be adapted particularly flexibly to different fieldbus types due to the modular design. In the event of a defect in the respective circuit, this can be replaced particularly simply without the whole connection module having to be replaced.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">It is furthermore preferred for the sensor interface, the bus interface, the gateway circuit and the I/O circuit of the connection module to be accommodated in a common housing.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In accordance with an advantageous embodiment, a permanent memory is furthermore integrated into the connection module for the storage of operating parameters and the gateway circuit and the I/O circuit can communicate with the fieldbus on the basis thereof. Thanks to such a permanent memory, the required operating parameters, for example the identification number of the connected sensor within the network, the data length to be used or the baud rate to be used always remain in memory as long as the stored parameters are not directly overwritten again. The operating parameters are thereby maintained even if the system is switched off for a time or if the associated sensor is replaced.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">It is preferred for the said permanent memory also to be made as a unit replaceable by the user, for example as a replaceable memory card. In this case, for example, the connection module with an associated gateway circuit and/or an I/O circuit can be replaced, with the operating parameters required for the communication with the fieldbus being maintained in a simple manner in that the permanent memory is taken out of the replaced connection module and inserted into the new connection module.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The permanent memory is preferably provided with its own micro-controller which permits a direct data exchange of the permanent memory with the serial data interface of the connection module. Alternatively to this, the permanent memory can also be directly connected to the gateway circuit and to the I/O circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In accordance with an advantageous further development, the gateway circuit and the I/O circuit are configured such that the operating parameters to be used for the communication with the fieldbus can be transmitted to the gateway circuit and to the I/O circuit via the sensor interface from a connected sensor. In this further development, the operating parameters required for the communication with the fieldbus can therefore be transmitted to the active circuits of the connection module by the connected sensor. The user in this case therefore does not have to parameterize two devices, but it is sufficient to set the required operating parameters only at the sensor. The operating parameters are transmitted by this to the gateway circuit and to the I/O circuit of the connection module. The parameterization can thus take place—jointly for the sensor and the connection module—in a simple manner within the operating interface of the connected sensor.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The gateway circuit, including the I/O circuit, is preferably connected to the sensor interface such that the operating parameters are automatically read in at the sensor interface of the connection module at the start of operation—and in particular during a limited parameterization time interval after the start of operation. In other words, the gateway circuit and the I/O circuit are configured such that a data link between the sensor interface of the connection module and the connected sensor can be set up after the start of operation in order to transmit operating parameters from the sensor to the connection module. The decisive event for the transmission of the operating parameters can be the start of operation of the connection module and/or of the connected sensor; if both devices are not switched on simultaneously, the transmission in particular takes place on the start of operation of the device switched on later.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">It is furthermore preferred for the connection module to be provided with a permanent memory, or with the already named permanent memory, in which the operating parameters received via the sensor interface can be stored. This permanent memory can be connected directly to the sensor interface or indirectly to the sensor interface via the gateway circuit and the I/O circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">In this process, the permanent memory can be configured such that those operating parameters stored in the permanent memory are transmitted from the permanent memory via the sensor interface to the connected sensor directly after the start of operation of the connection module and still before the transmission of operating parameters from the connected sensor. In this manner, the stored operating parameters can be transmitted indirectly from the permanent memory via the sensor interface and the connected sensor to the gateway circuit and to the I/O circuit. A direct connection between the permanent memory, on the one hand, and the gateway circuit and I/O circuit on the other hand can thereby be omitted.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">In this further development, the gateway circuit and the I/O circuit can also be configured such that—if no operating parameters are received by the connected sensor after the start of operation—they use those operating parameters for the communication with the fieldbus which were previously stored in the permanent memory before the last start of operation of the connection module. If the connection module therefore exceptionally does not receive any operating parameters from a connected sensor after the start of operation, the connection module communicates with the fieldbus on the basis of the last received and stored operating parameters. It is thereby possible, for example, to replace a previously connected sensor with a simple switching unit or a simple actuator which are not made to initialize the connection module or the permanent memory with operating parameters. Nevertheless, such simple units can communicate with the fieldbus after replacement since the connection module now bases the communication on the previously transmitted and stored operating parameters.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The invention also relates to a method for the connection of a sensor, in particular of an optoelectronic sensor, to a fieldbus via a connection module in which a sensor connected to a connection module transmits operating parameters via a sensor interface to a gateway circuit of the connection module and in which the gateway circuit communicates with the fieldbus on the basis of the operating parameters transmitted by the sensor, with the connection module not necessarily having to be equipped with an I/O circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">This method makes it possible, in a similar manner as with the explained further development of the connection module, for the user generally not to have to parameterize the connection module and a sensor connected thereto separately. It is rather sufficient for the user to parameterize the connected sensor via the operating interface anyway provided, i.e. to provide the operating parameters required for the communication with the fieldbus. These operating parameters can then be transmitted by the sensor via the sensor interface of the connection module to the gateway circuit, including a possible I/O circuit of the connection module.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">In this method, too, the said operating parameters can, for example, also be an identification number of the sensor within the network or the fieldbus system, a data length to be used or a baud rate to be used.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">The operating parameters are preferably automatically transmitted from the connected sensor to the gateway circuit of the connection module at the start of operation of the connection module or of the sensor, with the gateway circuit in particular querying the sensor interface only during a limited parameterization time interval from the start of operation. The decisive event for the transmission of the operating parameters can here also be the start of operation of the connection module and/or of the connected sensor; if both devices are not switched on simultaneously, the transmission in particular takes place on the start of operation of the device switched on later.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">It is preferred for the operating parameters transmitted by the sensor to be stored in a permanent memory of the connection module. It is possible in this case that those operating parameters already stored in the permanent memory of the connection module are transmitted from the permanent memory to the connected sensor directly after the start of operation of the connection module or of the sensor and still before the explained transmission of operating parameters by the sensor to the gateway circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">In an advantageous embodiment of this method, in the event that no operation parameters are received by the sensor at the sensor interface after a start of operation of the connection module, those operating parameters are used for the communication with the fieldbus which were already stored in the said permanent memory before the last start of operation of the connection module. In other words, the connection module uses the last received and stored operating parameters if no new operating parameters are received at the sensor interface after a new start. This can, for example, be the case if the previously connected sensor has in the meantime been replaced by a simple unit such as an I/O circuit or an actuator which does not permit any initialization of the connection module with operating parameters. In this case, the relevant unit can nevertheless be addressed via the fieldbus without any further parameterization measures since the connection module can make use of the last stored operating parameters.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Finally, it is also of advantage with the explained method for the operating parameters to be stored in a permanent memory of the connection module replaceably by the user. In this case the connection module used can be replaced without a reparameterization being necessary since the permanent memory can be replaced with the previously stored operating parameters and can thus be used in the new connection module.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Further areas of applicability of the present invention will become apparent from the detailed description provided hereinafter. It should be understood that the detailed description and specific examples, while indicating the preferred embodiment of the invention, are intended for purposes of illustration only and are not intended to limit the scope of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The present invention will become more fully understood from the detailed description and the accompanying drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> schematically shows the design of a connection module connected to a fieldbus and to an optoelectronic sensor; and</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows this connection module in a perspective view.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The following description of the preferred embodiments is merely exemplary in nature and is in no way intended to limit the invention, its application, or uses.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows, in a block diagram, a connection module <b>11</b> with a serial bus interface <b>13</b> and a parallel sensor interface <b>15</b>. The latter has a serial data interface <b>17</b> and—parallel thereto—a switch input <b>19</b> and a switch output <b>21</b>. The connection module <b>11</b> is connected to a fieldbus <b>23</b>, for example of the type Profibus or DeviceNet, via the bus interface <b>13</b>. Furthermore, the connection module <b>11</b> is connected via the serial data interface <b>17</b> and via the switch input <b>19</b> and the switch output <b>21</b> of the sensor interface <b>15</b> to an optoelectronic sensor <b>25</b>, for example to an optical code reader.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The connection module <b>11</b> furthermore has a gateway circuit <b>27</b> which is connected to the bus interface <b>13</b> and to the serial data interface <b>17</b> of the sensor interface <b>15</b>. The gateway circuit <b>27</b> serves for the conversion of the data exchanged between the bus interface <b>13</b> and the sensor interface <b>15</b> into the respective data format, as will be explained in the following.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">An I/O circuit <b>29</b>, which specifically serves for the conversion of the switching data or switching signals exchanged between the bus interface <b>13</b> and the switch input <b>19</b> and the switch output <b>21</b>, as will likewise be explained below, is connected to the gateway circuit <b>27</b>. The I/O circuit <b>29</b> is connected for this purpose indirectly via the gateway circuit <b>27</b> to the bus interface <b>13</b>, on the one hand, and to the switch input <b>19</b> and the switch output <b>21</b> of the sensor interface <b>15</b>, on the other hand.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The connection module <b>11</b> furthermore has an optional permanent memory <b>33</b> for the storage of operating parameters. The permanent memory <b>33</b> is connected to the serial data interface <b>17</b> of the sensor interface <b>15</b>. Alternatively or additionally, the permanent memory <b>33</b> can, however, also be directly connected to the gateway circuit <b>27</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A plurality of I/O circuits in accordance with the number of circuit inputs/outputs <b>19</b>, <b>21</b> can also be provided instead of a single I/O circuit <b>29</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The connection module <b>11</b> is furthermore provided with an energy supply not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, which can, for example, be a <b>24</b>V power supply. The energy supply preferably jointly provides the connection module <b>11</b> and the optoelectronic sensor <b>25</b> with the required operating voltage so that the start of operation of these two devices generally also takes place simultaneously. The connection between the connection module <b>11</b> and the sensor <b>25</b> takes place via one single common cable harness.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a possible embodiment of the connection module <b>11</b> in accordance with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in a schematic perspective view. Here, a passive motherboard <b>41</b> is provided at which a card <b>43</b> replaceable by the user is mounted which includes both the gateway switch <b>27</b> and the I/O circuit <b>29</b> in accordance with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, including a micro-controller.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">A further card <b>45</b> (insertable card) replaceable by the user is furthermore used at the motherboard <b>21</b> and carries the permanent memory <b>33</b> in accordance with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> together with an associated micro-controller.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The motherboard <b>41</b> is furthermore provided with a serial plug connector <b>47</b>, which serves as a bus interface <b>13</b> in accordance with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and with parallel clamp connectors <b>49</b>, which serve as the serial data interface <b>17</b> or the switch input <b>19</b> and switch output <b>21</b> of the sensor interface <b>15</b> in accordance with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The motherboard <b>41</b> connects the contacts for the gateway-I/O card <b>43</b>, the contacts for the optional permanent memory card <b>45</b>, the serial plug connector <b>47</b> and the parallel clamp connectors <b>49</b> via conductor tracks not shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The motherboard <b>41</b>, the gateway-I/O card <b>43</b>, the permanent memory cad <b>45</b>, the serial plug connector <b>47</b> and the parallel clamp connectors <b>49</b> are arranged within a common housing <b>51</b> which is open at the upper side and at the two sides facing the viewer in the view in accordance with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The connection module <b>11</b> is thus a substantially passive module with an active gateway-I/O card <b>43</b> and an active permanent memory card <b>45</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The connection module <b>11</b> showed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> serves for the connection of the sensor <b>25</b> to the fieldbus <b>23</b>. The connection module <b>11</b> in this process serves, on the one hand, as an adapter between the serial interface of the sensor <b>25</b> and the serial interface of the fieldbus <b>23</b>. On the other hand, a translation takes place within the connection module <b>11</b> of the data exchanged at the interface <b>15</b> with the sensor <b>25</b> into the format of the data exchanged at the bus interface <b>13</b>, and vice versa. This mutual data conversion takes place in the gateway circuit <b>27</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Since a gateway circuit usually adapts a serial data interface (interface <b>17</b>) to a bus system, in addition to the gateway circuit <b>27</b> at least one I/O circuit <b>29</b> is provided which is additionally integrated into the connection module <b>11</b>. The I/O circuit <b>29</b> therefore permits the direct communication of the fieldbus <b>23</b> with the switch inputs/outputs of the sensor <b>25</b>. In the embodiment in accordance with <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the I/O circuit <b>29</b> communicates for this purpose indirectly via the gateway circuit <b>27</b> with the bus interface <b>13</b> and with the switch input <b>19</b> and the switch output <b>21</b>, with a direct connection to the interfaces <b>13</b>, <b>19</b>, <b>21</b> alternatively also being able to be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">A particular advantage of the connection module <b>11</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> lies in the fact that it permits a linking of the serial fieldbus <b>23</b> to the parallel interface of the sensor <b>25</b> due to the integrated I/O circuit <b>29</b> without further I/O modules being required in addition to the actual connection module <b>11</b> which have to be connected between the sensor <b>25</b> and the fieldbus <b>23</b>. The I/O circuit <b>29</b> takes over the conversion inside the connection module <b>11</b> of the switching data received serially at the bus interface <b>13</b> into digital switching signals for the parallel switch inputs/outputs <b>19</b>, <b>21</b>, and vice versa.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">The digital switching signals can thereby be controlled in a simple manner in the process mapping of the fieldbus <b>23</b> used without additional I/O modules being necessary which have to be separately parameterized for the specific fieldbus <b>23</b>. The combination of sensor <b>25</b> and connection module <b>11</b> with a gateway circuit <b>27</b> and an I/O circuit <b>29</b> presents itself to the user as one single device, with both the sensor <b>25</b> and the gateway circuit <b>27</b> and the I/O circuit <b>29</b> being able to be jointly parameterized inside the operating interface of the sensor <b>25</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">Since the gateway circuit <b>27</b> and the I/O circuit <b>29</b> are installed in the connection module <b>11</b> (card <b>43</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>), a particularly short lead connection is possible to the parallel clamp connectors <b>49</b> and thus to the switch inputs/outputs of the sensor <b>25</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">Since the gateway-I/O card <b>43</b> is replaceable without tools or at most with a simple tool, the connection module <b>11</b> can be simply adapted to different fieldbus systems and the related connection module <b>11</b> with the further components can be used flexibly for different fieldbus systems.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The optional permanent memory <b>33</b> permits the non-volatile storage of the operating parameters which permit the identification of the connected sensor <b>25</b> by the fieldbus <b>23</b> and fix the type of communication with the fieldbus <b>23</b>. Since the connection module <b>11</b> is fitted with such a permanent memory <b>33</b>, these operating parameters are also available after an intermediate deactivation of the connection module <b>11</b> so that no new parameterization is required after a switching off and a repeated switching on of the connection module <b>11</b>. Since the permanent memory <b>33</b> is present in the form of the card <b>45</b> replaceable by the user, the connection module <b>11</b> can be replaced in a very simple manner in the event of a defect, for example, since the required operating parameters are maintained by taking over the permanent memory card <b>45</b> into the new connection module.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The parameterization of the gateway circuit <b>27</b> and of the I/O circuit <b>29</b> using the permanent memory <b>33</b> can take place in the following manner:</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">After a start of operation of the connection module <b>11</b>—and due to the common voltage supply of the connected sensor <b>25</b>, too—a connection is set up between the sensor <b>25</b> and the permanent memory <b>33</b> of the connection module <b>11</b> via the serial data interface <b>17</b> of the sensor interface <b>15</b> during a limited parameterization time interval. In this process, the sensor <b>25</b> recognizes whether it is connected to a connection module <b>11</b> and whether a permanent memory <b>33</b> with valid operating parameters is present. In the applicable case, the sensor <b>25</b> reads the operating parameters from the permanent memory <b>33</b> via the sensor interface <b>15</b> and transmits the operating parameters—again via the sensor interface <b>15</b>—to the gateway circuit <b>27</b>, including the I/O circuit <b>29</b>. In this process, a check, an additional storage and/or a supplementation of the operating parameters can take place inside the sensor <b>25</b> in the meantime.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">If the sensor <b>25</b>, in contrast, does not receive any operating parameters from the permanent memory <b>33</b> despite its connection to it—for example on the basis of a defect of the permanent memory <b>33</b>—it transmits those operating parameters to the gateway circuit <b>27</b>, including the I/O circuit <b>29</b>, which the sensor <b>25</b> has stored in its own non-volatile memory.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">If, vice versa, the gateway circuit <b>27</b> of the connection module <b>11</b> does not receive any operating data at the serial data interface <b>17</b> from the sensor <b>25</b> during the parameterization time interval after a start of operation, it reads the last stored and used operating parameters from the permanent memory <b>33</b> and uses them for the communication with the fieldbus <b>23</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">In view of this automatic parameterization of the gateway circuit <b>27</b>, including the I/O circuit <b>29</b>, the user does not have to parameterize two or more devices separately in order to configure the system for the connection to the fieldbus <b>23</b>. It is instead sufficient for the user only to initialize the sensor <b>25</b> with the operating parameters inside its operating interface. In the event of a replacement of the sensor <b>25</b>, no new parameterization is likewise necessary, since the operating parameters previously transmitted to the gateway circuit <b>27</b> of the connection module <b>11</b> and stored in the permanent memory <b>33</b> there can continue to be used.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Even if the connection module <b>11</b> does not have any permanent memory <b>33</b>, it is possible for the operating parameters stored in the sensor <b>25</b> to be transmitted automatically from the connected sensor <b>25</b> via the serial data interface <b>17</b> of the sensor interface <b>15</b> to the gateway circuit <b>27</b> and, optionally, to the I/O circuit <b>29</b> after a restart of the system, preferably only during a limited parameterization time interval. The advantage also hereby results in this case that the user does not have to parameterize both the sensor <b>25</b> and the gateway circuit <b>27</b> of the connection module <b>11</b> separately.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The description of the invention is merely exemplary in nature and, thus, variations that do not depart from the gist of the invention are intended to be within the scope of the invention. Such variations are not to be regarded as a departure from the spirit and scope of the invention.</p>
<heading id="h-0006" level="1">REFERENCE NUMERAL LIST</heading>
<p id="p-0062" num="0000">
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0061"><b>11</b> connection module</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0002" num="0062"><b>13</b> bus interface</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0003" num="0063"><b>15</b> sensor interface</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0004" num="0064"><b>17</b> serial data interface</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0005" num="0065"><b>19</b> switch input</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0006" num="0066"><b>21</b> switch output</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0007" num="0067"><b>23</b> fieldbus</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0008" num="0068"><b>25</b> optoelectronic sensor</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0009" num="0069"><b>27</b> gateway circuit</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0010" num="0070"><b>29</b> I/O circuit</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0011" num="0071"><b>33</b> permanent memory</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0012" num="0072"><b>41</b> motherboard</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0013" num="0073"><b>43</b> Gateway-I/O card</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0014" num="0074"><b>45</b> permanent memory card</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0015" num="0075"><b>47</b> serial plug connector</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0016" num="0076"><b>49</b> parallel clamp connector</li>
    <li id="ul0001-0017" num="0077"><b>51</b> housing</li>
</ul>
</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A connection module (<b>11</b>) for the connection of a sensor, in particular of an optoelectronic sensor (<b>25</b>), to a fieldbus (<b>23</b>), comprising:
<claim-text>a sensor interface (<b>15</b>, <b>49</b>) for the connection of the connection module to an interface of a sensor;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a serial bus interface (<b>13</b>, <b>47</b>) for the connection of the connection module to an interface of a fieldbus; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>), which is connected to the bus interface and to the sensor interface to convert data received at the bus interface into a data format of a connected sensor and to output them at the sensor interface and to convert data received at the sensor interface into a data format of the fieldbus and to output them at the bus interface, wherein the sensor interface (<b>15</b>, <b>49</b>) of the connection module (<b>11</b>) is made as a parallel interface with a serial data interface (<b>17</b>) and with at least one separate switch input/output (<b>19</b>, <b>21</b>) parallel thereto; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>at least one I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) is integrated into the connection module (<b>11</b>) and is connected to the bus interface and to the sensor interface to convert switching data serially received at the bus interface into switching signals and to output them at the switch input/output of the sensor interface and to convert switching signals received in parallel at the switch input/output of the sensor interface into switching data and to output them serially at the bus interface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>) is integrated into the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) is made as a unit replaceable by the user, in particular a card.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that the sensor interface (<b>15</b>, <b>49</b>), the bus interface (<b>13</b>, <b>47</b>), the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) and the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) are arranged in a common housing (<b>51</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that a permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) is furthermore integrated into the connection module (<b>11</b>) for the storage of operating parameters for the communication of the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) and of the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) with the fieldbus (<b>23</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, characterized in that the permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) is made as a unit replaceable by the user.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, characterized in that the operating parameters are identification numbers, data lengths or baud rates for the fieldbus.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, characterized in that the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) and the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) are configured such that operating parameters for the communication with the fieldbus (<b>23</b>) can be communicated to the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) and to the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) from a connected sensor (<b>25</b>) via the sensor interface (<b>15</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, characterized in that the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) and the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) are configured such that the operating parameters can be transmitted at the start of operation of the connection module (<b>11</b>) or of the connected sensor (<b>25</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, characterized in that the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) and the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) are configured such that the operating parameters can be transmitted at the start of operation of the connection module (<b>11</b>) or of the connected sensor (<b>25</b>) during a limited parameterization time interval.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00008">claim 8</claim-ref>, characterized in that the connection module (<b>11</b>) is provided with a permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) in which the operating parameters transmitted via the sensor interface (<b>15</b>) can be stored, wherein the permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) is connected directly to the sensor interface (<b>15</b>) or indirectly to the sensor interface (<b>15</b>) via the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) and the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, characterized in that the permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) is configured such that operating parameters stored in the permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) can be transmitted from the permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) via the sensor interface (<b>15</b>) to the connected sensor (<b>25</b>) directly after the start of operation of the connection module (<b>11</b>) or of the connected sensor (<b>25</b>) and still before a transmission of operating parameters from the connected sensor (<b>25</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A connection module in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, characterized in that the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) and the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) are configured such that, if no operating parameters are transmitted from the connected sensor (<b>25</b>) to the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) and to the I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) after a start of operation of the connection module (<b>11</b>) or of the connected sensor (<b>25</b>), they use those operating parameters for the communication with the fieldbus (<b>23</b>) which are stored in the permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. a method for the connection of a sensor, in particular an optoelectric sensor (<b>25</b>), via a connection module (<b>11</b>) to a fieldbus (<b>23</b>);
<claim-text>a sensor (<b>25</b>) connected to a connection module (<b>11</b>) transmits operating parameters to a gateway circuit (<b>27</b>,<b>43</b>) of the connection module (<b>11</b>) via a sensor interface (<b>15</b>) of the connection module; and in that the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) communicates with the fieldbus (<b>23</b>) via a serial bus interface (<b>13</b>) on the basis of the operating parameters transmitted by the sensor (<b>25</b>), where the sensor interface (<b>15</b>, <b>49</b>) of the connection module (<b>11</b>) is made as a parallel interface with a serial data interface (<b>17</b>) and with at least one separate switch input/output (<b>19</b>, <b>21</b>) parallel thereto: and at least one I/O circuit (<b>29</b>, <b>43</b>) is integrated into the connection module (<b>11</b>) and is connected to the bus interface and to the sensor interface to convert switching data serially received at the bus interface into switching signals and to output them at the switch input/output of the sensor interface and to convert switching signals received in parallel at the switch input/output of the sensor interface into switching data and to output them serially at the bus interface.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A method in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, characterized in that the sensor (<b>25</b>) transmits the operating parameters to the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) at the start of operation of the connection module (<b>11</b>) or of the sensor (<b>25</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, characterized in that the sensor (<b>25</b>) transmits the operating parameters to the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) at the start of operation of the connection module (<b>11</b>) or of the sensor (<b>25</b>) during a limited parameterization time interval.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, characterized in that the operating parameters transmitted by the sensor (<b>25</b>) are stored in a permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) of the connection module.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A method in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, characterized in that operating parameters stored in the permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) of the connection module are transmitted from the permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) to the sensor (<b>25</b>) directly after the start of operation of the connection module (<b>11</b>) or of the sensor (<b>25</b>) and still before a transmission of operating parameters by the sensor (<b>25</b>) to the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A method in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00017">claim 17</claim-ref>, characterized in that, in the event that no operating parameters are transmitted from the sensor (<b>25</b>) to the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) after a start of operation of the connection module (<b>11</b>) or of the sensor (<b>25</b>), the gateway circuit (<b>27</b>, <b>43</b>) communicates with the fieldbus (<b>23</b>) on the basis of those operating parameters which are stored in the permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>).</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. A method in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, characterized in that the operating parameters are stored in a permanent memory (<b>33</b>, <b>45</b>) of the connection module (<b>11</b>) replaceable by the user.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00021" num="00021">
<claim-text>21. A method in accordance with <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, characterized in that the operating parameters are identification numbers, data lengths or baud rates for the fieldbus.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
