<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296672-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296672</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11448464</doc-number>
<date>20060607</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="regional">
<country>EP</country>
<doc-number>05104963</doc-number>
<date>20050607</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>66</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>23</main-group>
<subgroup>06</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>198335</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Wheel for driving a flexible handrail</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4134883</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mendelsohn et al.</name>
<date>19790100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>528 63</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5160009</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Iyoda et al.</name>
<date>19921100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>198337</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6119845</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Song</name>
<date>20000900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>198331</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6199678</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Reo</name>
<date>20010300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>198330</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6457573</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Ostermeier et al.</name>
<date>20021000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>198330</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6971497</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Illedits et al.</name>
<date>20051200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>198330</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO 2004/108581</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20041200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>198335</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>198336</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>198337</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>198331</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060272923</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061207</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Novacek</last-name>
<first-name>Thomas</first-name>
<address>
<city>Schwechat</city>
<country>AT</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>AT</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>AT</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Illedits</last-name>
<first-name>Thomas</first-name>
<address>
<city>Neufeld</city>
<country>AT</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>AT</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>AT</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Schweitzer Cornman Gross &amp; Bondell LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Inventio AG</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Hergiswil</city>
<country>CH</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Deuble</last-name>
<first-name>Mark A</first-name>
<department>3651</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A wheel for driving a flexible handrail of an escalator or moving walk. The wheel has a power transmission element that can be turned about an axis of rotation and that has, on its circumference a contact surface through which an outwardly acting radial force can be exerted. The wheel also has two base sheaves that are arranged coaxially to the power transmission element. Each base sheave has a plurality of slits that are arranged in the outer edge area of the base sheave and extend toward the axis of rotation. The slits of one base sheave form, with the slits of the other base sheave, slit pairs. The wheel has a circumferential cover with an inside surface against which the contact surface of the power transmission element rests. A plurality of pins is arranged in the circumferential cover, each pin engaging a separate respective slit pair.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="110.49mm" wi="134.11mm" file="US07296672-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="222.42mm" wi="147.24mm" file="US07296672-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="108.63mm" wi="128.10mm" file="US07296672-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a wheel for driving a flexible handrail of an escalator or moving walk.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Escalators and moving walks generally have balustrades that are locationally fixed at their sides. Mounted on or against the balustrades are band-shaped handrails that move relative to the balustrades as synchronously as possible with the step elements of the escalator or moving walk. The handrails consist essentially of a flexible band and can be driven by a wheel that can itself be driven directly or indirectly by a motor. At the same time, the wheel can also serve the function of a diverter sheave to divert the handrail where a change of direction of the handrail is required.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The drive of handrails should be as smooth and continuous as possible, free of jerks, as quiet as possible, and the wheel as well as the handrail itself should be constructed in such a manner that noise and wear are minimized. In particular, so-called slip-stick effects should be avoided. Slip-stick effects are instability effects associated with parameters which affect the static friction and sliding friction between the handrail and the contact surface of the wheel that drives the handrail. To realize a continuous drive of the handrail, sliding of the handrail relative to the wheel should be avoided, which means that the static friction should not be less than a certain amount. In practice, however, it is common for brief periods of sliding friction to occur, which is comparable to aquaplaning and results in the slip-stick effect.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">To prevent slip-stick effects, a known wheel for driving a handrail is executed essentially as a driving-wheel tire. The driving-wheel tire is filled with a filling agent such as compressed air or an inert gas. The driving-wheel tire acts as a power transmission element with its outer circumferential surface resting under pressure against the inner surface of the handrail so that on rotation of the driving-wheel tire the handrail is driven by the static friction acting between the power transmission element and the handrail.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Disadvantageous with such a driving wheel is, among others, the formation of bulges on the driving-wheel tire, which occurs as a consequence of its elasticity, as well as substantial wear of the tire through use.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">It is accordingly an objective of the present invention to provide a wheel for driving a handrail of an escalator or moving walk with which the disadvantages of the prior art can be avoided.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In accordance with the invention, a wheel for driving a flexible handrail of an escalator or moving walk, also known as a caterpillar wheel, has a power transmission element that can be turned about an axis of rotation. The cross sections of the power transmission element that lie perpendicular to the axis of rotation have circular enveloping curves whose centers lie on the axis of rotation. The approximately cylindrical area of the external surface of the power transmission element forms a contact surface that rests under pressure against the handrail and drives or moves the handrail along with it. The wheel also contains two base sheaves that are arranged coaxially with the power transmission element and have approximately the same diameter. On the side facing the power transmission element, each base sheave is provided with a plurality of cutouts. These cutouts are arranged in an outer edge area of the base sheave and are aligned toward the axis of rotation. The cutouts of the first base sheave along with the cutouts of the other base sheave form cutout pairs. The wheel has a plurality of pins, the ends of one pin always engaging in the cutouts of a given cutout pair. The pins are accommodated in an enveloping cover, which rests with at least a portion of its inner surface against the contact surface of the power transmission element.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The base sheaves hold the power transmission element under tension and prevent its lateral displacement. The power transmission element acts in the outward radial direction on the enveloping cover and holds the latter under tension against the handrail in such manner that the friction between the enveloping cover and the handrail is sufficiently high to uninterruptedly manifest itself as static friction, not interrupted by phases of sliding friction.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The pins increase the rigidity of the enveloping cover. An enveloping cover can therefore be selected which is relatively easily elastically deformable and which therefore rests closely against the handrail with no risk of bulge formation of bulges.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The power transmission element can consist of at least one gas-filled tire-like tube that is filled with flowable material, preferably a gas.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Alternatively or additionally to such a tire-like tube, the wheel can contain as the power transmission element one or more power transmission sheaves.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The two base sheaves are usually arranged axially on opposite sides of the power transmission element. The wheel can have further base sheaves that are arranged adjacent to, or with a gap between, the first-mentioned base sheaves. The base sheaves guide the power transmission element at its sides or grip the power transmission element and prevent its lateral displacement.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The power transmission element can be divided into several power transmission units, preferably in the axial direction. Adjacent power transmission units can be separated from each other by the further base sheaves, which can function as a power transmission element.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The cutouts of one cutout pair are usually executed identically and arranged in line with each other. Their shape can either match the ends of the pins or have somewhat larger dimensions so as to allow the pins a certain amount of play.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Especially to facilitate the installation and any necessary replacement of individual pins, it has proved advantageous to execute the cutouts as breakthroughs of the base sheave. It is preferable for such slit-like cutouts to start at the outer circumferential surface and to be directed toward the axis of rotation.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Important advantages of the new wheel include prevention of the slip-stick effect between the wheel and the handrail and prevention of bulge formation in the contact area of the wheel and handrail.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The slip-stick effect is essentially determined by the ratio of static friction and sliding friction between the enveloping cover of the wheel and the handrail. The type of friction essentially depends firstly on the coefficients of static and sliding friction between the materials of the cover of the wheel and the handrail; secondly on the pressure under which the enveloping cover of the wheel rests against the handrail; and thirdly on the extent of the contact surface.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">The formation of bulges essentially depends on the respective rigidity of the material as well as the thickness of the material since, depending on these, bulges can form both in and perpendicular to the direction of motion and result in vibrations that create noise and wear.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">If the slip-stick effect is avoided, the creation of noise is reduced to the extent that it depends on the energy that is freed on transition from static friction to sliding friction. If the formation of bulges is reduced, the creation of noise is reduced to the extent that it depends on the resulting vibrations. At the same time, wear of the respective components and the power required for driving are reduced while ride comfort is increased.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">It is self-evident that, in addition to the shape given to the individual components, the selection of suitable materials is of great importance for the characteristics of the wheel. The base sheaves can consist of, for example, PE-HD, PA, or metallic materials. The pins can be made of a suitable metal or of PE-HD or PA. For the enveloping cover it is advantageous to choose an elastomer, NR, SBR, or HNBR, since with such materials a high coefficient of static friction can be attained. The power transmission element can take the form of a body made from an elastomer or fluid-pressure filled tire-like tube. Attention is expressly drawn to the fact that such materials are to be understood as merely illustrative of materials that can be used.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">It is preferable for the wheel to be driven by a lantern pinion, such as shown in EP1464609. The lantern pinion engages in the step chain and turns the wheel which comes into contact with the handrail either on the upper surface or the lower surface of the handrail and moves the handrail. Alternatively the wheel can be driven by a conventional handrail drive unit such as a friction wheel.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Further characteristics and advantages of the invention are explained below in relation to exemplary embodiments and by reference to the annexed drawings, wherein</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a highly simplified side view representation of a portion of a moving walk or escalator with a handrail that can be driven by means of a wheel according to the invention;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a partial diagrammatical representation of a drive wheel according to the invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a cross-sectional view of the wheel shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, containing the axis of rotation.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a wheel <b>10</b> according to the invention that can be turned about an axis of rotation A and drives a handrail <b>11</b>. The handrail <b>11</b> is located on the upper edge of a balustrade <b>12</b> that is arranged at the side of not-shown step elements of the escalator or moving walk. The handrail <b>11</b> lies longitudinally at almost 180° to the wheel <b>10</b>. Drive of the wheel <b>10</b> takes place, for example, by means of a motor <b>13</b> via an endless element <b>14</b> and a drive wheel <b>15</b>. A diverter pulley <b>16</b> is also provided for the handrail. The wheel <b>10</b> is fastened in a conventional manner to a locationally fixed supporting construction <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">According to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> the wheel <b>10</b> has two base sheaves <b>20</b>, <b>21</b>, a power transmission element <b>40</b>, an enveloping cover <b>60</b>, and a plurality of pins <b>80</b>. The wheel <b>10</b> can be either directly or indirectly motor driven and serves to drive the flexible handrail <b>12</b> of the escalator or moving walk, which is guided on the circumference of the wheel <b>10</b>. The handrail <b>12</b> can overlap the side of the wheel <b>10</b> or embrace it.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Each of the base sheaves <b>20</b>, <b>21</b> has two side sheave surfaces <b>22</b> and a circumferential surface <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In addition to the base sheaves <b>20</b>, <b>21</b>, one or more further base sheaves can be provided. For example, a further base sheave <b>23</b> can be arranged at a location, bordering on each of the base sheaves <b>20</b> and <b>21</b>, or a further base sheave can be arranged centrally between the base sheaves <b>20</b>, <b>21</b> at location <b>23</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In the areas of their peripheral edges the base sheaves <b>20</b>, <b>21</b> contain cutouts <b>26</b> that extend toward the axis of rotation A. These cutouts <b>26</b> take the form of slits that extend from the circumferential surface <b>24</b> of the base sheave toward the axis A. Each of the cutouts <b>26</b> of base sheave <b>20</b> forms, along with a cutout of the other base sheave <b>21</b>, a cutout pair.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">The cutouts need not be executed as breakthroughs through the sheaves but can also be executed as grooves in the inner side surface <b>22</b> of the sheave.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">According to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> the cutouts are arranged radially but they could also be at an angle to the radial direction which angle must self-evidently be considerably less than 90°.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">In the present exemplary embodiment, the two base sheaves <b>20</b>, <b>21</b> are formed identically and the slit-like cutouts <b>26</b> are also formed identically. The base sheaves <b>20</b>, <b>21</b> are arranged in such manner that the cutouts <b>26</b> lie not only in register with each other but also lie parallel with the axis A so that rods <b>80</b>, which extend into and are supported by the cutouts, can be straight. Other arrangements are, however, possible, with bent or bendable rods <b>80</b> being required for cutout pairs that are not connected by a line parallel to the axis.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Arranged or held between the base sheaves <b>20</b>, <b>21</b> is the power transmission element <b>40</b>. The power transmission element <b>40</b> has cross sections (in the end-face direction) that have envelopes of curvature that are circles whose centers lie on the axis of rotation A. On the circumference of the power transmission element <b>40</b> there is a contact surface <b>42</b> that is held under tension on the circumferential cover <b>60</b>. In the present exemplary embodiment, not only are the enveloping curves circular but also are the entire cross sections, and the power transmission element <b>40</b> has approximately the form of a short cylinder.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">The power transmission element <b>40</b> can be divided into two power transmission units. This is particularly advantageous if in total three base sheaves are provided that are separated from each other at a distance, such as by locating a central sheave at location <b>23</b>′ between sheaves <b>20</b> and <b>21</b>. One power transmission unit is arranged between the base sheave <b>20</b> and the sheave at location <b>23</b>′, and the other power transmission unit is arranged between the base sheave <b>21</b> and the sheave at location <b>23</b>′.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The power transmission element <b>40</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref> is executed as a tire-like tube that is filled with a fluid, gas, or other filling agent that is under pressure.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The enveloping cover <b>60</b> is made of a flexible elastic material and has on its outer surface ribs <b>62</b>. In the radial direction the circumferential cover <b>60</b> projects outward beyond the base sheaves <b>20</b>, <b>21</b>. On its inside surface <b>64</b> the circumferential cover <b>60</b> is in contact with the contact surface <b>42</b> of the power transmission element <b>40</b> by which it is radially pretensioned in the outward direction. Furthermore, the circumferential cover <b>60</b> has cutouts extending inwardly from its inside surface <b>64</b> that, in the present exemplary embodiment, are aligned parallel to the axis of rotation A.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">The pins <b>80</b> are accommodated in these cutouts and therefore are integrated to a certain extent into the circumferential cover <b>60</b>. The pins <b>80</b> have ends <b>82</b>, <b>83</b> that project from the circumferential cover <b>60</b> in the direction of the axis A and into the cutouts <b>26</b> of the base sheaves <b>20</b> and <b>21</b>. The cross sections of the pins <b>80</b> all comprise identical circles but the pins <b>80</b> can also have other cross sections, and can also vary along the length of the pins <b>80</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">If the cutouts <b>26</b> are slit-shaped, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>, the pins <b>80</b> can project through the cutouts <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">According to the invention, the pins <b>80</b> of the circumferential cover <b>60</b> along with the cutouts <b>26</b> of the base sheaves <b>21</b>, <b>22</b>, <b>23</b> form an interlocking connection for the purpose of converting a rotational motion of the base sheaves <b>21</b>, <b>22</b>, <b>23</b> into a rotational motion of the circumferential cover <b>60</b>. Between the circumferential cover <b>60</b> and the inside surface of the handrail <b>11</b> a frictional transmission of power takes place. By means of this frictional connection, the rotation of the circumferential cover <b>60</b> is converted into motion of the handrail <b>11</b>. The necessary press-on pressure between circumferential cover <b>60</b> and handrail <b>11</b> is essentially provided by the power transmission element <b>40</b> and can be changed by changing the internal pressure in the power transmission element <b>40</b>. The grooves and slit-shaped cutouts <b>26</b> that run radially on the sheaves <b>21</b>, <b>22</b> allow a certain movement of the rods <b>80</b> and therefore also of the circumferential cover <b>60</b> in the radial direction. By increasing the internal pressure in the power transmission element <b>40</b>, the circumferential cover <b>60</b> can be moved radially outward along with the rods <b>80</b> so as to increase the press-on pressure applied to the handrail. The same effect can also be attained if rods <b>80</b> are used that are themselves flexible but cannot move radially in the area of the base sheaves <b>21</b>, <b>22</b>.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>We claim:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A wheel for driving a flexible handrail of an escalator or moving walk, the wheel having a power transmission element that can be turned about an axis of rotation and having cross sections perpendicular to the axis of rotation have circular enveloping curves with centers lying on the axis of rotation and having on a circumference a contact surface through which an outwardly acting radial force can be exerted, the wheel further comprising:
<claim-text>two base sheaves arranged coaxially to the power transmission element, each base sheave having a plurality of cutouts arranged on a side of the base sheave that faces the other base sheave, the cutouts being located in an outer edge area of the base sheave and form, with the cutouts of the other base sheave, cutout pairs;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a circumferential cover with an inner surface that faces the axis of rotation and an outer surface upon which at least part of a contact surface of the power transmission element rests; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of pins arranged in the circumferential cover, a different one of the pins engaging in each cutout pair.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The wheel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the power transmission element comprises at least one gas-filled tire-like tube that is filled with a flowable material.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The wheel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref> wherein the flowable material is a gas.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The wheel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the power transmission element contains at least one power transmission sheave.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The wheel according to one <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the wheel has at least one further base sheave arranged between the two base sheaves.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The wheel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">2</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">4</claim-ref> or <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">5</claim-ref>, wherein the power transmission element is divided into a plurality of power transmission units.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The wheel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">2</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">4</claim-ref> or <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">5</claim-ref>, wherein the cutouts of a cutout pair are linearly aligned.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The wheel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">2</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">4</claim-ref> or <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">5</claim-ref>, wherein the cutouts are in the form of slits.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The wheel according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">2</claim-ref>, <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">4</claim-ref> or <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">5</claim-ref>, wherein the cutouts start from an outer circumferential surface of the base sheave and extend toward the axis of rotation.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
