<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297470-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297470</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10751807</doc-number>
<date>20040105</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>584</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>03</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>7</main-group>
<subgroup>20</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>11</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>127</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>430315</main-classification>
<further-classification>430319</further-classification>
<further-classification>430320</further-classification>
<further-classification>430323</further-classification>
<further-classification>430324</further-classification>
<further-classification>430330</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Image transfer process for thin film component definition</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2003/0182790</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Hsiao et al.</name>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 2960315</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2001-344711</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<date>20011200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>19</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>9</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>None</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>11</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050147924</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050707</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Cornwell</last-name>
<first-name>Dwight</first-name>
<address>
<city>Salinas</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Werner</last-name>
<first-name>Douglas Johnson</first-name>
<address>
<city>Fremont</city>
<state>CA</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Zilka-Kotab, PC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Hitachi Global Storage Technologies Netherlands B.V.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<country>NL</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>McPherson</last-name>
<first-name>John A.</first-name>
<department>1756</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A method for fabricating a thin film component includes forming a wafer having a thin film layer, a release layer, and a patterned layer of photoresist. The pattern of the layer of photoresist is transferred to the release layer and the thin film layer. A layer of metal is added to the wafer. The wafer is heated to a temperature above a glass transition temperature of the photoresist for a period of time sufficient to cause deformation of the photoresist to an extent that the photoresist creates cracks in the metal layer. A solvent is applied to the wafer to dissolve the release layer, the solvent penetrating the cracks in the metal layer to reach the release layer. The release layer and any material above the release layer are removed.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="92.63mm" wi="128.95mm" file="US07297470-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="111.08mm" wi="129.20mm" file="US07297470-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="241.13mm" wi="127.42mm" file="US07297470-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="227.25mm" wi="166.45mm" file="US07297470-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="224.62mm" wi="168.57mm" file="US07297470-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="194.73mm" wi="161.37mm" file="US07297470-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to thin film device fabrication, and more particularly, this invention relates to an image transfer process for defining a width of a thin film layer or layers.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The heart of a computer is a magnetic disk drive which includes a rotating magnetic disk, a slider that has read and write heads, a suspension arm above the rotating disk and an actuator arm that swings the suspension arm to place the read and write heads over selected circular tracks on the rotating disk. The suspension arm biases the slider into contact with the surface of the disk when the disk is not rotating but, when the disk rotates, air is swirled by the rotating disk adjacent an air bearing surface (ABS) of the slider causing the slider to ride on an air bearing a slight distance from the surface of the rotating disk. When the slider rides on the air bearing the write and read heads are employed for writing magnetic impressions to and reading magnetic signal fields from the rotating disk. The read and write heads are connected to processing circuitry that operates according to a computer program to implement the writing and reading functions.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In high capacity disk drives, magnetoresistive (MR) read sensors, commonly referred to as MR heads, are the prevailing read sensors because of their capability to read data from a surface of a disk at greater track and linear densities than thin film inductive heads. An MR sensor detects a magnetic field through the change in the resistance of its MR sensing layer (also referred to as an “MR element”) as a function of the strength and direction of the magnetic flux being sensed by the MR layer.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The conventional MR sensor operates on the basis of the anisotropic magnetoresistive (AMR) effect in which an MR element resistance varies as the square of the cosine of the angle between the magnetization in the MR element and the direction of sense current flow through the MR element. Recorded data can be read from a magnetic medium because the external magnetic field from the recorded magnetic medium (the signal field) causes a change in the direction of magnetization of the MR element, which in turn causes a change in resistance of the MR element and a corresponding change in the sensed current or voltage.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Another type of MR sensor is the giant magnetoresistance (GMR) sensor manifesting the GMR effect. In GMR sensors, the resistance of the GMR sensor varies as a function of the spin-dependent transmission of the conduction electrons between ferromagnetic layers separated by a non-magnetic layer (spacer) and the accompanying spin-dependent scattering which takes place at the interface of the ferromagnetic and non-magnetic layers and within the ferromagnetic layers.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">GMR sensors using only two layers of ferromagnetic material (e.g., Ni—Fe) separated by a layer of non-magnetic material (e.g., copper) are generally referred to as spin valve (SV) sensors. In an SV sensor, one of the ferromagnetic layers, referred to as the pinned layer (reference layer), has its magnetization typically pinned by exchange coupling with an antiferromagnetic (e.g., NiO or Fe—Mn) layer. The pinning field generated by the antiferromagnetic layer should be greater than demagnetizing fields (about 200 Oe) at the operating temperature of the SV sensor (about 120° C.) to ensure that the magnetization direction of the pinned layer remains fixed during the application of external fields (e.g., fields from bits recorded on the disk). The magnetization of the other ferromagnetic layer, referred to as the free layer, however, is not fixed and is free to rotate in response to the field from the recorded magnetic medium (the signal field).</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">One well known way to increase the performance of magnetic disk drives is to increase the areal data storage density of the magnetic hard disk. This can be accomplished by reducing the written data track width, such that more tracks per inch can be written on the disk. To read data from a disk with a reduced track width, it is also necessary to develop sufficiently narrow read head components, such that unwanted magnetic field interference from adjacent data tracks is substantially eliminated.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Thin film head components such as sensors are created by wafer processing. Typically, a layer of photoresist is added to define the width of the component positioned underneath, and exposed material is removed by various processes. As components become smaller, the lithographic patterns must also become smaller yet must maintain a high resolution to properly form the components.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Shrinking thin-film head (TFH) device geometries force adoption of more advanced lithography platforms for enhanced resolution of small features. Products planned for the near-term future exceed the printing capability of the existing manufacturing platform, deep-ultraviolet (DUV, 248 nm wavelength) lithography. The 193 nm wavelength lithography platform provides extended resolving capability, but poses challenges in integration of the lithographic pattern into the TFH read-head build process.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">One difficulty is that 193 nm photoresists tend to have poor etch resistance. If reactive ion etching (RIE) is used, the topography of the photoresist pattern tends to be destroyed because the photoresist etches away along with the underlayer. If edges of the photoresist are reduced, i.e., the resolution is degraded, the edges of the component will be removed, resulting in a deformed component. Further, if too little photoresist remains, the photoresist will tend to become encapsulated by subsequently deposited materials, making liftoff difficult or impossible. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> illustrates a read head <b>100</b> just before liftoff according to a standard photolithography process. As shown, the photoresist <b>102</b> becomes shrunken and rounded from the RIE, resulting in the deposited material <b>104</b> encasing the remaining resist structure completely. The solvent cannot reach the photoresist <b>102</b> to effect the liftoff.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Prior art attempts to overcome the problem of photoresist erosion used thicker layers of photoresist. However, the photoresist tended to fall over during subsequent processing. For typical photoresists, only an aspect ratio of about 3 to 1 photoresist height/width or less is stable enough for further processing.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Yet another problem is the need for a bottom antireflective coating (BARC) to suppress standing waves and sensitivity of the photoresist's printed linewidth to fluctuations in photoresist thickness. Most BARC materials are insoluble in wet stripping reagents, complicating rework of the photoresist pattern.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Electron-beam (e-beam) lithography provides an alternative platform for extended resolving capability, but it lags behind the optical platforms in readiness and is generally less cost-effective due to low tool throughput.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A method for fabricating a thin film component includes forming a wafer having a thin film, an etch-stop layer, and a release layer, the release layer being soluble in a solvent. A layer of photoresist is added and patterned. Etching is performed to substantially remove exposed regions of the release layer and the etch-stop layer. Milling is performed to substantially remove exposed regions of the thin film. A layer of metal is added to the wafer. The wafer is baked at a temperature above a glass transition temperature of the photoresist for a period of time sufficient to cause deformation of the photoresist to an extent that the photoresist creates cracks in the metal layer. A solvent is applied to the wafer to dissolve the release layer, the solvent penetrating the cracks in the metal layer to reach the release layer. The release layer and any material above the release layer are removed.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The etch-stop layer is preferably carbon based. The release layer preferably also functions as an antireflective coating. The photoresist is preferably capable of resolving lines 60 nm wide or smaller.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">The photoresist is preferably resistant to O<sub>2 </sub>reactive ion etching, and may contain silicon to achieve this property. The layer of metal can be a monolayer or multiple layer to form such things as biasing magnets, leads, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Other aspects and advantages of the present invention will become apparent from the following detailed description, which, when taken in conjunction with the drawings, illustrate by way of example the principles of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">For a fuller understanding of the nature and advantages of the present invention, as well as the preferred mode of use, reference should be made to the following detailed description read in conjunction with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a cross sectional view of a read head during fabrication.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a flow chart of a process for fabricating a thin film component.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A-H</figref> are partial cross-sectional views of a wafer being processed according to a preferred method.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a cross sectional view of a read head during fabrication according to a preferred method.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">BEST MODE FOR CARRYING OUT THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">The following description is the best embodiment presently contemplated for carrying out the present invention. This description is made for the purpose of illustrating the general principles of the present invention and is not meant to limit the inventive concepts claimed herein.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">The present invention provides new, unique processes for defining and dimensioning thin film components. For clarity, much of the description shall be described in terms of defining a width of a magnetic sensor, one skilled in the art understanding that this process can be adapted to fabrication of many other types of electronic components.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates the general process flow of a method <b>200</b> for fabricating a thin film component. In step <b>202</b>, a wafer having a thin film layer, a release layer, and a patterned layer of photoresist is formed. In step <b>204</b>, the pattern of the layer of photoresist is transferred to the release layer. In step <b>205</b>, the wafer is subjected to ion milling to remove exposed portions of the thin film layer. A layer of metal is added to the wafer in step <b>206</b>. In step <b>208</b>, the wafer is heated to a temperature above a glass transition temperature of the photoresist for a period of time sufficient to cause deformation of the photoresist to an extent that the photoresist creates cracks in the overlying metal layer. In step <b>210</b>, a solvent is applied to the wafer to dissolve the release layer, the solvent penetrating the cracks in the metal layer to reach the release layer. The release layer and any material above the release layer are removed in step <b>212</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Following is a description of a preferred combination of process flow and material set which uniquely and satisfactorily addresses each of the preferred elements of a process for defining a read track width for a magnetic sensor:
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0001-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0002-0001" num="0027">Good adhesion of photoresist stencil materials to substrate;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0002" num="0028">Linewidth imaging capability down to 60 nm or smaller;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0003" num="0029">Suppression of thin-film interference effects on the photoresist size &amp; profile;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0004" num="0030">Ability of the photoresist pattern to withstand downstream etching processes;</li>
        <li id="ul0002-0005" num="0031">Reworkability of the photoresist stencil.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0032">The process flow is as follows.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0033">Step 1:</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0034">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, a wafer substrate including a gap layer <b>302</b> and a magnetic sensor film <b>304</b> is formed. The magnetic sensor film <b>304</b> (which can be magnetoresistive (MR), giant-magnetoresistive (GMR), magnetic tunnel-junction (MTJ), or other) is coated with a carbon film <b>306</b> of sufficient thickness and toughness to act as an etch-stop layer <b>306</b> in subsequent chemical-mechanical polishing (CMP) step 9.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0035">Step 2:</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0036">The substrate is coated with a non-photoactive “underlayer” or “release layer” material <b>308</b>, as depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>. The release layer <b>308</b> is a multifunctional layer, and also functions as a sacrificial layer. The release layer <b>308</b> is preferably formed of a material having some, and ideally, all, of the following properties:
<ul id="ul0003" list-style="none">
    <li id="ul0003-0001" num="0000">
    <ul id="ul0004" list-style="none">
        <li id="ul0004-0001" num="0037">Good adhesion to the underlying carbon so that the resist subsequently added will adhere to the substrate.</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0002" num="0038">Good resistance to downstream etching.</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0003" num="0039">Good absorption of 193 nm light to provide BARC functionality. Good antireflective qualities are desirable at these wavelengths of exposure because of the generation of standing waves, and because the process is very sensitive to minor fluctuations in resist thickness.</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0004" num="0040">Solvent strippability to simplify rework processing and to facilitate the downstream liftoff step. This is not a characteristic shared by typical BARC layers, which normally require RIE to remove. Preferably, the material is soluble in conventional liftoff solvents such as NMP. If the photo mask needs to be reworked because of misalignment, etc., the underlayer can be easily removed by applying solvent. In contrast, if dry etchable BARCs were used, a dry etching process would have to be performed, and since this layer is formed on a carbon surface, some carbon would also be removed. Thus, additional processing to replenish the carbon layer would have to be performed.</li>
        <li id="ul0004-0005" num="0041">Resistance to intermixing with the overlying photoresist image layer.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0042">One material which has all of these properties is a polyimide manufactured by Arch Chemicals, Inc. 501 Merritt 7, Norwalk, Conn. 06856 under the trade name Durimide. The coated thickness is determined by the extent of downstream etching, but may be in the range of about 20-400 nm. The methodology disclosed herein provides a new use for this preferred material, which is generally sold in a form about 10× thicker (3-6 microns) than is used in this illustrative process, and is typically used in fully cured form as a lasting part of the device structure rather than as a sacrificial layer as here.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0043">The material is baked at a temperature and time sufficient to drive off casting solvents and prevent intermixing, but insufficient to cure the polyimide (which would render it insoluble in liftoff and rework solvents). In the illustrative process, the Durimide is baked at 200° C. for two minutes.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0044">Step 3:</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0045">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3C</figref>, the substrate is coated with a photoresist “image layer” material <b>310</b> which is preferably capable of resolving lines down to 60 nm width and smaller, at a thickness and etch resistance sufficient to withstand downstream etching steps 4 and 5 such that not all of the material is removed. Since photoresist lines tend to collapse at a height/width aspect ratio greater than 4 or 5, it is preferred that the material's resistance to downstream etching be sufficient to allow its thickness to be about 250 nm or less before the etching, yet maintain a thickness of at least 100 nm after etching so that the reflow bake step 7 can be effective. A suitable photoresist material is TIS 51-23, also available from Arch Chemicals, Inc. TIS 51-23 combines excellent imaging characteristics with good resistance to RIE etching in an O<sub>2 </sub>environment, conferred by incorporation of silicon (Si) into the polymer structure. Si-containing resists have been found to improve the resistance of the imaging layer to reactive ion etching (RIE). It is believed that the Si reacts with the oxygen and forms a glass that reduces damage to the imaging layer by the RIE.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0046">A stencil of the read-head track image is formed in the image layer photoresist <b>310</b>, using 193 nm light through a suitable mask in a step and scan printer, followed by post-exposure bake and develop steps under conditions suitable for the particular imaging resist being used.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0047">Step 4:</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0048">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3D</figref>, the wafer is subjected to RIE in an O<sub>2 </sub>environment to remove the release layer and carbon etch-stop layer in the areas exposed in step 3. Again, the release layer <b>308</b> is preferably fairly resistant to the RIE due to the Si content. Experimentation with the preferred materials listed herein have shown about a 6 to 1 ratio of etch rate between the carbon layer <b>306</b> and the release layer <b>308</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0049">Step 5:</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0050">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3E</figref>, the wafer is subjected to ion milling to remove the magnetic sensor film <b>304</b> in the areas exposed in step 3. At this point, it is preferred that some image layer photoresist material <b>310</b> be left atop the release layer <b>308</b> in order for the downstream step 7 to work effectively.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0051">Step 6:</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0052">As depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3F</figref>, metal <b>312</b> is added to the wafer to form biasing magnets and electrical connections to the sensor which is protected by the photoresist stencil <b>310</b> unexposed in step 3. Any suitable process to add the metal <b>312</b> may be used, such as ion beam deposition (IBD). At this point, enough of the imaging photoresist layer <b>310</b> is typically left that it is able to support the deposited material <b>312</b> without falling over. In the lower corners <b>314</b> of the structure, the thickness of the deposited metal <b>312</b> tends to be thinner, the importance of which will become apparent during discussion of the next processing step.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0053">Step 7:</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0054">The wafer is baked at a temperature above the glass transition (Tg) of the image layer photoresist <b>310</b> for a time sufficient to cause it to flow. A temperature of about 150° C. is preferred for the materials listed herein. The resist flow causes the deposited metal layer <b>312</b> to crack and form pathways for solvent to penetrate to the release layer <b>308</b> in the subsequent step 8. In this exemplary method, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3G</figref>, the photoresist <b>310</b> swells and breaks the weak points (corners <b>314</b> and possibly other areas) of the deposited metal <b>312</b>, creating cracks at the corners <b>314</b> (exaggerated in the FIG.) that allow the solvent to penetrate to the underlying release layer <b>308</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0055">Step 8:</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0056">The wafer is exposed to a solvent such as NMP or other solvent capable of dissolving or weakening the release layer <b>308</b> to dissolve the release layer <b>308</b>, and allow lifting off of the photoresist <b>310</b> and metal <b>312</b> atop it. Upon liftoff, the deposited metal layer <b>312</b> is then generally left only in the areas originally exposed during lithographic patterning in step 3, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3H</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0057">Step 9:</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0058">An optional CMP process can be used to remove residues of metal and photoresist that may be left behind after the liftoff step 8. Formation and transfer of the read head track is now complete. The remainder of the head can then be formed.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0059"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> illustrates a read head <b>400</b> formed by the process above just before the baking of step 7. As shown, the track width is very well defined.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0060">While various embodiments have been described above, it should be understood that they have been presented by way of example only, and not limitation. Thus, the breadth and scope of a preferred embodiment should not be limited by any of the above-described exemplary embodiments, but should be defined only in accordance with the following claims and their equivalents.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method for fabricating a magnetic head, comprising:
<claim-text>forming a wafer having a sensor film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>adding an etch-stop layer to the wafer above the sensor film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>adding a release layer to the wafer above the etch-stop layer, the release layer being soluble in a solvent;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a layer of photoresist above the release layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>processing the layer of photoresist to define a pattern, the patterned layer of photoresist defining covered and uncovered regions of the layers under the patterned layer of photoresist, the covered regions being located under the patterned layer of photoresist;</claim-text>
<claim-text>etching to substantially remove the uncovered regions of the release layer and the etch-stop layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>milling to substantially remove the uncovered regions of the sensor film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>adding a layer of metal to the wafer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>baking the wafer at a temperature above a glass transition temperature of the photoresist for a period of time sufficient to cause deformation of the photoresist to an extent that the photoresist creates cracks in the metal layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>applying a solvent to the wafer to dissolve the release layer, the solvent penetrating the cracks in the metal layer to reach the release layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>removing the release layer and any portions of the layers above the release layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the etch-stop layer is carbon based.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the release layer also functions as an antireflective coating.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the layer of photoresist is capable of resolving lines 60 nm in width or smaller.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the photoresist is resistant to O<sub>2 </sub>reactive ion etching.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the photoresist contains silicon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the layer of metal forms a biasing magnet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the layer of metal forms a lead.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. A method for fabricating a thin film component, comprising:
<claim-text>forming a wafer having a thin film layer, a release layer, and a patterned layer of photoresist;</claim-text>
<claim-text>transferring the pattern of the layer of photoresist to the release layer and the thin film layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>adding a layer of metal to the wafer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>heating the wafer to a temperature above a glass transition temperature of the photoresist for a period of time sufficient to cause deformation of the photoresist to an extent that the photoresist creates cracks in the metal layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>applying a solvent to dissolve the release layer, the solvent penetrating the cracks in the metal layer to reach the release layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>removing the release layer and any portions of the layers above the release layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the wafer further includes an etch-stop layer, wherein the pattern is transferred to the release layer by reactive ion etching.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00010">claim 10</claim-ref>, wherein the etch-stop layer is carbon based.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the pattern is transferred to the thin film layer by milling.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the release layer also functions as an antireflective coating.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the layer of photoresist is capable of resolving lines 60 nm in width or smaller.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the photoresist is resistant to O<sub>2 </sub>reactive ion etching.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the photoresist contains silicon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the layer of metal forms a biasing magnet.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. A method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein the layer of metal forms a lead.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. A method for fabricating a thin film component, comprising:
<claim-text>forming a wafer having a thin film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>adding an etch-stop layer to the wafer above the thin film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>adding a release layer to the wafer above the etch-stop layer, the release layer being soluble in a solvent;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a layer of photoresist above the release layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>patterning the layer of photoresist;</claim-text>
<claim-text>etching to substantially remove exposed regions of the release layer and the etch-stop layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>milling to substantially remove exposed regions of the thin film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>adding a layer of metal to the wafer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>baking the wafer at a temperature above a glass transition temperature of the photoresist for a period of time sufficient to cause deformation of the photoresist to an extent that the photoresist creates cracks in the metal layer;</claim-text>
<claim-text>applying a solvent to the wafer to dissolve the release layer, the solvent penetrating the cracks in the metal layer to reach the release layer; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>removing the release layer and any portions of the layers above the release layer.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
