<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297615-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297615</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11341519</doc-number>
<date>20060130</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>KR</country>
<doc-number>10-2005-0040165</doc-number>
<date>20050513</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>C</section>
<class>30</class>
<subclass>B</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>20</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>N</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438486</main-classification>
<further-classification>977762</further-classification>
<further-classification>977814</further-classification>
<further-classification>977900</further-classification>
<further-classification>977938</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Si nanowire substrate, method of manufacturing the same, and method of manufacturing thin film transistor using the same</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7109072</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Saito et al.</name>
<date>20060900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438149</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0005747</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Park et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438197</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438486</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>977762</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>977814</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>977900</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>977938</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>16</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>29</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060261409</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061123</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Cho</last-name>
<first-name>Hans S.</first-name>
<address>
<city>Seoul</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Noguchi</last-name>
<first-name>Takashi</first-name>
<address>
<city>Seongnam-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="003" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Xianyu</last-name>
<first-name>Wenxu</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yongin-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="004" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Kim</last-name>
<first-name>Do-Young</first-name>
<address>
<city>Suwon-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="005" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yin</last-name>
<first-name>Huaxiang</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yongin-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="006" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Zhang</last-name>
<first-name>Xiaoxin</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yongin-si</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>KR</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>KR</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Harness, Dickey &amp; Pierce</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Samsung Electronics, Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Gyeonggi-Do</city>
<country>KR</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Elms</last-name>
<first-name>Richard T.</first-name>
<department>2824</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Lulis</last-name>
<first-name>Michael</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A silicon nanowire substrate having a structure in which a silicon nanowire film having a fine line-width is formed on a substrate, a method of manufacturing the same, and a method of manufacturing a thin film transistor using the same. The method of manufacturing the silicon nanowire substrate includes preparing a substrate, forming an insulating film on the substrate, forming a silicon film on the insulating film, patterning the insulating film and the silicon film into a strip shape, reducing the line-width of the insulating film by undercut etching at least one lateral side of the insulating film, and forming a self-aligned silicon nanowire film on an upper surface of the insulating film by melting and crystallizing the silicon film.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="148.59mm" wi="118.45mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="97.96mm" wi="115.40mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="105.16mm" wi="122.77mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="177.46mm" wi="132.25mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="177.88mm" wi="124.04mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="173.40mm" wi="120.90mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="97.54mm" wi="113.54mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="169.33mm" wi="120.73mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="172.47mm" wi="122.51mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="180.93mm" wi="131.49mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="175.01mm" wi="131.40mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="174.16mm" wi="129.71mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="177.21mm" wi="117.01mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00013" num="00013">
<img id="EMI-D00013" he="175.77mm" wi="118.62mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00013.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00014" num="00014">
<img id="EMI-D00014" he="180.76mm" wi="134.70mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00014.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00015" num="00015">
<img id="EMI-D00015" he="169.50mm" wi="115.57mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00015.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00016" num="00016">
<img id="EMI-D00016" he="177.63mm" wi="119.38mm" file="US07297615-20071120-D00016.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">PRIORITY STATEMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims the benefit of Korean Patent Application No. 10-2005-0040165, filed on May 13, 2005, in the Korean Intellectual Property Office, the disclosure of which is incorporated herein in its entirety by reference.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Example embodiments of the present invention relate to a method of manufacturing a silicon nanowire film, and more particularly, to a silicon nanowire substrate having a structure in which a silicon nanowire film having a fine line-width is formed on a substrate, and a method of manufacturing the same, and a method of manufacturing a thin film transistor using the same.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Poly crystalline silicon (poly-Si) may be applied to various electronic devices, for example, flat display devices and solar cells, as a result of having a higher mobility than amorphous silicon (a-Si). However, poly crystalline silicon has lower mobility and uniformity than single crystalline silicon. Single crystalline silicon may be useful in a system on panel (SOP) structure in which a system is formed on the display panel itself, and may have a mobility of more than 300 cm<sup>2</sup>/Vs. Single crystalline silicon allows the manufacture of improved quality switching devices required for higher performance display devices.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">Recently, to comply with stricter miniaturization requirements and higher performance devices, nano scale devices have been developed. To manufacture nano scale devices, nanowire forming techniques have been developed. A nanowire may be defined as an ultra fine line having a cross-sectional diameter of a few nanometers to a few tens of nanometers. Nanowires may be utilized in many fields, for example, laser, transistors, memories and chemical detecting sensors. Naowire materials may include carbon nanotubes (CNT), CdTe, ZnO<sub>2</sub>, and/or SiGe.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">Methods of manufacturing nanowires may be difficult and complicated. A crystal growth inducing method may be used to grow nanowires, but this method may only provide nanowire crystals grown perpendicular to a substrate, and a nanowire grown by such a method may have many impurities. In some cases, location control of the nanowire is needed, which conventional methods may have difficulty providing. Unlike crystal growth inducing methods that uses a catalyst, a nanowire may also be manufactured by lithography, in order to control their horizontal location. However, the conventional lithographic resolution limit is approximately 30 nm. Therefore, the manufacture of a nanowire having a line-width of 30 nm or less is difficult.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Example embodiments of the present invention provide a silicon nanowire substrate having a structure in which a silicon nanowire film having a line-width is formed on a substrate, a method of manufacturing the same, and a method of manufacturing a thin film transistor using the same.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">According to an example embodiment of the present invention, there is provided a silicon nanowire substrate including a substrate, an insulating film formed on the substrate in a strip shape, and a silicon nanowire film covering an upper surface of the insulating film.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In an example embodiment, the insulating film and the silicon nanowire film may have the same line-width, which may be 30 nm or less. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film may have a length in the range of 100 to 10000 nm. In an example embodiment, the substrate may be formed of at least one material selected from the group consisting of silicon, oxidized silicon, quartz, glass, sapphire, and plastic. In an example embodiment, the insulating film may be formed of at least one material selected from SiN or SiO<sub>2</sub>, and the silicon nanowire film may be single crystalline silicon.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">According to another example embodiment of the present invention, there is provided a silicon nanowire substrate including a single crystalline silicon substrate, an insulating film formed on the single crystalline silicon substrate in a strip shape, a silicon crystal seed which is epitaxially grown on the single crystalline silicon substrate and contacts one end of the insulating film, and a silicon nanowire film, which is laterally crystallized from the silicon crystal seed, covers the upper surface of the insulating film, and has an extension part which contacts the silicon crystal seed.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">In an example embodiment, the insulating film and the silicon nanowire film may have the same line-width, which may be 30 nm or less. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film may have a length in the range of 100 to 10000 nm. In an example embodiment, the insulating film may be formed of at least one material selected from SiN and SiO<sub>2</sub>, and the insulating film may comprise a SiO<sub>2 </sub>film and a SiN film sequentially stacked on the single crystalline silicon substrate. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film may be single crystalline silicon.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">According to an example embodiment of the present invention, there is provided a method of manufacturing a silicon nanowire substrate, including preparing a substrate, forming an insulating film on the substrate, forming a silicon film on the insulating film, patterning the insulating film and the silicon film into a strip shape, reducing the line-width of the insulating film by undercut etching at least one lateral side of the insulating film, and forming a self-aligned silicon nanowire film on the upper surface of the insulating film by melting and crystallizing the silicon film.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">In an example embodiment, the patterning of the insulating film may include patterning the insulating film and the silicon film to the same line-width, which may be in the range of 20 to 300 nm. In an example embodiment, the patterning of the insulating film and/or the silicon film may be performed by reactive ion etching.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">In an example embodiment, the substrate may be formed of at least one material selected from the group consisting of silicon, oxidized silicon, quartz, glass, sapphire, and plastic. In an example embodiment, the insulating film may be formed of at least one material selected from SiN or SiO<sub>2</sub>. In an example embodiment, the lateral etching of the insulating film may be performed by isotropic dry etching and/or the silicon film may be melted by laser annealing. In crystallizing the silicon film, the nucleation rate of crystallizing silicon may be 1 event/μs or less.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">In an example embodiment, the line-width of the silicon nanowire film self-aligned on the insulating film may be controlled by controlling the line-width of the insulating film, and the silicon nanowire film may have a line-width of 30 nm or less. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film may have a length in the range of 100 to 10000 nm and the silicon nanowire film may be single crystalline silicon.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">According to another example embodiment of the present invention, there is provided a method of manufacturing a silicon nanowire substrate, including preparing a single crystalline silicon substrate, forming an insulating film on the single crystalline silicon substrate, exposing the single crystalline silicon substrate by etching a region of the insulating film, forming a silicon crystal seed on the exposed surface of the single crystalline silicon substrate by epitaxially growing silicon, forming a silicon film on the upper surface of the insulating film, patterning the insulating film and the silicon film formed on the insulating film into a strip shape of which one end part contacts the silicon crystal seed, reducing the line-width of the insulating film by undercut etching at least one lateral side of the insulating film and the silicon crystal seed; melting the silicon film formed on the upper surface of the insulating film and the silicon crystal seed, and forming a self-aligned silicon nanowire film on the upper surface of the insulating film by laterally crystallizing the silicon film from the silicon crystal seed.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">In an example embodiment, the patterning of the insulating film may include patterning the insulating film and the silicon film to have the same line-width, which may be in the range of 20 to 300 nm. In an example embodiment, the patterning of the insulating film and/or the silicon film may be performed by reactive ion etching. In an example embodiment, the exposing of the single crystalline silicon substrate by etching a region of the insulating film may be performed by reactive ion etching. In an example embodiment, the insulating film may be formed of at least one material selected from SiN or SiO<sub>2</sub>, and the insulating film may comprise a SiO<sub>2 </sub>film and a SiN film sequentially stacked on the single crystalline silicon substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In an example embodiment, the lateral etching of the insulating film may be performed by isotropic dry etching, and the silicon film may be melted by laser annealing. In crystallizing the silicon film, the nucleation rate of crystallizing silicon may be 1 event/μs or less.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">In an example embodiment, the line-width of the silicon nanowire film self-aligned on the insulating film may be controlled by controlling the line-width of the insulating film, and the silicon nanowire film may have a line-width of 30 nm or less. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film may have a length in the range of 100 to 10000 nm, and the silicon nanowire film may be single crystalline silicon.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">According to an example embodiment of the present invention, there is provided a method of manufacturing a thin film transistor, including preparing a substrate, forming an insulating film on the substrate, forming a silicon film on the insulating film, patterning the insulating film and the silicon film into a strip shape, reducing the line-width of the insulating film by undercut etching at least one lateral side of the insulating film, forming a self-aligned silicon nanowire film on the upper surface of the insulating film by melting and crystallizing the silicon film, defining a source region, a drain region, and a channel region on the silicon nanowire film, sequentially forming a gate insulating film and a gate electrode on the channel region, and doping the source and drain regions with a conductive dopant.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">According to another example embodiment of the present invention, there is provided a method of manufacturing a thin film transistor, including preparing a single crystalline silicon substrate, forming an insulating film on the single crystalline silicon substrate, exposing the single crystalline silicon substrate by etching a region of the insulating film, forming a silicon crystal seed on the exposed surface of the single crystalline silicon substrate by epitaxially growing silicon, forming a silicon film on the upper surface of the insulating film and the silicon crystal seed, patterning the insulating film and the silicon film formed on the insulating film into a strip shape of which one end part contacts the silicon crystal seed, reducing the line-width of the insulating film by undercut etching at least one lateral side of the insulating film, melting the silicon film formed on the upper surface of the insulating film and the silicon crystal seed, and forming a self-aligned silicon nanowire film on the upper surface of the insulating film by laterally crystallizing the silicon film from the silicon crystal seed, cutting the silicon nanowire film to a desired length, defining a source region, a drain region, and a channel region on the silicon nanowire film, sequentially forming a gate insulating film and a gate electrode on the channel region, and doping the source and drain regions with a conductive dopant.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">In an example embodiment, the gate insulating film may be formed of at least one material selected from SiO<sub>2 </sub>and HfO<sub>2</sub>, and the gate electrode may be formed of a metal.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film manufacturing process may be simpler, and the location of the silicon nanowire film can be readily controlled.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The above and other features and advantages of example embodiments of the present invention will become more apparent by describing in detail exemplary embodiments thereof with reference to the attached drawings in which:</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view illustrating a silicon nanowire substrate according to an example embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view illustrating a silicon nanowire substrate according to another example embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A through 3G</figref> are perspective views for explaining a method of manufacturing a silicon nanowire substrate according to an example embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A through 4J</figref> are perspective views for explaining a method of manufacturing a silicon nanowire substrate according to another example embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A through 5E</figref> are perspective views for explaining an example method of manufacturing a thin film transistor using the silicon nanowire substrate manufactured by the processes depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A through 3G</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A through 6E</figref> are perspective views for explaining a n example method of manufacturing a thin film transistor using the silicon nanowire substrate manufactured by the processes depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A through 4J</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF EXAMPLE EMBODIMENTS OF THE PRESENT INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The present invention will now be described more fully with reference to the accompanying drawings, in which exemplary embodiments of the invention are shown. In the drawings, the thicknesses of layers and regions are exaggerated for clarity.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Detailed illustrative embodiments of the present invention are disclosed herein. However, specific structural and functional details disclosed herein are merely representative for purposes of describing example embodiments of the present invention. This invention may, however, may be embodied in many alternate forms and should not be construed as limited to only the embodiments set forth herein.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Accordingly, while example embodiments of the invention are capable of various modifications and alternative forms, embodiments thereof are shown by way of example in the drawings and will herein be described in detail. It should be understood, however, that there is no intent to limit example embodiments of the invention to the particular forms disclosed, but on the contrary, example embodiments of the invention are to cover all modifications, equivalents, and alternatives falling within the scope of the invention. Like numbers refer to like elements throughout the description of the figures.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">It will be understood that, although the terms first, second, etc. may be used herein to describe various elements, these elements should not be limited by these terms. These terms are only used to distinguish one element from another. For example, a first element could be termed a second element, and, similarly, a second element could be termed a first element, without departing from the scope of example embodiments of the present invention. As used herein, the term “and/or” includes any and all combinations of one or more of the associated listed items.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">It will be understood that when an element is referred to as being “connected” or “coupled” to another element, it can be directly connected or coupled to the other element or intervening elements may be present. In contrast, when an element is referred to as being “directly connected” or “directly coupled” to another element, there are no intervening elements present. Other words used to describe the relationship between elements should be interpreted in a like fashion (e.g., “between” versus “directly between”, “adjacent” versus “directly adjacent”, etc.).</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The terminology used herein is for the purpose of describing particular embodiments only and is not intended to be limiting of example embodiments of the invention. As used herein, the singular forms “a”, “an” and “the” are intended to include the plural forms as well, unless the context clearly indicates otherwise. It will be further understood that the terms “comprises”, “comprising,”, “includes” and/or “including”, when used herein, specify the presence of stated features, integers, steps, operations, elements, and/or components, but do not preclude the presence or addition of one or more other features, integers, steps, operations, elements, components, and/or groups thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">It will be understood that when an element or layer is referred to as being “on”, “connected to” or “coupled to” another element or layer, it can be directly on, connected or coupled to the other element or layer or intervening elements or layers may be present. In contrast, when an element is referred to as being “directly on,” “directly connected to” or “directly coupled to” another element or layer, there are no intervening elements or layers present. Like numbers refer to like elements throughout. As used herein, the term “and/or” includes any and all combinations of one or more of the associated listed items.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">It will be understood that, although the terms first, second, third etc. may be used herein to describe various elements, components, regions, layers and/or sections, these elements, components, regions, layers and/or sections should not be limited by these terms. These terms are only used to distinguish one element, component, region, layer or section from another region, layer or section. Thus, a first element, component, region, layer or section discussed below could be termed a second element, component, region, layer or section without departing from the scope of example embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Spatially relative terms, such as “beneath”, “below”, “lower”, “above”, “upper” and the like, may be used herein for ease of description to describe one element or a feature's relationship to another element or feature as illustrated in the FIGS. It will be understood that the spatially relative terms are intended to encompass different orientations of the device in use or operation in addition to the orientation depicted in the FIGS. For example, if the device in the FIGS. is turned over, elements described as “below” or “beneath” other elements or features would then be oriented “above” the other elements or features. Thus, for example, the term “below” can encompass both an orientation which is above as well as below. The device may be otherwise oriented (rotated 90 degrees or viewed or referenced at other orientations) and the spatially relative descriptors used herein should be interpreted accordingly.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">The terminology used herein is for the purpose of describing particular embodiments only and is not intended to be limiting of example embodiments of the invention. As used herein, the singular forms “a”, “an” and “the” are intended to include the plural forms as well, unless the context clearly indicates otherwise. It will be further understood that the terms “comprises,” “comprising,” “includes” and/or “including,” when used in this specification, specify the presence of stated features, integers, steps, operations, elements, and/or components, but do not preclude the presence or addition of one or more other features, integers, steps, operations, elements, components, and/or groups thereof.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Also, the use of the words “compound,” “compounds,” or “compound(s),” refer to either a single compound or to a plurality of compounds. These words are used to denote one or more compounds but may also just indicate a single compound.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Example embodiments of the present invention are described herein with reference to cross-sectional illustrations that are schematic illustrations of idealized embodiments (and intermediate structures). As such, variations from the shapes of the illustrations as a result, for example, of manufacturing techniques and/or tolerances, may be expected. Thus, example embodiments of the invention should not be construed as limited to the particular shapes of regions illustrated herein but may include deviations in shapes that result, for example, from manufacturing. For example, an implanted region illustrated as a rectangle may have rounded or curved features and/or a gradient (e.g., of implant concentration) at its edges rather than an abrupt change from an implanted region to a non-implanted region. Likewise, a buried region formed by implantation may result in some implantation in the region between the buried region and the surface through which the implantation may take place. Thus, the regions illustrated in the figures are schematic in nature and their shapes do not necessarily illustrate the actual shape of a region of a device and do not limit the scope of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">It should also be noted that in some alternative implementations, the functions/acts noted may occur out of the order noted in the FIGS. For example, two FIGS. shown in succession may in fact be executed substantially concurrently or may sometimes be executed in the reverse order, depending upon the functionality/acts involved.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Unless otherwise defined, all terms (including technical and scientific terms) used herein have the same meaning as commonly understood by one of ordinary skill in the art to which example embodiments of the present invention belong. It will be further understood that terms, such as those defined in commonly used dictionaries, should be interpreted as having a meaning that is consistent with their meaning in the context of the relevant art and will not be interpreted in an idealized or overly formal sense unless expressly so defined herein.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">In order to more specifically describe example embodiments of the present invention, various aspects of the present invention will be described in detail with reference to the attached drawings. However, the present invention is not limited to the example embodiments described. In the figures, if a layer is formed on another layer or a substrate, it means that the layer is directly formed on another layer or a substrate, or that a third layer is interposed therebetween. In the following description, the same reference numerals denote the same elements.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view illustrating a silicon nanowire substrate according to an example embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a silicon nanowire substrate according to an example embodiment of the present invention may include a substrate <b>10</b>, an insulating film <b>22</b> formed in a strip shape on the substrate <b>10</b>, and/or a silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> covering the insulating film <b>22</b>. In an example embodiment, the substrate <b>10</b> may be an oxidized Si substrate and the oxidized Si substrate <b>10</b> may include a Si wafer <b>10</b><i>a </i>and a SiO<sub>2 </sub>layer <b>10</b><i>b </i>formed on the Si wafer <b>10</b><i>a</i>. The insulating film <b>22</b> may be formed of SiN or SiO<sub>2</sub>, and the silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> may be single crystalline. In an example embodiment, the SiN insulating film <b>22</b> has high interface contact with the silicon nanowire film <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In an example embodiment, the insulating film <b>22</b> and the silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> have the same line-width of 30 nm or less. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> has a length of 100-10000 nm.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">In an example embodiment, the substrate <b>10</b> may be formed of at least one material selected from the group consisting of silicon, oxidized silicon, quartz, glass, sapphire, and plastic.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire substrate having the above structure may readily provide a silicon nanowire film having a line-width of 30 nm or less, beyond the conventional lithographic resolution limit. In an example embodiment, the location of the silicon nanowire film on the substrate <b>10</b> may be readily controlled, and the silicon nanowire film can be used for a channel of a thin film transistor. In an example embodiment, a single crystalline silicon nanowire film has a smaller parasitic capacitance and/or a higher carrier mobility. Accordingly, a single crystalline silicon nanowire film may be used as a transistor channel of a next generation transistor having improved device characteristics.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view illustrating a silicon nanowire substrate according to another example embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a silicon nanowire substrate according to another example embodiment of the present invention may include a single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b>, an insulating film <b>28</b> formed in a strip shape on the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b>, a silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> which may be epitaxially grown on the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b> and contacts an end part of the insulating film <b>28</b>, and/or a silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> that may cover the insulating film <b>28</b> and has an extension part which contacts the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b>. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> is laterally crystallized from the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b>. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> may be single crystalline.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In an example embodiment, the insulating film <b>28</b> may be formed of SiN or SiO<sub>2</sub>. In an example embodiment, the insulating film <b>28</b> may include a SiO<sub>2 </sub>film <b>24</b> and a SiN film <b>26</b> sequentially formed on the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b>. In an example embodiment, the SiN film <b>26</b> has high interface contact with the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In an example embodiment, the insulating film <b>28</b> and the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> have the same line-width of 30 nm or less. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> has a length of 100 to 10000 nm.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In the silicon nanowire substrate having the above structure, the crystalline direction of the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> epitaxially grown from the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b> may be determined according to the crystalline direction of the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b>, and the crystalline direction of the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> laterally crystallized from the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> may be determined according to the crystalline direction of the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b>. That is, the crystalline direction of the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> may be controlled by controlling the crystalline direction of the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b>, and the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> can be provided with various characteristics depending on the crystalline direction.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A through 3G</figref> are perspective views for explaining a method of manufacturing a silicon nanowire substrate according to an example embodiment of the present invention. In example embodiment of the present invention, a thin film may be manufactured using methods well known in the art, for example, CVD, PVD, or MOCVD.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, the substrate <b>10</b> may be prepared. The substrate <b>10</b> may be formed of at least one material selected from the group consisting of silicon, oxidized silicon, quartz, glass, sapphire, and plastic. For example, the substrate <b>10</b> may be an oxidized Si substrate, and as depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, may include a Si wafer <b>10</b><i>a </i>and a SiO<sub>2 </sub>layer <b>10</b><i>b </i>formed on the Si wafer <b>10</b><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3B and 3C</figref>, an insulating film <b>21</b> and a silicon film <b>33</b> may be sequentially formed on the substrate <b>10</b>. The insulating film <b>21</b> may be formed of SiN or SiO<sub>2</sub>, and the silicon film <b>33</b> may be formed of poly crystalline silicon, poly-Si or amorphous silicon, a-Si. In an example embodiment, the insulating film <b>21</b> may be formed of SiN because SiN has high interface contact with the silicon film <b>33</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3D</figref>, the insulating film <b>21</b> and the silicon film <b>33</b> may be patterned into a strip shape having the same line-width in the range of 20 to 300 nm. In an example embodiment, the insulating film <b>21</b> and the silicon film <b>33</b> may have the same length, in the range of 100 to 10000 nm. In an example embodiment, the patterning may be performed by reactive ion etching.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3E</figref>, the line-width of the patterned insulating film <b>21</b><i>a </i>may be reduced by undercut etching both sides of the insulating film <b>21</b><i>a</i>. In an example embodiment, the lateral etching of the insulating film <b>21</b><i>a </i>may be performed by isotropic dry etching.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3F and 3G</figref>, the silicon film <b>33</b><i>a </i>may be melted by laser annealing. In an example embodiment, the surface energy of the melted silicon film <b>33</b><i>a </i>may be reduced by melting the silicon film <b>33</b><i>a</i>, so that the surface width of the melted silicon film <b>33</b><i>a </i>is reduced to the width of the insulating film <b>22</b> thereunder; however, the thickness of the silicon film <b>33</b><i>a </i>increases according to the volume conservation rule. By the same principle, the melted silicon film <b>33</b><i>a </i>may crystallize by self-aligning on the upper surface of the etched insulating film <b>22</b>. Accordingly, a fine silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> can be obtained on the upper surface of the insulating film <b>22</b>. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> obtained in this manner may be narrower than a silicon nanowire film patterned by conventional lithography.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">In an example embodiment, the line-width of the silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> self aligned on the upper surface of the insulating film <b>22</b> may be finely controlled by finely controlling the line-width of the insulating film <b>22</b>. In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> may be formed with a line-width of 30 nm or less. In an example embodiment, when the nucleation rate of crystallizing silicon is controlled to 1 event/μs or less, the silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> may be single crystalline silicon. Accordingly, the single crystalline silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> may be used for a channel of a next generation transistor having improved device characteristics.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The nucleation rate will now be described in more detail. Generally, the nucleation rate of one mole of silicon is 1011 event/ns. If the volume of the silicon nanowire film is 30 nm (width)×30 nm (thickness)×1000 nm (length)=9×10<sup>−22 </sup>m<sup>3</sup>, this corresponds to 7.5×10<sup>−15 </sup>moles. Accordingly, the nucleation rate is 7.5×10<sup>−15 </sup>moles×1011 event/ns, which is equivalent to 1 event/μs. Accordingly, a single crystalline silicon nanowire film may be formed by controlling the nucleation rate of the crystallizing silicon to 1 event/μs.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire substrate having the above structure may provide a silicon nanowire film having a line-width of 30 nm or less, beyond the conventional lithographic resolution limit. In an example embodiment, the method of manufacturing the silicon nanowire film is simpler and the location of the silicon nanowire film on the substrate <b>10</b> may be readily controlled.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A through 4J</figref> are perspective views for explaining a method of manufacturing a silicon nanowire substrate according to another embodiment of the present invention. In these processes, the thin film can be manufactured using methods well known in the art, such as CVD, PVD, or MOCVD.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref>, after a single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b> is prepared, an insulating film <b>27</b> may be formed on the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b>. The insulating film <b>27</b> may be formed of SiN or SiO<sub>2</sub>. In an example embodiment, the insulating film <b>27</b> may be formed by sequentially forming a SiO<sub>2 </sub>film <b>23</b> and a SiN film <b>25</b> on the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b>. In an example embodiment, SiN has high interface contact with the silicon film.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4C and 4D</figref>, a portion of the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b> is exposed by etching a region of the insulating film <b>27</b>. In an example embodiment, this process may be performed by reactive ion etching. Afterward, a silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> may be formed on the exposed surface of the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b> by epitaxially growing silicon. In an example embodiment, the crystalline direction of the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> epitaxially grown may vary according to the crystalline direction of the single crystalline silicon substrate <b>20</b>, and the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> may be formed to the same height as the etched insulating film <b>27</b><i>a. </i></p>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4E and 4F</figref>, a silicon film <b>35</b> may be formed on the insulating film <b>27</b><i>a </i>and the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b>. In an example embodiment, the insulating film <b>27</b><i>a </i>and the silicon film <b>35</b> stacked on the insulating film <b>27</b><i>a </i>may be patterned into a strip shape. In an example embodiment, one end of the patterned insulating film <b>27</b><i>b </i>may contact the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The insulating film <b>27</b><i>b </i>and the silicon film <b>35</b><i>a </i>stacked on the insulating film <b>27</b><i>b </i>may be patterned to have the same line-width in the range of 20 to 300 nm and/or the same length in the range of 100 to 10000 nm. The patterning can be performed by reactive ion etching.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4G</figref>, the line-width of the patterned insulating film <b>27</b><i>b </i>may be reduced by undercut etching both sides of the insulating film <b>27</b><i>b</i>. The lateral etching of the insulating film <b>27</b><i>b </i>may be performed by isotropic dry etching.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4H and 4J</figref>, a silicon film <b>35</b><i>a </i>formed on the laterally etched insulating film <b>28</b> and the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> may be melted by laser annealing.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">The surface energy of the melted silicon film <b>35</b><i>a </i>may be reduced by melting the silicon film <b>35</b><i>a</i>, because the surface width of the melted silicon film <b>35</b><i>a </i>is reduced to the width of the insulating film <b>28</b> thereunder; however, the thickness of the silicon film <b>35</b><i>a </i>increases according to the volume conservation rule. By the same principle, the melted silicon film <b>35</b><i>a </i>may crystallize while self-aligning on the upper surface of the etched insulating film <b>28</b>. In an example embodiment, the melted silicon film <b>35</b><i>a </i>crystallizes from laterals, and a single crystalline silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> may be formed on the upper surface of the insulating film <b>28</b>. In an example embodiment, in this process, the crystalline direction of the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> may be controlled by controlling the crystalline direction of the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b>, and the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> may be provided various physical properties depending on the crystalline direction. Also, the crystalline direction of the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> may be readily controlled according to the crystalline direction of the selected single crystalline silicon substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">In an example embodiment, the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> can be formed to have a line-width of 30 nm or less. In an example embodiment, when the nucleation rate of the crystallizing silicon is controlled to 1 event/μs or less, the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> may be formed into single crystalline silicon. Accordingly, the single crystalline silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> may be used for a channel of a next generation transistor having improved device characteristics.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">The silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> obtained by the above method according to example embodiments of the present embodiment may be narrower than a silicon nanowire film patterned by conventional lithography. In example embodiments of the present invention, the line-width of the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> self-aligned on the upper surface of the insulating film <b>28</b> may be controlled by controlling the line-width of the insulating film <b>28</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5A through 5E</figref> are perspective views for explaining an example method of manufacturing a thin film transistor using the silicon nanowire substrate manufactured by the processes depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A through 3G</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5A</figref>, a silicon nanowire substrate may be manufactured by the processes depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A through 3G</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5B</figref>, a source <b>34</b>S, a drain <b>34</b>D, and a channel region <b>34</b>C may be defined on a silicon nanowire film <b>34</b> formed on the substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5C</figref>, a gate insulating film <b>41</b> and a gate electrode <b>42</b> may be sequentially formed on the channel region <b>34</b>C. In an example embodiment, the gate insulating film <b>41</b> may be formed of SiO<sub>2 </sub>or HfO<sub>2</sub>. In an example embodiment, the gate electrode <b>42</b> may be formed of a metal, for example, Al or Cr.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 5D and 5E</figref>, a conductive dopant may be added to the source <b>34</b>S and the drain <b>34</b>D regions, to produce a thin film transistor that uses the silicon nanowire substrate according to an example embodiment of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6A through 6E</figref> are perspective views for explaining an example method of manufacturing a thin film transistor using the silicon nanowire substrate manufactured by the processes depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A through 4J</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6A</figref>, a silicon nanowire substrate may be manufactured by the process depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A through 4J</figref>. A silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> formed on the substrate may be cut to the desired size. For example, the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> side may be cut and removed because the silicon crystal seed <b>29</b> is not needed for forming a thin film transistor.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6B</figref>, a source <b>36</b>S, a drain <b>36</b>D, and a channel region <b>36</b>C may be defined on the silicon nanowire film <b>36</b> formed on the substrate.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6C</figref>, a gate insulating film <b>41</b> and a gate electrode <b>42</b> may be sequentially formed on the channel region <b>36</b>C. In an example embodiment, the gate insulating film <b>41</b> may be formed of SiO<sub>2 </sub>or HfO<sub>2</sub>. In an example embodiment, the gate electrode <b>42</b> may be formed of a metal, for example, Al or Cr.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6D and 6E</figref>, a conductive dopant may be added to the source <b>36</b>S and the drain <b>36</b>D regions, to produce a thin film transistor that uses the silicon nanowire substrate according to example embodiments of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">According to example embodiments of the present invention, a silicon nanowire substrate having the above structure may provide a silicon nanowire film having a line-width of 30 nm or less, beyond the conventional lithographic resolution limit. The example processes for manufacturing the silicon nanowire film are simpler and the location of the silicon nanowire film on the substrate can be readily controlled. In example embodiments, the silicon nanowire film may be formed of single crystalline silicon by controlling the nucleation rate of the crystallizing silicon. A single crystalline silicon nanowire film has a smaller parasitic capacitance and/or higher carrier mobility. Accordingly, a single crystalline silicon nanowire film may be used as a transistor channel of a next generation transistor having improved device characteristics.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">While the present invention has been particularly shown and described with reference to example embodiments thereof, it will be understood by those of ordinary skill in the art that various changes in form and detail may be made therein without departing from the spirit and scope of the present invention as defined by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A method of manufacturing a silicon nanowire substrate, comprising:
<claim-text>preparing a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming an insulating film on the substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a silicon film on the insulating film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>patterning the insulating film and the silicon film into a strip shape;</claim-text>
<claim-text>reducing the line-width of the insulating film by undercut etching at least one lateral side of the insulating film; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a self-aligned silicon nanowire film on an upper surface of the insulating film by melting and crystallizing the silicon film.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the patterning of the insulating film comprises patterning the insulating film and the silicon film to a line-width in the range of 20 to 300 nm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the insulating film and the silicon film are patterned to the same line-width.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the patterning of the insulating film and the silicon film is performed by reactive ion etching.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the substrate is formed of one material selected from the group consisting of silicon, oxidized silicon, quartz, glass, sapphire, and plastic.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the insulating film is formed of one selected from SiN or SiO<sub>2</sub>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the lateral etching of the insulating film is performed by isotropic dry etching.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the silicon film is melted by laser annealing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein in crystallizing the silicon film, the nucleation rate of crystallizing silicon is 1 event/μs or less.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the line-width of the silicon nanowire film self-aligned on the insulating film is controlled by controlling the line-width of the insulating film.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the silicon nanowire film has a line-width of 30 nm or less.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the silicon nanowire film has a length in the range of 100 to 10000 nm.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the silicon nanowire film is single crystalline silicon.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein
<claim-text>the substrate is a single crystalline silicon substrate and the insulating film is formed on the single crystalline silicon substrate, the method further comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>exposing the single crystalline silicon substrate by etching a region of the insulating film;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a silicon crystal seed on the exposed surface of the single crystalline silicon substrate by epitaxially growing silicon;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein</claim-text>
<claim-text>the silicon film is formed on the upper surface of the insulating film and the silicon crystal seed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the insulating film and the silicon film are patterned formed on the insulating film into a strip shape of which one end part contacts the silicon crystal seed, the method further comprising:</claim-text>
<claim-text>melting the silicon film formed on the upper surface of the insulating film and the silicon crystal seed;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the self-aligned silicon nanowire film is formed on the upper surface of the insulating film by laterally crystallizing the silicon film from the silicon crystal seed.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the exposing of the single crystalline silicon substrate by etching a region of the insulating film is performed by reactive ion etching.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The method of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein the insulating film comprises a SiO<sub>2 </sub>film and a SiN film sequentially stacked on the single crystalline silicon substrate.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
