<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297605-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297605</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10842308</doc-number>
<date>20040510</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>193</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>336</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>L</subclass>
<main-group>21</main-group>
<subgroup>425</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438299</main-classification>
<further-classification>438514</further-classification>
<further-classification>257E21598</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Source/drain extension implant process for use with short time anneals</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5486712</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Arima</name>
<date>19960100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>257296</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6187643</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Borland</name>
<date>20010200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6297098</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>Lin et al.</name>
<date>20011000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438264</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2004/0137687</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Feudel et al.</name>
<date>20040700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>438302</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>13</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438197</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438299</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438301</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438302</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438303</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438305</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438306</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438514</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438525</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>438527</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21598</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21619</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E2162</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21634</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>257E21668</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>5</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>9</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050250288</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051110</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Jain</last-name>
<first-name>Amitabh</first-name>
<address>
<city>Allen</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Pollack</last-name>
<first-name>Gordon</first-name>
<address>
<city>Richardson</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Keagy</last-name>
<first-name>Rose Alyssa</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Brady</last-name>
<first-name>W. James</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="03" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Telecky, Jr.</last-name>
<first-name>Frederick J.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Texas Instruments Incorporated</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Dallas</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Geyer</last-name>
<first-name>Scott B.</first-name>
<department>2812</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention provides, in one embodiment, a process for fabricating a metal oxide semiconductor (MOS) device (<b>100</b>). The process includes forming a gate (<b>120</b>) on a substrate (<b>105</b>) and forming a source/drain extension (<b>160</b>) in the substrate (<b>105</b>). Forming the source/drain extension (<b>160</b>) comprises an abnormal-angled dopant implantation (<b>135</b>) and a dopant implantation (<b>145</b>). The abnormal-angled dopant implantation (<b>135</b>) uses a first acceleration energy and tilt angle of greater than about zero degrees. The dopant implantation (<b>145</b>) uses a second acceleration energy that is higher than the first acceleration energy. The process also includes performing an ultrahigh high temperature anneal of the substrate (<b>105</b>), wherein a portion (<b>170</b>) of the source/drain extension (<b>160</b>) is under the gate (<b>120</b>).</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="216.83mm" wi="309.88mm" file="US07297605-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="264.84mm" wi="154.86mm" file="US07297605-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="241.47mm" wi="164.00mm" file="US07297605-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="234.44mm" wi="178.14mm" file="US07297605-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="248.24mm" wi="113.03mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297605-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="254.34mm" wi="151.13mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297605-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention is directed in general to the manufacture of a semiconductor device and, more specifically, to the fabrication of a source/drain extension.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">There is a continuing push to produce smaller semiconductor devices with lower power consumption and faster switching speeds. With device miniaturization, however, comes a number of new design problems. In particular, as new technologies are implemented to produce smaller device components, there is a need to retain compatibility with other components still being produced by older technologies.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">For instance, consider the efforts to scale-down a metal oxide semiconductor (MOS) device. Scaling down the gate length, in addition to increasing device packing density, also facilitates the use of lower voltages and the faster operation of a field effect transistor (FET). Scaling down the gate, however, tends to increase the transistor's leakage current in the off-state. One approach to reduce the leakage current is to form a shallow source/drain extension immediately next to the gate and near the substrate's surface and the channel region. The source/drain extensions, as well understood by those skilled in the art, act as extensions of the more heavily doped source and drain region. The source/drain extensions are also widely referred to as shallow junctions or lightly doped drains (LDD).</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Unfortunately, a conventionally-formed, and therefore conventionally-sized source/drain extension, used with a scaled-down gate does not necessarily cure the leakage current problem. A conventionally-sized drain extension can undesirably generate an electrical field that is sufficient to lower the gate threshold voltage and cause drain-induced barrier lowering (DIBL). The gate threshold voltage is reduced because the electric field from the drain penetrates into the channel and acts oppositely to the gate's electric field. DIBL occurs when the electric field from the drain reaches the source, thereby lowering the energy barrier to inject carriers into the channel.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Consequently, it is necessary to also scale-down the source/drain extension to reduce the strength of the electric field generated by the drain. Moreover, it is important to be able to scale down the dimensions of the source/drain extension in proportion to the degree of reduction in gate length. Source/drain extension can be scaled-down by using low dopant implant energies in combination with rapid or spike thermal annealing. The use of increasingly shorter thermal anneal times to provide smaller source/drain dimensions as devices are continuously scaled down, has been problematic, however.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">As the duration of the annealing time is reduced, the dopant of the source/drain extension diffuses substantially shorter distances. This advantageously minimizes the depth of the source/drain extension in the substrate and produces extensions having a well-defined border, as exemplified by an abrupt decrease in dopant concentration in transitioning from the extension to substrate. An abrupt border is desirable as this supports the low-voltage operation of transistor devices and better defines the width of the channel region. Unfortunately, short anneal times also limit the extent to which implanted dopants of the source/drain extension diffuse under the gate.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It is desirable to form the source/drain extension such that it overlaps with the gate because this facilitates the electric field generated by the gate to cause majority carriers to accumulate in the border of the source/drain extension. The accumulation of majority carriers, in turn, helps mitigate the increased resistance associated with lower dopant concentrations in the border of the extension. High resistance in the border of the source/drain extension is undesirable because this reduces the transistor's on-state current.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Therefore there is need for an improved method to manufacture scaled-down source/drain extensions in semiconductor devices that avoid the above-mentioned limitations.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">To address the above-discussed deficiencies of the prior art, the present invention provides a process for fabricating a metal oxide semiconductor (MOS) device. The process includes forming a gate on a substrate and forming a source/drain extension in the substrate. Forming the source/drain extension includes an abnormal-angled dopant implantation process, using a first acceleration energy and tilt angle of greater than about zero degrees. There is also a dopant implantation using a second acceleration energy that is higher than the first acceleration energy. In addition, an ultrahigh high temperature anneal of the substrate is performed, wherein a portion of the source/drain extension is under the gate.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">In another embodiment, the present invention provides a MOS device. The MOS device comprises a substrate having a top surface, a gate structure on the top surface and a source/drain extension in the silicon substrate. A portion of the source/drain extension is under the gate. The source/drain extension has a border at a depth of less than about 25 nanometers from the top surface of the substrate. The border is defined to occur when there is a decrease in dopant concentration, corresponding to an abruptness of less than about 30 Angstroms/decade.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Yet another embodiment of the present invention is a method of manufacturing an integrated circuit. The method includes forming MOS transistors using the above-described process. The method further includes interconnecting metal lines on one of more insulating layers located over the MOS transistors and interconnecting the MOS transistors to form an operative integrated circuit.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The foregoing has outlined preferred and alternative features of the present invention so that those of ordinary skill in the art may better understand the detailed description of the invention that follows. Additional features of the invention will be described hereinafter that form the subject of the claims of the invention. Those skilled in the art should appreciate that they can readily use the disclosed conception and specific embodiment as a basis for designing or modifying other structures for carrying out the same purposes of the present invention. Those skilled in the art should also realize that such equivalent constructions do not depart from the scope of the invention.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The invention is best understood from the following detailed description when read with the accompanying FIGUREs. It is emphasized that in accordance with the standard practice in the semiconductor industry, various features may not be drawn to scale. In fact, the dimensions of the various features may be arbitrarily increased or reduced for clarity of discussion. Reference is now made to the following descriptions taken in conjunction with the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A to 1F</figref> illustrate sectional views of selected steps in a process for fabricating a metal oxide semiconductor (MOS) device according to the principles of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> illustrates a sectional view of an exemplary metal oxide semiconductor (MOS) device of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> illustrate sectional views of selected steps in a method of manufacturing integrated circuit according to the principles of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The present invention benefits from an extensive series of investigations directed to the engineering of source/drain extensions having shallow depths. The examination of simulated dopant profiles, generated for various combinations of implantation energies and implantation tilt angles, lead to the realization of the multi-step implantation process of the present invention. The use of a multi-step implantation process of the present invention affords the necessary degrees of freedom to fabricate source/drain extensions having shallow depths and abrupt borders while still overlapping the gate. Moreover, this process can be modified so as to continuously adjust the dimensions of the source/drain extension as other components of the semiconductor device are scaled down.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">One embodiment of the present invention is presented in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A to 1F</figref>, which illustrate sectional views of selected steps, at various stages of manufacture, of a process for fabricating a MOS semiconductor device <b>100</b> according to the principles of the present invention. Turning first to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>, depicted is a partial sectional view of a conventionally formed semiconductor substrate <b>105</b> that has a top surface <b>107</b>. The substrate <b>105</b> can be made of conventional materials, such as silicon. A doped well <b>110</b> can be formed in the substrate to form a p-type or n-type well. For example, an n-type well <b>110</b> is preferably a silicon substrate <b>105</b> doped with an n-type dopant, such as arsenic (As<sup>+</sup>) or phosphorus (P<sup>+</sup>) using conventional procedures. A p-type well <b>110</b> is preferably a silicon substrate doped with a p-type dopant like boron (B<sup>+</sup>). Also shown are conventionally-formed shallow trench isolation structures <b>115</b>, which serve to electrically isolate the MOS device <b>100</b> from other adjacent devices formed in the substrate <b>105</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Turning now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>, illustrated is the MOS device <b>100</b> after forming a gate <b>120</b> structure on the substrate <b>105</b>, using conventional materials, deposition and photolithography techniques. The gate <b>120</b> preferably includes a gate insulating layer <b>122</b> and gate electrode <b>124</b>. In some embodiments, the insulating layer <b>122</b> comprises a dielectric material, such as silicon dioxide. Suitable materials for the gate electrode <b>124</b> include doped polysilicon, metal, or combinations thereof. The shallow trench isolation structure <b>115</b> and gate <b>120</b>, by acting as masks, can advantageously define portions of the substrate <b>105</b> or well <b>110</b> to be exposed to dopants during the formation of the source/drain extension, as further discussed below.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">As also illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>, in some cases, it is desirable to deposit an optional thin conformal dielectric layer <b>125</b>, over the substrate <b>105</b> and gate <b>120</b> before forming source/drain extensions. Thus, a portion <b>127</b> of the dielectric layer <b>125</b> is on one or more sidewalls <b>130</b> of the gate <b>120</b>. Preferably, the conformal dielectric layer <b>125</b> is an oxide layer having a thickness <b>132</b> of less than about 100 Angstroms, and more preferably less than about 10 Angstroms.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1C and 1D</figref> depict an exemplary multi-step implantation process of the present invention used in forming source/drain extensions. For clarity, the implantations to form a single source/drain extension are shown. It would be apparent to one skilled in the art that pairs of source/drain extensions could be formed simultaneously or sequentially using this process. As illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1C</figref>, one component of forming source/drain extensions involves an abnormal-angled dopant implantation (a beam of dopants represented by arrow <b>135</b>) using a first acceleration energy and tilt angle <b>137</b> of greater than about zero degrees. The term abnormal-angled, refers to the dopant implantation source <b>140</b> being located substantially different from a direction normal to the top surface <b>107</b> of the substrate <b>105</b>. Preferably, the tilt angle <b>137</b> is less than about 20 degrees, because this avoids undesirable shadow mask effects associated with a substrate <b>105</b> densely packed with other device components. Shadow masking occurs when an angled dopant implantation is at least partially blocked by a device component, or partially constructed component, near the MOS device <b>100</b>. Even more preferably, the tilt angle <b>137</b> ranges from between about 10 and about 20 degrees. In some instances, a tilt angle <b>137</b> of between about 10 and about 14 degrees is preferred, because this is conducive to the production of MOS devices <b>100</b> with a higher device packing density on the substrate <b>105</b>. Of course, the abnormal-angled, dopant implantation can be done in a plurality of stages. In some preferred embodiments, for instance, the location of the implantation source <b>140</b> is moved symmetrically around the substrate <b>105</b> with a portion of the implantation done at each location. For example, the implantation source <b>140</b> could be moved to two or four location around the substrate <b>105</b> with one-half or one fourth of the implantation being done at each of the two or four locations, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1D</figref>, another component of forming source/drain extensions involves a dopant implantation (a beam of the dopants being represented by arrows <b>145</b>) using a second acceleration energy that is higher than the first acceleration energy of the dopant implantation <b>145</b>. In some preferred embodiments, the acceleration energy of the abnormal-angled implantation <b>135</b> is less about 3000 eV, and the second acceleration energy is less than about 5000 eV.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Preferably, the dopant implantation <b>145</b> is done at a second tilt angle <b>147</b> that is less than the tilt angle <b>137</b> of the abnormal-angled dopant implantation <b>135</b>. In some instances, for example, the second tilt angle <b>147</b> is about zero degrees. A tilt angle substantially equal to zero degrees can be achieved by situating the dopant implantation <b>145</b> substantially normal (e.g., second tilt angle <b>147</b> less than about ±1 degrees).</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">In some embodiments, the dopant implantation <b>145</b> is done before the abnormal-angled dopant implantation <b>135</b>. More preferably, however, the abnormal-angled dopant implantation <b>135</b> is done before the dopant implantation <b>145</b>. The latter process sequence is advantageous because the abnormal-angled dopant implantation <b>135</b> serves to disorder or amorphize the substrate surface <b>107</b> so that the higher energy dopant implantation <b>145</b> is less prone to result in excessive depths of dopant channeling into the substrate <b>105</b>. Of course, in some cases, it may be desirable to also perform a pre-amorphization implant to amorphize the substrate surface <b>107</b> before forming the source/drain extension structure. As well understood by those skilled in the art, an amorphized surface is one that has lost its crystallinity and become substantially disordered.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">Of course, the choice of dopant and the dose used depend on the type of MOS device <b>100</b> being produced and its intended use. For example, a positive channel metal oxide semiconductor (pMOS) transistor has a source/drain extension comprising p-type dopants such as B<sup>+</sup>. Alternatively, a negative channel metal oxide semiconductor (nMOS) transistor has a source/drain extension comprising n-type dopants such as P<sup>+</sup> or As<sup>+</sup>. Preferably, the abnormal-angled dopant implantation <b>135</b> and dopant implantation <b>145</b> use dopants of the same dopant type. However, the abnormal-angled implantation <b>135</b> and dopant implantation <b>145</b> can have a first and second dopant, respectively, where the second dopant has a different chemical composition than the first dopant. In some embodiments, for instances, the first dopant is P<sup>+</sup> and the second dopant is As<sup>+</sup>. One of ordinary skill in the art would understand the appropriate doses of dopants to use.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Turning now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1E</figref>, illustrated is the partially completed MOS device <b>100</b> after forming sidewall spacers <b>150</b> on the gate sidewall <b>130</b>, and implanting source/drain dopants (represented by arrow <b>155</b>) in the substrate <b>105</b>. The dopant dose and acceleration energy associated with the source/drain implantation <b>155</b> are substantially higher than that used in source/drain extension implantations <b>135</b>, <b>145</b>. For example, implanting the source/drain dopant <b>155</b> includes a conventional dose and acceleration energy of dopants <b>155</b>, and a tilt angle of substantially zero degrees.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">The multi-step source/drain extension implantations <b>135</b>,<b>145</b> are done without the source/drain sidewall spacer <b>150</b> in place. Preferably, therefore, the source/drain dopant implantation <b>155</b> is done subsequent to the source/drain extension dopant implantation <b>135</b>,<b>145</b>. In some cases, however, source/drain dopant implantation <b>155</b> is done before source/drain extension dopant implantation <b>135</b>,<b>145</b>. In such embodiments, the sidewall spacer <b>150</b> is formed, and source/drain dopant implantation <b>155</b> is done as described above. Next, the side wall spacer <b>150</b> is removed and then the above-described source/drain extension dopant implantation <b>135</b>,<b>145</b> is performed. One of ordinary skill in the art would understand how to incorporate alternative conventional processes for forming source/drain extension implantations <b>135</b>,<b>145</b> and source/drain dopant implantation <b>155</b> into the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1F</figref> illustrates the MOS device <b>100</b> after performing an ultrahigh high temperature (UHT) anneal of the substrate <b>105</b> to complete the formation of the source/drain extensions <b>160</b>, and the source/drain structures <b>165</b>. The UHT anneal serves to repair the substrate surface <b>107</b> and diffuse dopants to a limited extent into the substrate <b>105</b>. Thus, the UHT anneal and above-described multi-step implantation process cooperate to result in a portion <b>170</b> of the source/drain extension <b>160</b> being under the gate <b>120</b>. In preferred embodiments, the UHT anneal comprises heating to a temperature of greater than about 1150° C. for a time of less than 1000 ms. More preferably, the UHT anneal comprises heating to a temperature between about 1200° C. and about 1400° C. for a time of less than 100 ms, and more preferably, less than about 5 ms.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Preferably, a single UHT anneal is performed after each of the multi-step implantations <b>135</b>, <b>145</b> for the source/drain extension <b>160</b> and after implanting the dopants <b>155</b> for the source/drain structure <b>165</b>. In other embodiments, however, the UHT anneal is done after forming the source/drain structure <b>165</b>. In the latter case, the source/drain structure <b>165</b> is made by forming the sidewall spacer <b>150</b> and implanting source/drain dopants <b>155</b> substantially as described above, followed by a thermal anneal. The thermal anneal to form the source/drain structure <b>165</b> could be an UHT anneal, similar to that described above. Alternatively, the thermal anneal to form the source/drain structure <b>165</b> could be a rapid thermal anneal or spike anneal, where heating is to a temperature up to about 1100° C. for more than 1 second. After the thermal anneal to form the source/drain structure <b>165</b>, the sidewall spacer <b>150</b> is removed, and the above-described multi-step implantation <b>135</b>, <b>145</b> and UHT anneal is performed to form the source/drain extension <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">The abnormal-angled dopant implantation <b>135</b> and dopant implantation <b>145</b>, in cooperation with the UHT anneal, offer at least two degrees of freedom for source/drain extension engineering. The abnormal-angled dopant implantation <b>135</b> governs chiefly the extent to which the source/drain extension is under the gate. The dopant implantation <b>145</b> governs mainly the depth <b>175</b> of the source/drain extension <b>160</b> in the substrate <b>105</b>. Additional dopant implantation steps can be added to the multi-step implantation process, to add additional degrees of freedom and thereby refine the formation of the source/drain extension <b>160</b>. As an example, forming the source/drain extension <b>160</b> can include third and fourth dopant implantations using acceleration energies and tilt angles that are the same or intermediate between the energies and tilt angles used for the abnormal-angled dopant implantation <b>135</b> and dopant implantation <b>145</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Another embodiment of the present invention is illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a metal oxide semiconductor (MOS) device <b>200</b>. Analogous reference numbers are used to depict similar structure to that presented in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A-1F</figref>. Any of the above-described embodiments of methods can be used to fabricate the MOS device <b>200</b>. In some preferred embodiments, the MOS device <b>200</b> can be a PMOS transistor device or an NMOS transistor device.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">The MOS device <b>200</b> includes a substrate <b>205</b> having a top surface <b>207</b>, a gate structure <b>220</b> on the top surface <b>207</b>, and a source/drain extension <b>260</b> in the silicon substrate <b>205</b>. A portion <b>270</b> of the source/drain extension <b>260</b> is under the gate <b>220</b> and the source/drain extension <b>260</b> has a border <b>275</b> at a depth <b>278</b> of about 25 nanometers or less from the top surface <b>207</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The border <b>275</b> of the source/drain extension <b>260</b> is defined as the location where there is an abrupt change in the concentration of dopants comprising the source/drain extension <b>260</b>. Those skilled in the art are familiar with the term abruptness. Abruptness is defined in terms of a distance interval one must travel through the source/drain extension <b>260</b> to realize a one-decade decrease in the dopant concentration. A common convention is to define the one-decade decrease in dopant concentration for the dopant concentration range of about 1×10<sup>19 </sup>atoms/cm<sup>3 </sup>to about 1×10<sup>18 </sup>atoms/cm<sup>3</sup>. Of course, the one-decade decrease could be defined for a different concentration range of dopant, depending on total dopant concentration in source/drain extension <b>260</b>. For the purposes of the present invention, an abrupt change occurs when the abruptness is less than about 30 Angstroms/decade. More preferably, the abruptness is less than about 15 Angstroms/decade</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">The multi-step implantation process and UHT anneal imparts the source/drain extensions <b>260</b> with several beneficial structural features. For instance, the depth <b>278</b> of the border <b>275</b> can be continuously varied from 25 nanometers to about 1 nanometer. This allows the source/drain extension <b>260</b> to be constructed to suit a wide range of gate lengths <b>280</b> (e.g., lengths <b>280</b> from about 100 nanometers to about 10 nanometers). Moreover, independent of the source/drain extension's depth <b>278</b>, the portion <b>270</b> of the source/drain extension <b>260</b> under the gate structure <b>220</b> can be continuously adjusted to have an overlap <b>285</b> with an outer perimeter <b>290</b> of the gate structure <b>220</b> ranging from about 10 Angstroms to about 70 Angstroms.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">As discussed in the context of the exemplary method presented in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A-1F</figref>, the source/drain extension <b>260</b> can include a first dopant and a second dopant corresponding to the abnormal-angled dopant implantation <b>135</b> and dopant implantation <b>145</b>, respectively. While first and second dopants are of a same dopant type, they can have the same or different chemical compositions. In certain embodiments, a ratio of the first to the second dopant in the <b>270</b> portion the extension <b>260</b> under the gate <b>220</b> is greater than a second ratio of the first to the second dopant in a second portion <b>295</b> of the extension <b>260</b> not under the gate <b>220</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">Of course, preferred embodiments of the MOS device <b>200</b> include a doped well <b>210</b>, source/drain structures <b>265</b> and sidewall spacers <b>250</b>. These structures can be formed as described above, or using other conventional procedures well known to those skilled in the art.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">Another aspect of the present invention is a method of manufacturing an integrated circuit. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> illustrate Sectional views of selected steps, at various stages of manufacture of an exemplary an integrated circuit <b>300</b>. Turning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>, illustrated is a partial completed integrated circuit <b>300</b>, after forming MOS transistors <b>305</b>, <b>310</b>. In some embodiments, the transistors <b>305</b>, <b>310</b> are PMOS and NMOS transistors, respectively, in a complementary metal oxide semiconductor (CMOS) device. The transistors <b>305</b>, <b>310</b> can form part of logic, memory or other conventional circuits <b>300</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Any of the above-described embodiments of the processes for fabricating a MOS device according to the present invention, such as illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A-1F</figref> and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, can be used to form the MOS transistors <b>305</b>, <b>310</b>. For instance, forming the MOS transistors <b>305</b>, <b>310</b> includes forming gate structures <b>315</b> on a substrate <b>320</b> and forming source/drain extensions <b>325</b> in the substrate <b>320</b>. The source/drain extensions <b>325</b> are formed via a multi-step implantation scheme, followed by a UHT anneal substantially as described above. Other transistor components, such as wells <b>330</b>, source/drain structures <b>335</b>, sidewall spacers <b>340</b> and shallow trench isolation structures <b>345</b> can be fabricated using process described above, or by other conventional processes.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The ability to fabricate transistors <b>305</b>, <b>310</b>, and in particular source/drain extensions <b>325</b>, according to the present invention permits a higher packing density of device structures because components of the transistors can be scaled down. It is still desirable, however, to maintain a certain minimum separation between transistors <b>305</b>, <b>310</b> so as to avoid detrimental shadow masks effects, as previously discussed above.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Turning to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>, illustrated is the integrated circuit <b>300</b> after interconnecting metal lines <b>360</b> on one or more insulating layer <b>365</b> located over the MOS transistors <b>305</b>, <b>310</b> and interconnecting the MOS transistors <b>305</b>, <b>310</b> to form an operative integrated circuit <b>300</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Although the present invention has been described in detail, one of ordinary skill in the art should understand that they can make various changes, substitutions and alterations herein without departing from the scope of the invention.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A process for fabricating a metal oxide semiconductor (MOS) device, comprising:
<claim-text>forming a gate on a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a source/drain extension in said substrate comprising:
<claim-text>a first dopant implantation using a first acceleration energy and a first tilt angle of greater than about zero degrees; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second dopant implantation using a second acceleration energy that is higher than said first acceleration energy; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a source/drain in said substrate comprising:
<claim-text>forming a sidewall spacer on a side wall of said gate; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>implanting a source/drain dopant in said substrate with a third dopant implantation.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said first tilt angle is less than 20 degrees.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said second dopant implantation further includes a second tilt angle that is less than said first tilt angle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said second tilt angle is about zero degrees.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said second tilt angle is less than about ±1 degrees from normal.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said first dopant implantation and said second dopant implantation further includes a first and second dopant, respectively, wherein said first and second dopant are a same dopant type.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said first acceleration energy is less than about 3000 eV and said second acceleration energy is less than about 5000 eV.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said step of forming said source/drain is subsequent to said step of forming said source/drain extension.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further includes a preamorphization implant performed before forming said source/drain extension.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further including performing an ultrahigh temperature anneal of said substrate, wherein a portion of said source/drain extension is under said gate and wherein said ultrahigh temperature anneal is performed after said implanting dopants for said source/drain structure.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further including performing an ultrahigh temperature anneal of said substrate, wherein a portion of said source/drain extension is under said gate and wherein said ultrahigh temperature anneal includes a temperature of greater than about 1150° C. for a time of less than 100 ms.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The method as recited in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said forming said source/drain extension further includes additional dopant implantation steps.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. A method of manufacturing an integrated circuit comprising:
<claim-text>forming MOS transistors including:
<claim-text>forming gates on a substrate;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming source/drain extensions in said substrate by a multi-step implantation scheme comprising:
<claim-text>a first dopant implantation using a first acceleration energy and tilt angle of greater than zero degrees; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second dopant implantation using a second acceleration energy that is higher than said first acceleration energy;</claim-text>
<claim-text>forming a sidewall spacer on a side wall of said gates;</claim-text>
<claim-text>implanting a source/drain dopant in said substrate with a third dopant implantation; and</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>performing an ultrahigh high temperature anneal of said substrate,</claim-text>
</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a portion of said source/drain extensions are under each of said gates; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>interconnecting metal lines on one of more insulating layers located over said MOS transistors and interconnecting said MOS transistors to form an operative integrated circuit.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
