<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297008-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297008</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10856709</doc-number>
<date>20040528</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>128</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>R</subclass>
<main-group>13</main-group>
<subgroup>62</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439157</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Cam and lever ejector assembly</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4975073</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Weisman</name>
<date>19901200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7114984</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Shirk et al.</name>
<date>20061000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439157</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7121866</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Testa et al.</name>
<date>20061000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>439347</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2002/0182909</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Stathopoulos et al.</name>
<date>20021200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>9</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439157</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439347</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>439372</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>8</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>10</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<us-provisional-application>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>60475218</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20030530</date>
</document-id>
</us-provisional-application>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040242039</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20041202</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Griffin</last-name>
<first-name>Joseph Dewey</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lake Oswego</city>
<state>OR</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Van Pelt, Yi &amp; James LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Alcatel USA Sourcing, L.P.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Plano</city>
<state>TX</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Nguyen</last-name>
<first-name>Khiem</first-name>
<department>2839</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An ejector assembly for securing a modular assembly in a chassis is disclosed. The ejector assembly comprises a cam rotatably mounted to the modular assembly such that the cam may be rotated about a first axis, the cam having a control member configured to extend into a recess in the chassis when the cam is rotated into a locked position and be retracted from the recess when the cam is rotated into a retracted position; and a lever rotatably mounted to the modular assembly such that the lever may be rotated about a second axis substantially parallel to the first axis, the lever being configured to cause the cam to be rotated about the first axis when a force is applied to the lever to rotate the lever about the second axis, whereby the cam may be rotated into either the locked position or the retracted position by operating the lever.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="136.91mm" wi="343.49mm" file="US07297008-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="267.63mm" wi="182.96mm" file="US07297008-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="283.55mm" wi="160.78mm" file="US07297008-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="217.59mm" wi="171.70mm" file="US07297008-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="255.02mm" wi="195.50mm" file="US07297008-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="257.05mm" wi="125.81mm" file="US07297008-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="250.95mm" wi="188.72mm" file="US07297008-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="201.93mm" wi="189.40mm" file="US07297008-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="242.15mm" wi="198.54mm" file="US07297008-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">CROSS REFERENCE TO RELATED APPLICATIONS</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application claims priority to U.S. Provisional Patent Application No. 60/475,218 entitled Cam and Lever Ejector Assembly filed May 30, 2003, which is incorporated herein by reference for all purposes.</p>
<?RELAPP description="Other Patent Relations" end="tail"?>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates generally to modular assemblies. More specifically, a cam and lever ejector assembly is disclosed.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Modular systems are used in many applications to provide flexibility and facilitate repair, maintenance, and upgrades. In the telecommunications industry, it is common to provide a system chassis or back plane into which one or more modular components, such as printed circuit boards, may be inserted.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">To facilitate the insertion and removal of such modular components, and to enable such components to be locked into place once installed, a variety of locking and ejection devices have been provided. In one approach, an “ejector” lever is provided. In a locked position, a cam portion of the lever arm extends into a detent in the chassis, locking the modular component securely into place. In an unlocked position, the cam portion does not extend into the detent, thereby making it possible to slide the modular component into or out of a position in the chassis.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> shows a frontal view of a chassis <b>100</b> configured to receive a modular component (not shown). The chassis <b>100</b> comprises a frame <b>102</b>, the front of which is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>. The frame <b>102</b> is formed in such a way as to leave an opening <b>104</b> into which a modular component may be inserted. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> shows a top sectional view of the chassis <b>100</b> in the plane indicated by the arrows “A” in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> shows the frame <b>102</b> comprising a left detent <b>106</b> and a right detent <b>108</b>, such as may be provided to receive the cam portion of the ejector lever described above.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> shows a typical prior art modular device <b>200</b>. The modular device <b>200</b> comprises a modular component <b>202</b> having a face plate <b>230</b>, a left ejector lever <b>204</b> attached to a left lever support <b>206</b> in a manner that permits the lever <b>204</b> to be rotated as indicated by the arrow <b>208</b> about an attachment point <b>210</b>. The modular device <b>200</b> further comprises a right ejector lever <b>212</b> attached to a right lever support <b>214</b> in a manner that permits the lever <b>212</b> to be rotated as indicated by the arrow <b>216</b> about an attachment point <b>218</b>. In the position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>, the ejector levers <b>204</b> and <b>212</b> are in an unlocked position and would not impede the insertion or extraction of the modular device <b>200</b> from a chassis, such as the chassis <b>100</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1A and 1B</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> shows the levers <b>204</b> and <b>212</b> after they have been rotated into a locked position. In this locked position, the lever <b>204</b> can be seen to comprise a cam portion <b>220</b> and the lever <b>212</b> to comprise a cam portion <b>222</b>. In one typical configuration, the cam portion <b>220</b> and cam portion <b>222</b> would in the position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> extend into a detent in the chassis frame, such as the detents <b>106</b> and <b>108</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref>. The arrows in FIG. <b>2</b>B show the direction in which the lever arms <b>204</b> and <b>212</b> would be rotated to return them to the unlocked position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">A problem that may arise with the above-described approach to locking a modular component into a chassis or other frame is that the non-cam portion of the ejector lever arm may block access to a portion of the face plate of the modular component when the component has been installed and the lever arm(s) is(are) in the locked position. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref>, for example, in the locked position shown the lever arms <b>204</b> and <b>222</b> block viewing of and access to portions of the face plate <b>230</b> of the modular component <b>202</b>. As such, in the locked position the lever arms may interfere with the viewing of indicator lights or other displays, and may interfere with the removal or insertion of cables or modular subcomponents that the modular component <b>202</b> may be configured to receive, such as the swapping of media daughter access (MDA) modules in a network switch input/output (I/O) module installed in a network switch chassis.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Therefore, there is a need for a way to provide for the locking and ejection of modular components from a chassis that does not result in a lever arm or other structure being in a position that would block viewing of and/or access to the face plate of the modular component.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Various embodiments of the invention are disclosed in the following detailed description and the accompanying drawings.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref> shows a frontal view of a chassis <b>100</b> configured to receive a modular component (not shown).</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1B</figref> shows a top sectional view of the chassis <b>100</b> in the plane indicated by the arrows “A” in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1A</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2A</figref> shows a typical prior art modular device <b>200</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2B</figref> shows the levers <b>204</b> and <b>212</b> after they have been rotated into a locked position.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> shows a cam and lever ejector assembly comprising a cam <b>302</b> and a lever <b>304</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> shows the cam and lever ejector assembly <b>300</b> in the locked position.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> shows a cam and lever ejector assembly <b>400</b> comprising a cam <b>402</b>, a lever <b>404</b>, and an idler gear <b>406</b> interposed between the two.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> shows the lock portion of the cam <b>402</b> extending into the corresponding detent in the chassis <b>420</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> shows an alternative configuration for the cam <b>402</b>, lever <b>404</b>, and idler gear <b>406</b>, which results in a more compact configuration.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows the cam and lever ejector assembly <b>300</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> as employed in one embodiment.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">The invention can be implemented in numerous ways, including as a process, an apparatus, a system, a composition of matter, a computer readable medium such as a computer readable storage medium or a computer network wherein program instructions are sent over optical or electronic communication links. In this specification, these implementations, or any other form that the invention may take, may be referred to as techniques. In general, the order of the steps of disclosed processes may be altered within the scope of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">A detailed description of one or more embodiments of the invention is provided below along with accompanying figures that illustrate the principles of the invention. The invention is described in connection with such embodiments, but the invention is not limited to any embodiment. The scope of the invention is limited only by the claims and the invention encompasses numerous alternatives, modifications and equivalents. Numerous specific details are set forth in the following description in order to provide a thorough understanding of the invention. These details are provided for the purpose of example and the invention may be practiced according to the claims without some or all of these specific details. For the purpose of clarity, technical material that is known in the technical fields related to the invention has not been described in detail so that the invention is not unnecessarily obscured.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">A cam and lever ejector assembly is disclosed. In one embodiment, the lever portion of the ejector assembly has been decoupled from the cam portion of the assembly. In one embodiment, a gear mechanism is used to transmit force from the lever to the cam, in such a way that the lever portion does not block access to the front of the modular component when the ejector assembly is in the installed and locked position.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref> shows a cam and lever ejector assembly comprising a cam <b>302</b> and a lever <b>304</b>. The cam <b>302</b> comprises a toothed portion <b>306</b> that includes a plurality of gear teeth and a control member <b>308</b>. The lever <b>304</b> comprises a toothed portion <b>310</b> configured and positioned to engage the toothed portion <b>306</b> of the cam <b>302</b> as shown. In the position shown, the cam and lever ejector assembly is in the unlocked position, in which the control member <b>308</b> of the cam <b>302</b> is retracted, thereby ensuring that the cam <b>302</b> does not interfere with the insertion or extraction of the component <b>314</b> from a chassis or other frame. In this unlocked position, the lever <b>304</b> is in a position that may block access to a portion of the faceplate <b>312</b> of the component <b>314</b>, but that condition typically would be acceptable for periods during which the component <b>314</b> is being inserted into or extracted from a chassis.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref> shows the cam and lever ejector assembly <b>300</b> in the locked position. The lever <b>304</b> has been rotated about its pivot point <b>307</b>, to the position shown, which has resulted in the cam <b>302</b> being rotated into a locked position by interaction of the toothed portion <b>310</b> of lever <b>304</b> with the toothed portion <b>306</b> of cam <b>302</b>. The pivot point <b>307</b> is fixed in relation to the component <b>314</b> and the lever <b>304</b> is rotatably mounted to the component <b>314</b> (or some structure, such as a tab or extension, affixed to the component <b>314</b>) at that point. Rotation of lever <b>304</b> into the position shown has caused the cam <b>302</b> to be rotated about its pivot point <b>309</b> into the position shown. Like pivot point <b>307</b>, pivot point <b>309</b> is fixed in relation to the component <b>314</b> and is the point at which the cam <b>302</b> is rotatably mounted to the component <b>314</b> (or some structure, such as a tab or extension, affixed to the component <b>314</b>). In this locked position, the control member <b>308</b> of the cam <b>302</b> extends into a detent in the chassis <b>340</b>, thereby preventing the modular component <b>314</b> from being extracted. In the locked position shown, the lever <b>304</b> is in a position that does not block access to the faceplate <b>312</b> of the modular component <b>314</b> (compare <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>), which would permit the viewing of indicators and displays and the swapping of cables or modular subcomponents, as applicable, during times when the modular component <b>314</b> is in the installed and locked position. In one embodiment, the respective toothed portions of the cam <b>302</b> and the lever <b>304</b> are configured to provide a mechanical advantage, thereby enabling the lever <b>304</b> to be shorter than otherwise would be necessary, with the result that the lever <b>304</b> does not extend too far out from the faceplate of the modular component when the modular component is in the installed and locked position, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">While in certain of the embodiments shown and described in detail herein a gear mechanism is used to cause the cam to rotate in response to movement of the lever, other mechanisms for transmitting force generated by rotating the lever <b>304</b> about its pivot to cause the cam <b>302</b> to rotate about its pivot into the locked or retracted position, as applicable, may be used.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref> show a variation on the cam and lever ejector assembly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> in order to reverse the position of the lever in the locked and unlocked positions. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> shows a cam and lever ejector assembly <b>400</b> comprising a cam <b>402</b>, a lever <b>404</b>, and an idler gear <b>406</b> interposed between the two. The toothed portion of the lever <b>404</b> engages the idler gear <b>406</b> at one point, and the toothed portion of the cam <b>402</b> engages the idler gear <b>406</b> at a second point, such that rotation of the lever <b>404</b> in the direction of arrow <b>408</b> causes the idler gear <b>406</b> to rotate in the clockwise direction, which in turn causes the cam <b>402</b> to rotate in the counterclockwise direction. In one embodiment, the position shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4A</figref> corresponds to the unlocked position, in which the lock portion of the cam <b>402</b> does not extend into the corresponding detent in the chassis (compare <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>). In one embodiment, moving the lever <b>402</b> in the direction of arrow <b>408</b> until the lever arm <b>402</b> is aligned with the faceplate of the modular component causes the cam <b>402</b> to be rotated into the locked position, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref> shows the lock portion of the cam <b>402</b> extending into the corresponding detent in the chassis <b>420</b>. While the configuration shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 4A and 4B</figref> results in the lever <b>404</b> blocking at least a portion of the faceplate of the associated modular component when the component is in the installed and locked position, in one embodiment the mechanical advantage provided by the gear mechanism makes it possible to use a shorter lever <b>404</b>, such that less of the face plate is blocked than would have been blocked by using a typical prior art ejector assembly, such as those shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> shows an alternative configuration for the cam <b>402</b>, lever <b>404</b>, and idler gear <b>406</b>, which results in a more compact configuration. The cam and lever assembly <b>400</b> is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4C</figref> in the unlocked position. Rotating lever <b>404</b> in the direction of arrow <b>422</b> would cause the cam <b>402</b> to be rotated counterclockwise into the locked position, similar to that shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows the cam and lever ejector assembly <b>300</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3A and 3B</figref> as employed in one embodiment. A modular assembly <b>500</b> comprises a planar horizontal body portion <b>504</b> and a vertically oriented faceplate <b>502</b>. The faceplate <b>502</b> includes a display <b>506</b>, a variety of cable receptacles <b>508</b>, and a plurality of modular subcomponents <b>510</b>. The left side cam and lever ejector assembly <b>300</b> of the modular assembly <b>500</b>, labeled <b>300</b>L in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> for clarity, is shown in the locked position (compare <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3B</figref>), whereas the right side cam and lever ejector assembly <b>300</b> of the modular assembly <b>500</b>, labeled <b>300</b>R, is shown in the unlocked (cam retracted) position (compare <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3A</figref>). As <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> shows, in the locked position left side ejector assembly <b>300</b>L does not obscure the faceplate <b>502</b> of modular assembly <b>500</b> and, as a result, does not obscure the display <b>506</b>. By contrast, if the right side cam and lever ejector assembly <b>300</b>R were in the locked position in the position as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, instead of the unlocked position, the lever would obscure the rightmost modular subassembly <b>510</b>, possibly preventing, e.g., that modular subassembly from being inserted, extracted, or otherwise serviced or accessed (e.g., by connecting or disconnecting a cable, reading an indicator, etc.) while the modular assembly <b>500</b> is locked in place.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">In one embodiment, use of a cam and lever ejector assembly such as described herein has the further advantage of reducing the risk of harm to the modular component or adjacent structures or individuals due to potentially harmful emissions by reducing the size of the cut out needed in the faceplate of the modular component to accommodate the ejector assembly. In addition, in one embodiment use of a cam and lever ejector assembly such as described herein avoids the need to extend the chassis forward beyond the faceplate of the modular component to allow the cam portion of the assembly to extend into the detent in the chassis without having a large cut out in the faceplate, such as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2A and 2B</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">Although the foregoing embodiments have been described in some detail for purposes of clarity of understanding, the invention is not limited to the details provided. There are many alternative ways of implementing the invention. The disclosed embodiments are illustrative and not restrictive.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An ejector assembly for securing a modular assembly in a chassis, comprising:
<claim-text>a cam rotatably mounted to the modular assembly such that the cam may be rotated about a first axis, the cam having a control member configured to extend into a recess in the chassis when the cam is rotated into a locked position and be retracted from the recess when the cam is rotated into a retracted position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a lever rotatably mounted to the modular assembly such that the lever may be rotated about a second axis substantially parallel to the first axis, the lever being configured to cause the cam to be rotated about the first axis when a force is applied to the lever to rotate the lever about the second axis, whereby the cam may be rotated into either the locked position or the retracted position by operating the lever.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The ejector assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the modular assembly comprises a front face and the cam and lever are configured such that the lever is in a first position substantially perpendicular to the front face when the cam is in the locked position and the lever is in a second position substantially parallel and adjacent to the front face when the cam is in the retracted position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The ejector assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein the cam comprises a first toothed portion having a plurality of cam gear teeth, the lever comprises a second toothed portion having a plurality of lever gear teeth, and the lever and cam are mounted and configured such that the lever gear teeth engage and transmit force to the cam gear teeth when the lever is rotated about the second axis such that when a force is applied to rotate the lever about the second axis in a first rotational direction the cam is rotated about the first axis in the opposite rotational direction.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The ejector assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref> wherein the first toothed portion, the second toothed portion, the cam, and the lever are sized and positioned so as to provide a mechanical advantage that reduces the minimum lever length required for the lever to be able to rotate the cam between the locked and retracted positions by rotating the lever through a desired range of rotation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The ejector assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref> wherein the desired range of rotation is approximately 90 degrees.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The ejector assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref> wherein:
<claim-text>the cam comprises a first toothed portion comprising a plurality of cam gear teeth;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the lever comprises a second toothed portion comprising a plurality of lever gear teeth;</claim-text>
<claim-text>the ejector assembly further comprises an idler gear interposed between the cam and the lever, the idler gear having a plurality of idler gear teeth; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the lever, idler gear, and cam are mounted and configured such that the lever gear teeth engage and transmit force to the idler gear teeth, which in turn engage and transmit force to the cam gear teeth, when the lever is rotated about the second axis such that when a force is applied to rotate the lever about the second axis the cam is rotated about the first axis in the same rotational direction.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The ejector assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the first toothed portion, the second toothed portion, the cam, the idler gear, and the lever are sized and positioned so as to provide a mechanical advantage that reduces the minimum lever length required for the lever to be able to rotate the cam between the locked and retracted positions by rotating the lever through a desired range of rotation.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The ejector assembly of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref> wherein the modular assembly comprises a front face and the cam, idler gear, and lever are configured such that the lever is in a first position substantially perpendicular to the front face when the cam is in the retracted position and the lever is in a second position substantially parallel and adjacent to the front face when the cam is in the locked position.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An ejector assembly for securing a modular assembly in a chassis, comprising:
<claim-text>means rotatably mounted to the modular assembly for locking the modular assembly in place in the chassis when the means for locking is in a locked position and leaving the modular assembly free to be inserted or extracted from the chassis when the means for locking is in an unlocked position; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>means rotatably mounted to the modular assembly for engaging and rotating the means for locking, whereby the means for locking may be rotated into either the locked position or the unlocked position by operating the means for engaging and rotating.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
