<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296680-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296680</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10824453</doc-number>
<date>20040414</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-002071 U</doc-number>
<date>20030415</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>416</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>65</class>
<subclass>D</subclass>
<main-group>81</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206521</main-classification>
<further-classification>206587</further-classification>
<further-classification>206591</further-classification>
<further-classification>206594</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Packing structure and packing member of corrugated cardboard</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2410591</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Turner</name>
<date>19461100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206586</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3838632</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Miyake</name>
<date>19741000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>493276</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5385238</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Lancaster et al.</name>
<date>19950100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206594</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5398808</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Chen et al.</name>
<date>19950300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206320</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5823352</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Mena et al.</name>
<date>19981000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206721</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6675973</doc-number>
<kind>B1</kind>
<name>McDonald et al.</name>
<date>20040100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>206583</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>6-14072</doc-number>
<date>19940200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>6-20279</doc-number>
<date>19940300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>6-44773</doc-number>
<date>19940600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>5</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206521</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206523</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206583</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206586</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206591-594</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>206320</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>7</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>13</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20040206657</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20041021</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yokawa</last-name>
<first-name>Akira</first-name>
<address>
<city>Osaka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Osha Liang LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Funai Electric Co., Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Osaka</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Mohandesi</last-name>
<first-name>Jila M</first-name>
<department>3728</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b> includes a pair of openings <b>25</b> provided in a bottom housing portion <b>21</b>, a pair of spacer portions <b>22</b> formed so that cores of a corrugated-cardboard sheet extend in a direction substantially orthogonal to their longitudinal direction, an attachment supporting portion <b>26</b> having a longitudinal portion which extends in a direction substantially in parallel to the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated-cardboard sheet, a pair of folding portions <b>23</b> which are arranged between the opposite sides of a pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> are folded downward in order to form the pair of openings <b>25</b>, and a tip projecting portion <b>24</b> arranged to be in contact with a projection <b>112</b> of each styrofoam member <b>110. </b></p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="72.73mm" wi="139.19mm" file="US07296680-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="229.62mm" wi="143.59mm" file="US07296680-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="217.09mm" wi="145.29mm" file="US07296680-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="229.87mm" wi="139.45mm" file="US07296680-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="217.42mm" wi="94.83mm" file="US07296680-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="235.71mm" wi="140.38mm" file="US07296680-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="206.59mm" wi="152.40mm" file="US07296680-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="115.57mm" wi="127.93mm" file="US07296680-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates to a packing structure and a packing member made of a corrugated cardboard (hereinafter referred to as a corrugated-cardboard packing member).</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Related Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Conventionally, in a packing structure in which various devices such as electric products and their attachments are packed, a packing member holding a product and its attachment(s) is arranged within a corrugated cardboard box so that they are immovable. A previously known packing member is a packing member made by molding plastic foam such as styrofoam plastic, or a packing member of corrugated cardboard (for example, See JP-UM-A-6-14072, JP-UM-A-6-020279, and JP-UM-A-6-044773).</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The documents JP-UM-A-6-14072, JP-UM-A-6-020279, and JP-UM-A-6-044773 disclose a corrugated cardboard packing member which uses, as a shock absorber, a box-like portion formed by bending one or more corrugated cardboard sheets.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a schematic view of an exemplary conventional packing structure. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, an explanation will be given of a conventional packing structure <b>100</b>. The conventional packing structure <b>100</b>, as seen from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, includes a corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b>, and a pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> and a corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> which serve as packing members arranged within the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b>. The packing member <b>120</b> is arranged between the upper surface of the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> and the upper inner surface of the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b> and holds an attachment <b>160</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a front view of the styrofoam member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a left side view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a top view of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 to 9</figref>, the conventional styrofoam member <b>110</b> includes a concave portion <b>111</b> for holding the side of a product <b>150</b>, projections <b>112</b> and <b>113</b> formed on the upper surface, projections <b>114</b> formed on the rear surface, and curved sides <b>115</b>. The projections <b>112</b> and <b>113</b> formed on the upper surface serve to support the lower surface of the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b>. The projections <b>114</b> formed on the rear surface of the styrofoam member <b>110</b> are located to be in contact with the inner side face of the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a perspective view of the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a perspective view of the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a perspective view for explaining the extending direction of cores of a corrugated cardboard sheet in the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref>, <b>10</b> and <b>11</b>, the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> includes a bottom housing portion <b>121</b>, a pair of spacer portions <b>122</b>, a pair of folding portions <b>123</b> and tip projecting portions <b>124</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">The pair of spacer portions <b>122</b> are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion <b>121</b> in a square shape and arranged to remove the gap between the upper surface of the styrofoam members <b>110</b> and the upper inner surface of the corrugated cardboard box <b>110</b>. The pair of folding portions <b>123</b> are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion <b>121</b> in a direction orthogonal to the direction of extension of the spacer portions <b>122</b>, toward the side opposite to the side where the spacer portions are located. Each of the folding portions <b>123</b> has an arch shape. The inner side faces <b>123</b><i>a </i>of the folding portion <b>123</b> are located to be in contact with the curved sides of the styrofoam members <b>110</b>, respectively. The tip projecting portions <b>124</b> are formed to project outwardly from the spacer portions <b>122</b> in such a manner that the tips of both ends of the sides of forming the spacer portions <b>121</b> are inserted into cutting portions <b>121</b><i>a </i>formed in the bottom housing portion <b>121</b>, respectively. Additionally, the cores <b>120</b><i>a </i>of the corrugated cardboard sheet which constitutes the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> extend in a direction of arrow A illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 11 and 12</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a view showing the arrangement relationship between the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member and the pair of styrofoam members illustrated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 and 13</figref>, in the conventional packing structure <b>100</b>, when shock is applied to the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b>, the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> and corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> were caused to have a shock absorbing function. Specifically, the styrofoam member <b>110</b>, which is elastically deformed to a certain degree when it receives the shock, has the shock absorbing function. The corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> arranged on the conventional styrofoam members <b>110</b> has the function of absorbing the shock through elastic deformation of the square spacer portions <b>122</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">However, the conventional packing structure <b>100</b> has the following inconvenience. Namely, in the conventional packing structure <b>100</b>, since the cores <b>120</b><i>a </i>of the corrugated cardboard sheet constituting the corrugated-cardboard member <b>120</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>) are formed to extend in the direction of arrow A, when force is applied from above to the spacer portions <b>122</b> of the corrugated cardboard member <b>120</b>, the sides <b>122</b><i>a </i>in a vertical direction of the square spacer portions <b>122</b> are likely to be not deformed elastically but bent. When the sides <b>122</b><i>a </i>in the vertical direction of the spacer portions <b>122</b> are bent, a problem occurs that the shock absorbing function of the spacer portions <b>122</b> is deteriorated. Further, the When the sides <b>122</b><i>a </i>in the vertical direction of the spacer portions <b>122</b> are bent, the height of the spacer portions <b>122</b> is reduced so that a space or gap is generated between the upper inner face of the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b> and upper face of the spacer portions <b>122</b>. Therefore, since the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> are likely to move vertically, a problem occurs that the product <b>150</b> falls out from the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> owing to the vertical movement of the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The conventional packing structure <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> has also the following inconvenience. Namely, when the shock in a horizontal direction is applied to the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b>, the end of one of the styrofoam member <b>110</b> is likely to move toward the opposite styrofoam member <b>110</b> (direction of arrow C in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6</figref> and <b>9</b>). Thus, also when the end of one of the styrofoam members <b>110</b> moves in the direction of arrow C, a problem occurs that the product <b>150</b> falls.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Further, the conventional packing structure has also an inconvenience that the bottom housing portion <b>121</b> of the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b>, which is formed of a single corrugated-cardboard sheet, is lack of flexibility. The conventional packing structure also presents a problem that it is difficult to provide the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> with a sufficient shock absorbing function owing to the reduction of the shock absorbing function of the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> due to the bending of the spacer portions <b>122</b> and lack of the flexibility of the bottom housing portion <b>121</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">The conventional packing structure <b>100</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> has also the following inconvenience. When strong shock is applied to the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b> owing to its dropping, great force is applied to the portion where the inner side faces <b>123</b><i>a </i>of the folding portion <b>123</b> of the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> and the sides <b>115</b> of the styrofoam member <b>100</b> are in contact with each other so that excessive pushing force in a direction of arrow B in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 7 to 9</figref> is applied to the sides of the styrofoam member <b>110</b>. Owing to the excessive pushing force in this direction of arrow B, the sides of the styrofoam member <b>110</b> may be damaged as indicated in two-dot chain line in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 8 and 9</figref>. Also when the sides <b>115</b> of the styrofoam member <b>110</b> are damaged, the styrofoam member <b>110</b> is likely to move in a direction of arrow D in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> so that the product <b>150</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) supported by the styrofoam members <b>110</b> falls from the styrofoam members <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Further, in the conventional box-like corrugated-cardboard packing member disclosed in the documents JP-UM-A-6-14072, JP-UM-A-6-020279, and JP-UM-A-6-044773, the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet is not taken into consideration. Therefore, in the case where the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet is longitudinal of the box portion, when force is applied vertically (short-length direction) to the box portion, the box portion may not deformed elastically but bent. In this case, like the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, a problem occurs that the shock absorbing function of the box portion is deteriorated. Further, like the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the corrugated-cardboard packing member disclosed in the documents JP-UM-A-6-14072, JP-UM-A-6-020279, and JP-UM-A-6-044773 have an inconvenience that the bottom housing portion, which is formed of a single corrugated-cardboard sheet, is lack of flexibility. Thus, in the corrugated-cardboard packing member disclosed in the above described documents, it is difficult to provide the bottom housing portion with a sufficient shock absorbing function.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">It is therefore an object of the invention to provide a corrugated cardboard packing member which is given excellent shock resistance by improving a shock absorbing function and a packing structure including the same.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">In order to solve the problems, according to a first aspect of the invention, there is provided a packing structure including: a corrugated-cardboard box for housing a product; a pair of styrofoam members each of which is arranged within the corrugated cardboard box and includes a concave portion for supporting the side of the product; and a corrugated-cardboard packing member arranged to be adjacent to the pair of styrofoam members within the corrugated-cardboard box and includes a bottom housing portion for housing an attachment and a pair of spacer portions which are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion in a square shape and arranged in a gap between the upper surface of the styrofoam members and the inner surface of the corrugated cardboard box, wherein the pair of styrofoam members each includes a projection on the upper surface, wherein the corrugated-cardboard packing member is formed so that cores of a corrugated cardboard sheet extend in a direction orthogonal to the direction of extending the pair of spacer portions, wherein the corrugated-cardboard packing member includes: a pair of openings formed by cutting off two predetermined areas of the bottom housing portion in a three edges of a square, respectively and folding back the remaining area downward; an attachment supporting portion located between the pair of openings and having a longitudinal area extending in a direction substantially in parallel to the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard; a pair of folding portions arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members and folded back downward in order to form said pair of openings; and a tip projecting portion formed in such a manner that the tip of the side of each said spacer portions on the side of bottom housing portion project downward from the spacer portions and arranged to be in contact with said projection of each said styrofoam members, respectively in such a manner that the styrofoam member is sandwiched by the tip projecting portion and each of the folding portions.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">According to a second aspect of the invention, there is provided a corrugated-cardboard packing member arranged to be adjacent to a pair of holding members for holding a first article to be arranged within a corrugated cardboard box, the corrugated-cardboard packing member including: a bottom housing portion for housing a second article; a pair of spacer portions that are provided to project upward from the ends of said bottom housing portion and arranged in a gap between the upper surface of the pair of holding members and the inner surface of the corrugated cardboard box, an opening formed by cutting off a predetermined area of the bottom housing portion and folding back the remaining area downward; a second article supporting portion adjacent to said opening; and a folding portion which is arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of holding members and folded back downward in order to form said opening.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">The above objects and advantages of the present invention will become more apparent by describing a preferred embodiment thereof in detail with reference to the accompanying drawings, wherein:</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic view of a packing structure according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of a corrugated-cardboard packing member which is used in the packing structure shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a plan developed view of the corrugated-cardboard packing member of a according to the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view showing an arrangement relationship between the corrugated-cardboard packing member and a pair of styrofoam members;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a plan view for explaining the positional relationship between the corrugated-cardboard packing member and the upper protruding portions of the pair of styrofoam members, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a schematic view of an exemplary conventional packing member;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a front view of a conventional styrofoam member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a left side view of the conventional styrofoam member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a top view of the conventional styrofoam member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a perspective view of the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a perspective view of the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is a perspective view for explaining the extending direction of cores of a corrugated cardboard sheet in the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a view showing the arrangement relationship between the conventional-cardboard packing member and the pair of conventional styrofoam members shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Referring now to the accompanying drawings, a description will be given in detail of a packing structure according to one or more embodiments of the invention.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic view of a packing structure according to an embodiment of the present invention. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a perspective view of a corrugated-cardboard packing member which is used in the packing structure shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a plan developed view of the corrugated-cardboard packing member of a according to the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a view showing an arrangement relationship between the corrugated-cardboard packing member and a pair of styrofoam members. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a plan view for explaining the positional relationship between the corrugated-cardboard packing member and the upper protruding portions of the pair of styrofoam members, shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a packing structure <b>1</b> includes a corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b>, a pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b>, and a corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b>, which serve as packing members arranged within the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b>. Incidentally, the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b> and the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> have the same configurations as those of the conventional corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b> and pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 6 to 9</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">The corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b> includes a bottom housing portion <b>21</b>, a pair of spacer portions <b>22</b>, a pair of folding portions <b>23</b>, tip projecting portions <b>24</b>, a pair of openings <b>25</b> and an attachment supporting portion <b>26</b>. The bottom housing portion <b>21</b> is provided to house the attachment. The pair of spacer portions <b>22</b> are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion <b>121</b> in a square shape. The pair of openings are formed by cutting off two predetermined areas of the bottom housing portion <b>21</b> in a three edges of a square, respectively and folding back the remaining area downward. The attachment supporting portion <b>26</b> are formed to be located between the pair of openings <b>25</b>. The folding portions <b>23</b> are formed by folding back the above remaining area in order to form the openings <b>25</b> downward. The folding portions <b>23</b>, as seen from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 4</figref>, are arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b>. The tip projecting portions <b>24</b> are formed to project downward from the spacer portions <b>22</b> in such a manner that the tips of both ends of the spacer portions <b>22</b> on the side of bottom housing portion <b>21</b> are inserted into cutting portions <b>21</b><i>a </i>formed in the bottom housing portion <b>21</b>, respectively. The tip projecting portions <b>24</b> are arranged to be in contact with the projecting portions <b>112</b> of the styrofoam members <b>110</b>, respectively in such a manner that the styrofoam members <b>110</b> are sandwiched by the tip projecting portions <b>24</b> and the folding portions <b>23</b> as seen from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">In this embodiment, the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet constituting the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b>, as indicated by arrow A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, is a direction in parallel to the longitudinal direction of the corrugated cardboard sheet of the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b>. Namely, unlike the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>120</b> (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>), the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet constituting the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b> according to this embodiment are formed to extend in a direction (short-length direction) substantially orthogonal to the direction of extending the pair of spacer portions <b>22</b> (longitudinal direction). Therefore, the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet constituting the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b> extend in a vertical direction (direction of arrow A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) in the vertical sides <b>22</b><i>a </i>of the pair of spacer portions <b>22</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">In the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b> according to this embodiment, as described above, the pair of openings <b>25</b> are formed in the bottom housing portion <b>21</b> of the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b> so that the planar area of the bottom housing portion <b>21</b> is reduced, thereby improving the flexibility of the bottom housing portion <b>21</b>. Thus, the bottom housing portion <b>21</b> can have a shock absorbing function. Further, in this embodiment, unlike the conventional corrugated-cardboard packing member, the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet constituting the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b> are formed to extend in a vertical direction (direction of arrow A in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) in the vertical sides <b>22</b><i>a </i>of the pair of spacer portions <b>22</b>. Therefore, when shock is vertically applied to the spacer portions <b>22</b> owing to dropping of the corrugated cardboard box <b>101</b>, the vertical sides <b>22</b><i>a </i>of the spacer portions <b>22</b> of the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b> are difficult to bend in the vertical direction as compared with those of the conventional spacer portions. Thus, when shock is applied to the spacer portions <b>22</b>, these sides are not bent but can be elastically deformed. This improves the shock absorbing function of the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b>. Further, the pair of spacer portions <b>22</b>, which are arranged in a gap between the upper surface of the styrofoam members <b>110</b> and the inner face of the corrugated cardboard box, can be prevented from bending vertically. This prevents a space from being generated between the upper surface of the styrofoam members <b>110</b> and the inner face of the corrugated cardboard box. As a result, the styrofoam members <b>110</b> can be prevented from moving vertically, thus preventing the product <b>150</b> from falling.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">In this embodiment, the folding portions <b>23</b> formed to project downward from the bottom housing portion <b>21</b> are arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b>. Therefore, the end of one of the styrofoam member <b>110</b> is prevented from moving toward the opposite styrofoam member <b>110</b>. Thus, it is possible to prevent the product <b>150</b> from falling from the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> owing to the movement of the end of one of the styrofoam members <b>110</b> toward the opposite styrofoam member <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">In the packing structure according to this embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, when shock in a horizontal direction (direction of arrow C in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) is applied to the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b>, the pushing force due to both folding portions and sides of the product <b>150</b> will be applied to the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b>. This prevents the linear pair of folding portions <b>23</b> from excessively pushing the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b>. Thus, the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> can be prevented from being damaged owing to that the linear pair of folding portions <b>23</b> have excessively pushed the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b>. Accordingly, the product <b>150</b> can be prevented from falling from the pair of styrofoam members <b>110</b> owing to that the styrofoam members <b>110</b> have been damaged.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">In this embodiment, as described above, the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet constituting the corrugated-cardboard packing member <b>20</b> are extended in a direction substantially in parallel to the longitudinal direction of the attachment supporting portion <b>26</b>. Owing to this, the longitudinal area of the attachment supporting portion <b>26</b>, which extends substantially in parallel to the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet, are difficult to bend. Thus, in the case where an attachment <b>160</b> is placed on the attachment supporting portion <b>26</b> which a slender shape, the attachment supporting portion <b>26</b> can be prevented from bending downward.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">In this embodiment, as described above, the tip projecting portions <b>24</b> are arranged to be in contact with the projecting portions <b>112</b> of the styrofoam members <b>110</b>, respectively in such a manner that the styrofoam members <b>110</b> are sandwiched by the tip projecting portions <b>24</b> and the folding portions <b>23</b>. Therefore, in the case where the corrugated cardboard <b>101</b> has fallen, the styrofoam members <b>110</b> can be surely prevented from moving. Accordingly, as compared with the conventional embodiment, the product <b>150</b> can be surely prevented from moving owing to movement of the styrofoam members <b>110</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">Additionally, it should be noted that the embodiment described hitherto is exemplary but not be limited in all the points. The scope of the present invention is defined by the claims but not by the description of the embodiment. The present invention includes all the modifications in a meaning and scope equivalent to those defined by claims.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">For example, in the embodiment described above, the explanation was given of the case where the product is held by the styrofoam members and the attachment is housed by the corrugated-cardboard packing member. However, the present invention should not be limited to such a case. The same effect can be obtained also in the case where other articles are housed by the styrofoam members and the corrugated-cardboard packing member.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">Further, in the embodiment described above, the packing member (holding member) to be combined with the corrugated-cardboard packing member was the styrofoam member. The present invention should not be limited to such a case. The holding member made of the material other than styrofoam may be combined with the corrugated-cardboard packing member.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">Further, in the embodiment described above, two openings are provided in the bottom housing portion of the corrugated-cardboard packing member. The present invention should not be limited to such a case. One or three or more openings may be provided.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">According to a first aspect of the present invention, there is provided a packing structure including: a corrugated-cardboard box for housing a product; a pair of styrofoam members each of which is arranged within the corrugated cardboard box and includes a concave portion for supporting the side of the product; and a corrugated-cardboard packing member arranged to be adjacent to the pair of styrofoam members within the corrugated-cardboard box and includes a bottom housing portion for housing an attachment and a pair of spacer portions which are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion in a square shape and arranged in a gap between the upper surface of the styrofoam members and the inner surface of the corrugated cardboard box, wherein the pair of styrofoam members each includes a projection on the upper surface, wherein the corrugated-cardboard packing member is formed so that cores of a corrugated cardboard sheet extend in a direction orthogonal to the direction of extending the pair of spacer portions, wherein the corrugated-cardboard packing member includes: a pair of openings formed by cutting off two predetermined areas of the bottom housing portion in a three edges of a square, respectively and folding back the remaining area downward; an attachment supporting portion located between the pair of openings and having a longitudinal area extending in a direction substantially in parallel to the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard; a pair of folding portions arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members and folded back downward in order to form said pair of openings; and a tip projecting portion formed in such a manner that the tip of the side of each said spacer portions on the side of bottom housing portion project downward from the spacer portions and arranged to be in contact with said projection of each said styrofoam members, respectively in such a manner that the styrofoam member is sandwiched by the tip projecting portion and each of the folding portions.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">According to the first aspect of the present invention, as described above, since the pair of openings are formed by cutting off two predetermined areas of the bottom housing portion of the corrugated-cardboard packing member, which is arranged to be adjacent to the pair of styrofoam members within the corrugated cardboard box, in a three edges of a square, respectively and folding back the remaining area downward, the planar area of the bottom housing portion of the corrugated-cardboard packing member is reduced as compared with the case where no opening is provided. Correspondingly, the flexibility of the bottom housing portion can be improved. Thus, the bottom housing portion can have a shock absorbing function, thereby providing the packing structure with excellent shock resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">In the packing structure according to the first aspect of the present invention, the pair of folding portions folded back downward in order to form the pair of openings are arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members. Therefore, the end of one of the styrofoam members for housing the product is prevented from moving toward the opposite styrofoam member. Thus, when the corrugated cardboard box drops, it is possible to prevent the product from falling from the pair of styrofoam members owing to the movement of the end of one of the styrofoam members toward the opposite styrofoam member. Further, since the pair of folding portions are arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members where the product is housed, when the end of one of the pair of styrofoam members is about to move toward the opposite side, the pushing force due to both of the pair of folding portions and the product will be applied to the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members. This prevents the linear pair of folding portions from excessively pushing the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members. Thus, the pair of styrofoam members can be prevented from being damaged owing to that the linear pair of folding portions have excessively pushed the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members. Accordingly, the product can be prevented from falling from the pair of styrofoam members owing to that the styrofoam members have been damaged.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">In the packing structure according to the first aspect of the present invention, the corrugated-cardboard packing member is formed so that the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet extend in a direction (short-length direction) substantially orthogonal to the direction of extending the pair of spacer portions (longitudinal direction). Therefore, where the pair of spacer portions are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion in a square shape, the pair of spacer portions are difficult to bend in the short-length direction (vertical direction). Thus, when shock is applied to the spacer portions, these spacer portions are not bent but can be elastically deformed. Correspondingly, the shock absorbing function of the spacer portions can be improved. Further, since the spacer portions are difficult to bend in the short-length direction (vertical direction), when shock is applied to the pair of spacer portions in the short-length direction (vertical direction) owing to drop of the corrugated cardboard box, a space can be prevented from being formed between the upper surface of the styrofoam members <b>110</b> and the inner face of the corrugated cardboard box owing to bending in the short-length direction (vertical direction) of the pair of spacer portions arranged in the gap between the upper surface of the styrofoam members and inner face of the corrugated cardboard box. As a result, the styrofoam members can be prevented from moving vertically, thus preventing the product from falling owing to the vertical movement of the styrofoam members. Further, the attachment supporting portion is provided to have a longitudinal area substantially in parallel to the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard. The longitudinal area of the attachment supporting portion, which extends substantially in parallel to the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet, is difficult to bend. Thus, in the case where an attachment is placed on the attachment supporting portion which a slender shape, the attachment supporting portion can be prevented from bending downward.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In the packing structure according to the first aspect of the present invention, a tip projecting portion is provided in such a manner that the tip of the side of each the spacer portions on the side of bottom housing portion project downward from the spacer portions and arranged to be in contact with the projection of each the styrofoam members, respectively in such a manner that the styrofoam member is sandwiched by the tip projecting portion and each of the folding portions. Therefore, in the case where the corrugated cardboard box has dropped, the styrofoam members can be surely prevented from moving. Accordingly, the product can be surely prevented from falling owing to movement of the styrofoam members.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">According to a second aspect of the invention, there is provided a corrugated-cardboard packing member arranged to be adjacent to a pair of holding members for holding a first article to be arranged within a corrugated cardboard box, the corrugated-cardboard packing member including: a bottom housing portion for housing a second article; a pair of spacer portions that are provided to project upward from the ends of said bottom housing portion and arranged in a gap between the upper surface of the pair of holding members and the inner surface of the corrugated cardboard box, an opening formed by cutting off a predetermined area of the bottom housing portion and folding back the remaining area downward; a second article supporting portion adjacent to said opening; and a folding portion which is arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of holding members and folded back downward in order to form the opening.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">In the corrugated-cardboard packing member according to the second aspect of the present invention, as described above, the opening is provided by cutting off a predetermined area of the bottom housing portion of the corrugated cardboard packing member arranged to be adjacent to the pair of the holding member within the corrugated cardboard box and folding back the remaining area downward. Therefore, the planar area of the bottom housing portion of the corrugated-cardboard packing member is reduced as compared with the case where the no opening is provided. Correspondingly, the flexibility of the bottom housing portion can be improved. Thus, the bottom housing portion can have a shock absorbing function of reducing shock, thereby providing a corrugated-cardboard packing member with excellent shock resistance.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">In the corrugated-cardboard packing member according to the second aspect of the present invention, a folding portion is arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of holding members and folded back downward in order to form the opening. This prevents the end of one of the pair of holding members which hold the product from moving toward the opposite holding member. Therefore, such an inconvenience can be obviated that when the corrugated-cardboard box has dropped, the first article falls from the pair of holding members owing to the movement of the end of one of the pair of holding members to the opposite holding member.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">In the corrugated-cardboard packing member according to the second aspect of the present invention, preferably, the pair of spacer portions are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion in a square shape, and the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet extend in a direction substantially orthogonal to the direction of extending the pair of spacer portions. In such a configuration, the pair of spacer portions become difficult to bend in the short-length direction (vertical direction). Thus, when shock is applied to the spacer portions, these spacer portions are not bent but can be elastically deformed. Correspondingly, the shock absorbing function of the spacer portions can be improved. Further, since the spacer portions are made difficult to bend in the short-length direction (vertical direction), a space can be prevented from being formed between the upper surface of the holding members and the inner face of the corrugated cardboard box owing to bending in the short-length direction (vertical direction) of the pair of spacer portions in the gap between the upper surface of the holding members and inner face of the corrugated cardboard box. As a result, the holding members can be prevented from moving vertically, thus preventing the first article from falling owing to the vertical movement of the holding members.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">In the corrugated-cardboard packing member according to the second aspect of the present invention, preferably, the second article holding portion has a longitudinal area substantially in parallel to the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard. According to such a configuration, the longitudinal portion, which extends substantially in parallel to the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard sheet, is difficult to bend. Thus, in the case where the second article is placed on the attachment supporting portion which a slender shape, the second article supporting portion can be prevented from bending downward.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">In the corrugated-cardboard packing member according to the second aspect of the present invention, it is preferred that the holding member includes a projection on the upper surface; the pair of spacer portions are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion in a square shape; and a tip projecting portion which is formed in such a manner that the tip of the side of each the spacer portions on the side of bottom housing portion project downward from the spacer portions and arranged to be in contact with the projection of each the holding members, respectively in such a manner that the holding member is sandwiched by the tip projecting portion and each of the folding portions. According to such a configuration, when the corrugated cardboard box has dropped, the holding members can be prevented from being moved. This prevents the first article from falling owing to the movement of the holding members.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">Although the present invention has been shown and described with reference to a specific preferred embodiment, various changes and modifications will be apparent to those skilled in the art from the teachings herein. Such changes and modifications as are obvious are deemed to come within the spirit, scope and contemplation of the invention as defined in the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A packing structure comprising:
<claim-text>a corrugated-cardboard box for housing a product;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pair of styrofoam members each of which is arranged within the corrugated cardboard box and includes a concave portion for supporting the side of the product; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a corrugated-cardboard packing member arranged to be adjacent to the pair of styrofoam members within the corrugated-cardboard box and includes a bottom housing portion for housing an attachment and a pair of spacer portions which are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion in a square shape and arranged in a gap between the upper surface of the styrofoam members and the inner surface of the corrugated cardboard box,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the pair of styrofoam members each includes a projection on the upper surface,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the corrugated-cardboard packing member is formed so that cores of a corrugated cardboard sheet extend in a direction orthogonal to the direction of extending the pair of spacer portions,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the corrugated-cardboard packing member includes:
<claim-text>a pair of openings formed by cutting off two predetermined areas of the bottom housing portion in a three edges of a square, respectively and folding back the remaining area downward;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an attachment supporting portion located between the pair of openings and having a longitudinal area extending in a direction substantially in parallel to the direction of extending the cores of the corrugated cardboard;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pair of folding portions arranged between the opposite sides of the pair of styrofoam members and folded back downward in order to form said pair of openings; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a tip projecting portion formed in such a manner that the tip of the side of each said spacer portions on the side of bottom housing portion project downward from the spacer portions and arranged to be in contact with said projection of each said styrofoam members, respectively in such a manner that the styrofoam member is sandwiched by the tip projecting portion and each of the folding portions.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. A corrugated-cardboard packing member adapted to be adjacent to a pair of holding members for holding a first article arranged within a corrugated cardboard box, the corrugated-cardboard packing member comprising:
<claim-text>a bottom housing portion for housing a second article;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a pair of spacer portions, each spacer portion folded upward from a respective end of said bottom housing portion and arranged in a gap between the upper surface of the pair of holding members and the inner surface of the corrugated cardboard box,</claim-text>
<claim-text>an opening formed by cutting a predetermined area from the bottom housing portion and folding the predetermined area downward, forming a folding portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second article supporting portion adjacent to said opening configured to support a second article;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the folding portion is arranged between the pair of holding members,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein each holding member includes a projection on the upper surface,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the pair of spacer portions are formed by bending both ends of the bottom housing portion in a square shape, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein tip projecting portions are formed such that a tip of a side of each spacer portion on a side of bottom housing portion projects downward from each spacer portion and is configured to contact said projection of said holding member, respectively, in such a manner that the holding member is sandwiched by the tip projecting portion and each of the folding portions.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The corrugated-cardboard packing member according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the pair of spacer portions are formed by bending ends of the bottom housing portion in a square shape, and wherein cores of corrugated cardboard of the corrugated-cardboard packing member extend in a direction orthogonal to a direction of extension of said pair of spacer portions.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The corrugated-cardboard packing member according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the second article supporting portion has a longitudinal area extending substantially in parallel to a direction of extension of the cores of said corrugated cardboard.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The corrugated-cardboard packing member according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a second opening formed by cutting a second predetermined area from the bottom housing portion and folding the second predetermined area downward, forming a second folding portion;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the second folding portion is arranged between the pair of holding members.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
