<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298361-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298361</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11004890</doc-number>
<date>20041207</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>576</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>09</class>
<subclass>G</subclass>
<main-group>5</main-group>
<subgroup>00</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345163</main-classification>
<further-classification>345174</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Non-contact electric inductance circuit for power source</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4507622</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Muth</name>
<date>19850300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>331115</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7030626</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Hayashi et al.</name>
<date>20060400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>324635</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7096741</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Schneider</name>
<date>20060800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73765</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7146845</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Raffalt</name>
<date>20061200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 73  183</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0141251</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Allwyn et al.</name>
<date>20050600</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>363 95</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0162228</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Putzeys</name>
<date>20050700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>330251</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2005/0248523</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Yu et al.</name>
<date>20051100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>345102</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>345156-169</main-classification>
<additional-info>unstructured</additional-info>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>31511121</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>31511151</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>21912121</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>333 32</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>330294</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>34082536</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>6</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>6</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060232549</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20061019</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Lin</last-name>
<first-name>Rung-Tsung</first-name>
<address>
<street>4F., No. 9, Alley 9, Lane 188, Sec. 1, Wunhua Rd.</street>
<city>Banciao City, Taipei County 220, Taipei Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Chang</last-name>
<first-name>Ding-Kan</first-name>
<address>
<street>4F., No. 9, Alley 9, Lane 188, Sec. 1, Wunhua Rd.</street>
<city>Banciao City, Taipei County 220, Taipei Hsien</city>
<country>TW</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>TW</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>TW</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Bacon &amp; Thomas, PLLC</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Patel</last-name>
<first-name>Nitin I.</first-name>
<department>2629</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source converts input alternating current into signals with harmonic vibration and of high frequency, a coil of a set of corresponding receiver equipment receives the harmonic vibration of the signals to convert it into electric energy; wherein the entire electric inductance circuit has a driving circuit, a harmonic circuit, a feedback circuit, a micro-processing circuit and an adapted-to-adjusting-frequency oscillating circuit integrated with one another. When in operation, the alternating electric current passes to the harmonic circuit after being amplified through the driving circuit, and the feedback circuit transmits the voltage or current of the harmonic circuit to the micro-processing circuit that analyses the value of the voltage or current detected, in order that the entire electric inductance circuit can generate the best harmonic frequency.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="133.94mm" wi="213.61mm" file="US07298361-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="213.44mm" wi="160.27mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298361-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="193.97mm" wi="158.75mm" file="US07298361-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="228.01mm" wi="136.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298361-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="223.27mm" wi="165.18mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298361-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="220.73mm" wi="131.83mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298361-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="228.85mm" wi="160.53mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07298361-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">1. Field of the Invention</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention is related to the technique of a non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source, and especially to improvement of circuit construction in an electric inductance circuit for a power source through alternating signals to emit harmonic vibration energy to a set of corresponding receiver equipment by wireless transmission, for the purpose of rendering the entire electric inductance circuit for the power source to generate the best harmonic frequency.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">2. Description of the Prior Art</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">A conventional wireless non-battery mouse concerns a technique taking advantage of a fact that harmonic vibration energy provided by alternating signals can be obtained by a coil and further converted into electric energy to render a power source that is expected to be supplied for a mouse (or a set of related receiver equipment) to emit in the mode of wireless transmission (i.e., the receiver equipment and the power supply do not contact via circuit contact points).</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Such a transmission technique for a power source in which harmonic vibration energy is emitted to a set of corresponding receiver equipment through alternating signals by wireless transmission mainly uses alternating electric current passing through a coil to generate signals of high frequency with harmonic vibration; while the coil of the corresponding receiver equipment receives the harmonic vibration of the signals of high frequency to convert it into electric energy. This means that the quality of the harmonic vibration (harmonic frequency) generated by the power supply (or the electric inductance circuit for the power source) will directly influence the subsequent electric energy received/converted from the receiver equipment.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">And more, the harmonic vibration generated by the power supply (or the electric inductance circuit for the power source) mainly is formed through operations of an internal inductance and an internal capacitor; hence the expected harmonic frequency generated can be obtained by using the inductance and the capacitor of given specifications. However, practical operating efficiencies of inductances of same specification or capacitors of same specification still have some differences among themselves; thereby similar power supplies (or electric inductance circuits for power sources) shall further be added with related adjusting parts (or material) in the process of production to compensate the operation effects of the inductances or capacitors, and the adjusting parts must take cumbersome and repeated adjustment actions to render the harmonic frequencies generated to get the range asked; thereby, the yield of production of the similar power supplies (or electric inductance circuits for power sources) can not be effectively elevated, this in turn affects their market competitiveness.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source of the present invention is an electric inductance circuit for a power source emitting harmonic vibration energy to a set of corresponding receiver equipment through alternating signals by wireless transmission to electrically charge the receiver equipment or instantly supply the receiver equipment with operation power source. The entire supplying circuit of the electric inductance circuit for the power source basically has a driving circuit, a harmonic circuit, a feedback circuit, a micro-processing circuit and an adapted-to-adjusting-frequency oscillating circuit integrated with one another.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">When in operation, the adapted-to-adjusting-frequency oscillating circuit generates alternating electric current that passes to the harmonic circuit after being amplified through the driving circuit, and the feedback circuit transmits the voltage or the current of the harmonic circuit to the micro-processing circuit that analyses the value of the voltage or the current detected, then the adapted-to-adjusting-frequency oscillating circuit adjusts the frequency of subsequent input alternating electric current, in order that the entire electric inductance circuit for the power source can generate the best harmonic frequency.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Moreover, the electric inductance circuit for the power source of the present invention can be further integrated with a signal processing circuit transmitted in the mode of radio signal transmission, so that the electric inductance circuit for the power source can be used as the equipment for the radio signal transmission (such as a signal receiver of a wireless mouse or a wireless keyboard), thereby the function and added value of the entire electric inductance circuit for the power source can be elevated.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">The present invention will be apparent in its structure combination and entire mode of operation after reading the detailed description of the preferred embodiment thereof in reference to the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a block view showing the construction of a first preferred embodiment of an electric inductance circuit for a power source of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a circuit diagram of the first preferred embodiment of an electric inductance circuit for a power source of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a block view showing the construction of a second preferred embodiment of an electric inductance circuit for a power source of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a block view showing the construction of a third preferred embodiment of an electric inductance circuit for a power source of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a block view showing the construction of a fourth preferred embodiment of an electric inductance circuit for a power source of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a block view showing the construction of a fifth preferred embodiment of an electric inductance circuit for a power source of the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENT</heading>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">The non-contact electric inductance circuit <b>10</b> for a power source of the present invention is an electric inductance circuit for a power source emitting harmonic vibration energy to a set of corresponding receiver equipment through alternating signals by wireless transmission to electrically charge the receiver equipment or instantly supply the receiver equipment with operating power source. When in operation, this can be applied on transmission of electric power by the receiver equipment such as a wireless mouse, a wireless keyboard, a backlight board, a contact-control panel, a write pen etc., the receiver equipment such as the wireless mouse or the wireless keyboard etc. can obtain the electric power required for instant operation without any contact of circuit contacting point (this is so called non-contact transmission), or can be applied on electrically charging products to charge the electric power storing element in the equipment; and even can be applied on a circuit of a radio frequency identification system (RFID system) to generate an electric-wave magnetic field.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, the entire electric inductance circuit <b>10</b> basically has a driving circuit <b>11</b>, a harmonic circuit <b>12</b>, a feedback circuit <b>13</b>, a micro-processing circuit <b>14</b> (namely the first micro-processing circuit <b>14</b> marked in the drawing) and an adapted-to-adjusting-frequency oscillating circuit <b>15</b> integrated with one another. The driving circuit <b>11</b> can amplify an alternative current generated by the adapted-to-adjusting-frequency oscillating circuit <b>15</b> and pass to the harmonic circuit <b>12</b>, and the input alternating electric current acquires a harmonic feature (f=½π√{square root over (LC)}) through an inductance L and a capacitor C in the harmonic circuit <b>12</b>, then the coil of a set of corresponding receiver equipment <b>20</b> can receive the harmonic vibration of signals, and the harmonic energy can be converted into electric energy.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">And as mentioned in the “Description of the Prior Art” above, the harmonic frequency generated by operations of an inductance and a capacitor will not be an expected harmonic frequency solely because of identity of the specifications of parts assembled, hence the point of improvement of the present invention is to use the feedback circuit <b>13</b> to transmit the voltage or the current of the harmonic circuit <b>12</b> to the first micro-processing circuit <b>14</b> that analyses the value of the voltage or the current detected (to obtain the practically generated quality of the harmonic vibration, and to obtain by comparing the degree of difference thereof from the quality of the harmonic vibration set in advance), then the adapted-to-adjusting-frequency oscillating circuit <b>15</b> adjusts the frequency to generate the best harmonic frequency. Thereby the entire electric inductance circuit <b>10</b> for the power source can completely save the cumbersome adjusting operation during the process of production, and the yield of production of the non-contact electric inductance circuit <b>10</b> for the power source can be effectively elevated.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">And as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 3 and 4</figref>, the electric inductance circuit <b>10</b> for the power source of the present invention can be further integrated with a signal processing circuit <b>16</b> specific for radio signal transmission, so that the electric inductance circuit <b>10</b> can be a set of radio-signal transmission equipment (such as a signal receiver of a wireless mouse or a wireless keyboard) for a personal computer (PC) or the like. When in practicing, such as is shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the micro-processing circuit <b>14</b> (namely the first micro-processing circuit <b>14</b>) used originally for analyzing/adjusting the quality of the harmonic vibration is used to make connection of the power source with the radio signals, or as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a micro-processing circuit (not shown) used originally for analyzing/adjusting the quality of the harmonic vibration is integrated with the feedback circuit <b>13</b>, an outer portion of the feedback circuit <b>13</b> is integrated further with a second micro-processing circuit <b>17</b> (not shown) specific for signal connection to expect that effective work division can be achieved without lowering speed of radio signal transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">One thing is worth mentioning, by virtue that the non-contact electric inductance circuit <b>10</b> for the power source of the present invention can continuously electrically charge an electric power storing element in the receiver equipment <b>20</b> when not in operation, thereby as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, a function of switching the mode of operation of the driving circuit <b>11</b> can be provided in the micro-processing circuit (namely the first micro-processing circuit <b>14</b> in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>) used originally for analyzing/adjusting the quality of the harmonic vibration, hence when it is in the state that the receiver equipment <b>20</b> emits radio signals, the driving circuit <b>11</b> is kept in the mode of operation of normally providing electric power; on the contrary, when it is in the state that the receiver equipment <b>20</b> does not emit radio signals (i.e., the receiver equipment <b>20</b> is in a non-operating state), the first micro-processing circuit <b>14</b> switches the driving circuit <b>11</b> to an operation mode of lowering output to avoid unnecessary consumption of electric power. Similarly, as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, a micro-processing circuit used originally for analyzing/adjusting the quality of the harmonic vibration is integrated with the feedback circuit <b>13</b>, an outer portion of the feedback circuit <b>13</b> is integrated further with a second micro-processing circuit <b>17</b>, this can also get the function of saving electric power without lowering speed of radio signal transmission.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">As is the description disclosed above, the present invention provides preferred embodiments of electric inductance circuits for power sources; while the description and the drawings given are only for illustrating the embodiment of the present invention, and not for giving any limitation to the scope of the present invention; it will be apparent to those skilled in this art that various equivalent modifications or changes in structure, arrangement as well as feature without departing from the spirit of this invention shall also fall within the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>Having thus described the present invention, what I claim as new and desire to be secured by Letters Patent of the United States are:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source, said circuit amplifies an alternative current generated by an oscillator through a circuit driving circuit and pass to a harmonic circuit; wherein: said electric inductance circuit has a feedback circuit, a micro-processing circuit and an adapted-to-adjusting-frequency oscillating circuit integrated with one another, in order that said feedback circuit transmits voltage or current of said harmonic circuit to said micro-processing circuit that analyses quality of harmonic vibration practically generated, and obtains by comparing the degree of difference of said harmonic vibration from quality of a harmonic vibration set in advance), then said adapted-to-adjusting-frequency oscillating circuit adjusts frequency to get the best harmonic frequency.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: said electric inductance circuit is further integrated with a signal processing circuit transmitted in a mode of radio signal transmission.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein: said micro-processing circuit is integrated with said feedback circuit, an outer portion of said feedback circuit is integrated further with another micro-processing circuit for radio signal transmission.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: said electric inductance circuit is further integrated with another signal processing circuit for radio signal transmission, said micro-processing circuit is given a function of switching mode of operation of said driving circuit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein: said micro-processing circuit is integrated with said feedback circuit, an outer portion of said feedback circuit is integrated further with another micro-processing circuit for radio signal transmission.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: said non-contact electric inductance circuit is applied on non-contact electrically charging products.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: said non-contact electric inductance circuit is applied on a radio-frequency identification system.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: said non-contact electric inductance circuit is applied on a backlight board.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: said non-contact electric inductance circuit is applied on a wireless mouse.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: said non-contact electric inductance circuit is applied on a wireless keyboard.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: said non-contact electric inductance circuit is applied on a contact-control panel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The non-contact electric inductance circuit for a power source as in <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein: said non-contact electric inductance circuit is applied on a write pen.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
