<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296773-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296773</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11052678</doc-number>
<date>20050207</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>187</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>A</section>
<class>47</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>08</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2483112</main-classification>
<further-classification>2483091</further-classification>
<further-classification> 47 4112</further-classification>
<further-classification> 47 411</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Stand for holding silk floral arrangements</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3183624</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Swett</name>
<date>19650500</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 47 4111</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3481075</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Dastoli et al.</name>
<date>19691200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 47 4101</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3778929</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Pearson</name>
<date>19731200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 47 581 R</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6119393</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wourms et al.</name>
<date>20000900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 47 39</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6874276</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Morrison</name>
<date>20050400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 47 45</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>7000347</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Roskin</name>
<date>20060200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification> 47 4111</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>10</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>248270</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2483112</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>2483091</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 47 4112</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 47 411</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 47 4101</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 47 4111</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification> 47 4114</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20060175497</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20060810</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Yang</last-name>
<first-name>Rong Teai</first-name>
<address>
<city>Lexington</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Walker</last-name>
<first-name>Clements</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
<agent sequence="02" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Bernard</last-name>
<first-name>Christopher L.</first-name>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Golden State Silk Flowers, Inc.</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Charlotte</city>
<state>NC</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Sterling</last-name>
<first-name>Amy J.</first-name>
<department>3632</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention provides a stand for holding silk floral arrangements that includes a substantially-tubular piece having a longitudinal axis and defining a first cross-sectional interior area at a first position along the longitudinal axis and a second cross-sectional interior area at a second position along the longitudinal axis. The stand also includes a base piece attached to an end of the substantially-tubular piece, the base piece configured to support the substantially-tubular piece in an upright alignment. The stand further includes a first area-adjustment piece configured to engage the substantially-tubular piece at the first position along the longitudinal axis, the first area-adjustment piece defining a third cross-sectional interior area that is smaller than the first cross-sectional interior area defined at the first position of the substantially-tubular piece. The stand still further includes a second area-adjustment piece configured to engage the substantially-tubular piece at the second position along the longitudinal axis, the second area-adjustment piece defining a fourth cross-sectional interior area that is smaller than the second cross-sectional interior area defined at the second position of the substantially-tubular piece.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="234.53mm" wi="138.68mm" file="US07296773-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="221.40mm" wi="156.80mm" file="US07296773-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="235.54mm" wi="147.66mm" file="US07296773-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="235.20mm" wi="161.63mm" file="US07296773-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to equipment for assisting in the assembly, preparation, and/or display of silk floral arrangements and the like. More specifically, the present invention relates to a stand for holding silk floral arrangements and the like during their assembly, preparation, and/or display.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Typically, silk floral arrangements and the like are assembled and/or prepared by inserting a plurality of silk flowers, branches with leaves, etc., the stems of which comprise a plurality of covered or uncovered wires or the like, into a rigid foam base. This foam base may have a substantially conical, tapered, or wedge shape. During the assembly and/or preparation process, it is often difficult for a floral arranger to adequately support and/or manipulate the foam base. The floral arranger needs to have his or her hands free to insert and align the plurality of silk flowers, branches with leaves, etc., and this is made difficult if he or she must also support and/or manipulate the foam base.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Typically, floral arrangers have used vases, jars, or crudely-fashioned, homemade stands to support and/or manipulate the foam bases as they assemble and/or prepare their silk floral arrangements and the like. Often, these vases, jars, or homemade stands are also used to display the silk floral arrangements and the like. The problem with using such equipment, however, is that, because the sizes of the foam blocks vary from floral arrangement to floral arrangement, different vases, jars, or homemade stands must be used for each. This results in an inefficient use of time and added expense.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">Thus, what is needed is a stand for holding silk floral arrangements and the like during their assembly, preparation, and/or display that is adjustable and capable of easily accommodating a plurality of foam base sizes. This would free the floral arrangers' hands to insert the plurality of silk flowers, branches with leaves, etc. into a silk floral arrangement or the like and align them, while eliminating the inefficient use of time and added expense of having to provide a plurality of different sized vases, jars, or homemade stands.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">In various embodiments, the present invention provides a stand for holding silk floral arrangements and the like during their assembly, preparation, and/or display that is adjustable and capable of easily accommodating a plurality of foam base sizes. This frees a floral arranger's hands to insert a plurality of silk flowers, branches with leaves, etc. into the foam base of a silk floral arrangement or the like and align them, while eliminating the inefficient use of time and added expense of having to provide a plurality of different sized vases, jars, or homemade stands.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">In one embodiment, the present invention provides a stand for holding silk floral arrangements that includes a substantially-tubular piece having a longitudinal axis and defining a first cross-sectional interior area at a first position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece and a second cross-sectional interior area at a second position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece. The stand also includes a base piece attached to an end of the substantially-tubular piece, the base piece attached perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece, the base piece configured to support the substantially-tubular piece in an upright alignment. The stand further includes a first area-adjustment piece configured to engage the substantially-tubular piece at the first position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece, the first area-adjustment piece defining a third cross-sectional interior area that is smaller than the first cross-sectional interior area defined at the first position of the substantially-tubular piece. The stand still further includes a second area-adjustment piece configured to engage the substantially-tubular piece at the second position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece, the second area-adjustment piece defining a fourth cross-sectional interior area that is smaller than the second cross-sectional interior area defined at the second position of the substantially-tubular piece.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">In another embodiment, the present invention provides a method for manufacturing a stand for holding silk floral arrangements that includes providing a substantially-tubular piece having a longitudinal axis and defining a first cross-sectional interior area at a first position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece and a second cross-sectional interior area at a second position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece. The method also includes attaching a base piece to an end of the substantially-tubular piece, the base piece attached perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece, the base piece configured to support the substantially-tubular piece in an upright alignment. The method further includes providing a first area-adjustment piece configured to engage the substantially-tubular piece at the first position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece, the first area-adjustment piece defining a third cross-sectional interior area that is smaller than the first cross-sectional interior area defined at the first position of the substantially-tubular piece. The method still further includes providing a second area-adjustment piece configured to engage the substantially-tubular piece at the second position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece, the second area-adjustment piece defining a fourth cross-sectional interior area that is smaller than the second cross-sectional interior area defined at the second position of the substantially-tubular piece.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">The present invention is illustrated and described herein with reference to various drawings, in which like reference numbers denote like components, parts, or steps, and in which:</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view of one embodiment of the stand for holding silk floral arrangements of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is another perspective view of the stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the configuration illustrated incorporating and using a first area-adjustment piece; and</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a further perspective view of the stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref>, the configuration illustrated incorporating and using the first area-adjustment piece and a second area-adjustment piece.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, in one embodiment of the present invention, a stand for holding silk floral arrangements <b>10</b> includes a substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> having a longitudinal axis <b>14</b> and defining a first cross-sectional interior area <b>16</b> at a first position <b>18</b> along the longitudinal axis <b>14</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> and a second cross-sectional interior area <b>20</b> at a second position <b>22</b> along the longitudinal axis <b>14</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b>. The stand <b>10</b> also includes a base piece <b>24</b> attached to an end <b>26</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b>, the base piece <b>24</b> attached perpendicular to the longitudinal axis <b>14</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b>, the base piece <b>24</b> configured to support the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> in an upright alignment.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> may have any suitable cross-sectional shape (which may, optionally, be variable along the longitudinal axis <b>14</b>) and may comprise a solid or partially-solid-walled structure. For example, in the embodiment illustrated, the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> comprises a plurality of ring members <b>28</b> disposed concentrically about the longitudinal axis <b>14</b> and a plurality of straight members <b>30</b> disposed parallel to the longitudinal axis <b>14</b>. The plurality of ring members <b>28</b> are connected together and held in a fixed relationship with respect to one another by the plurality of straight members <b>30</b>. The plurality of ring members <b>28</b> and the plurality of straight members <b>30</b> are made of a substantially-rigid material, such as metal, wood, or plastic, and are connected together using welds, an adhesive, mechanical fasteners, etc.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">Preferably, the plurality of ring members <b>28</b> and the plurality of straight members <b>30</b> each have a thickness or diameter of between about ⅛ in. and about ½ in., although another suitable dimension may be used. Preferably, the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> has an overall height of between about 3 in. and about 18 in. and a cross sectional area (which may, optionally, be variable along the longitudinal axis <b>14</b>) of between about 1 sq. in. and about 20 sq. in., although other suitable dimensions may be used. The cross-sectional shape and area of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> are selected such that the substantially-tubular piece is capable of receiving the lower portion <b>32</b> of the rigid foam base <b>34</b> associated with a silk floral arrangement or the like, while supporting the upper portion <b>36</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">The base piece <b>24</b> attached to the end <b>26</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> may comprise a solid or wire-frame structure. For example, in the embodiment illustrated, the base piece <b>24</b> comprises a ring member <b>38</b> welded, adhered, or mechanically fastened to radially-extending portions <b>40</b> of the plurality of straight members <b>30</b>. Preferably, the base piece <b>24</b> has a size and shape that are sufficient to support the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> in an upright alignment, especially when a silk floral arrangement or the like is disposed partially within the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the stand for holding silk floral arrangements <b>10</b> also includes a first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b> configured to engage the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> at the first position <b>18</b> along the longitudinal axis <b>14</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b>, the first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b> defining a third cross-sectional unobstructed interior area <b>44</b> that is smaller than the first cross-sectional interior area <b>16</b> defined at the first position <b>18</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b>. The first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b> may comprise a solid or wire-frame structure. For example, in the embodiment illustrated, the first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b> comprises a plurality of ring members <b>46</b> of varying interior diameter joined together by a plurality of spanning members <b>48</b>. The first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b> is secured relative to the first position <b>18</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> via a plurality of attachment mechanisms <b>50</b>, such as a plurality of metal tabs, clips, or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the stand for holding silk floral arrangements <b>10</b> further includes a second area-adjustment piece <b>52</b> configured to engage the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> at the second position <b>22</b> along the longitudinal axis <b>14</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b>, the second area-adjustment piece <b>52</b> defining a fourth cross-sectional interior area <b>54</b> that is smaller than the second cross-sectional interior area <b>20</b> defined at the second position <b>22</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b>. The second area-adjustment piece <b>52</b> may comprise a solid or wire-frame structure. For example, in the embodiment illustrated, the second area-adjustment piece <b>52</b> comprises a plurality of ring members <b>56</b> of varying interior diameter joined together by a plurality of spanning members <b>58</b>. The second area-adjustment piece <b>52</b> is secured relative to the second position <b>22</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> via a plurality of attachment mechanisms <b>60</b>, such as a plurality of metal tabs, clips, or the like.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2 and 3</figref>, in one exemplary configuration of the stand for holding silk floral arrangements <b>10</b> of the present invention, the fourth cross-sectional interior area <b>54</b> defined by the second area-adjustment piece <b>52</b> is smaller than the third cross-sectional interior area <b>44</b> defined by the first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b>. In another exemplary configuration of the stand for holding silk floral arrangements <b>10</b> of the present invention, the first cross-sectional interior area <b>16</b> defined at the first position <b>18</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b> is equal to the second cross-sectional interior area <b>20</b> defined at the second position <b>22</b> of the substantially-tubular piece <b>12</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">In general, the stand for holding silk floral arrangements <b>10</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>) may be selectively used with or without the first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) and/or the second area-adjustment piece <b>52</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) depending upon the size and shape of the foam base <b>34</b> (<figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1-3</figref>) used. For example, the size and shape of the foam base <b>34</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> require that neither the first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b> nor the second area-adjustment piece <b>52</b> be used. The size and shape of the foam base <b>34</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> require that only the first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b> be used. Finally, the size and shape of the foam base <b>34</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> require that both the first area-adjustment piece <b>42</b> and the second area-adjustment piece <b>52</b> be used. This illustrates the flexibility of the apparatus of the present invention.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">Although the present invention has been illustrated and described with reference to preferred embodiments and examples thereof, it will be readily apparent to those of ordinary skill in the art that other embodiments and examples may perform similar functions and/or achieve similar results. All such equivalent embodiments and examples are within the spirit and scope of the present invention and are intended to be covered by the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A stand for holding silk floral arrangements that accommodates a plurality of sizes of floral bases, comprising:
<claim-text>a substantially-tubular piece having a longitudinal axis and comprising a first ring member disposed concentrically about the longitudinal axis defining a first cross-sectional interior area at a first position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece and a second ring member disposed concentrically about the longitudinal axis defining a second cross-sectional interior area at a second position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a base piece attached to an end of the substantially-tubular piece, the base piece attached perpendicular to the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece, the base piece configured to support the substantially-tubular piece in an upright alignment; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first area-adjustment piece selectively and removably secured to the first ring member at the first position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece, the first area-adjustment piece defining a third cross-sectional interior area with an open center that is smaller than the first cross-sectional interior area defined by the first ring member at the first position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the cross-sectional interior areas are configured to receive a lower portion of a floral base and support an upper portion of the floral base.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a second area-adjustment piece configured to engage the substantially-tubular piece at the second position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece, the second area-adjustment piece defining a fourth cross-sectional interior area that is smaller than the second cross-sectional interior area defined at the second position of the substantially-tubular piece.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the fourth cross-sectional interior area defined by the second area-adjustment piece is smaller than the third cross-sectional interior area defined by the first area-adjustment piece.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first cross-sectional interior area defined by the first ring member at the first position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece is equal to the second cross-sectional interior area defined by the second ring member at the second position along the longitudinal axis of the substantially-tubular piece.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the substantially-tubular piece comprises a plurality of ring members disposed concentrically about the longitudinal axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the substantially-tubular piece further comprises a plurality of straight members disposed parallel to the longitudinal axis and connecting the plurality of ring members together.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the plurality of ring members and the plurality of straight members are made of a material selected from the group consisting of metal, wood, and plastic.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the first area-adjustment piece comprises an inner ring member disposed concentrically within an outer ring member, the inner ring member defining the third cross-sectional interior area with the open center.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the second area-adjustment piece comprises an inner ring member disposed concentrically within an outer ring member, the inner ring member defining the fourth cross-sectional interior area.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The stand for holding silk floral arrangements of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the first area-adjustment piece and the second area-adjustment piece engage and are secured relative to the first position of the substantially-tubular piece and the second position of the substantially-tubular piece, respectively, via a plurality of attachment mechanisms.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
