<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07297085-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07297085</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11260875</doc-number>
<date>20051027</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>201</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>F</section>
<class>16</class>
<subclass>H</subclass>
<main-group>3</main-group>
<subgroup>44</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475280</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e53">Three mode, multi-speed transmission</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3118319</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Straub</name>
<date>19640100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>477 20</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5620387</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Janiszewski</name>
<date>19970400</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475150</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6010422</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Garnett et al.</name>
<date>20000100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475  5</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>2006/0063638</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<name>Sowul et al.</name>
<date>20060300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>475  5</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>20</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475280</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475288</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475290</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475329</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475330</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475903</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475207</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475218</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>475219</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>12</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>24</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20070099741</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20070503</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Klemen</last-name>
<first-name>Donald</first-name>
<address>
<city>Carmel</city>
<state>IN</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>omitted</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>US</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>General Motors Corporation</orgname>
<role>02</role>
<address>
<city>Detroit</city>
<state>MI</state>
<country>US</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Pang</last-name>
<first-name>Roger</first-name>
<department>3681</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Young</last-name>
<first-name>Edwin A</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">An automatic transmission providing modal speed ratios, single transition gear shifting, low internal speeds, and an output lock feature is provided. First, second and third modal torque-transmitting mechanisms are selectively engagable along with first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms to effect power flow to first and second planetary gear set to cause the speed of a member of one of the gear sets to increase in the first mode (when the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engaged in successive order while the first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged), decrease in the second mode (when the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engaged in reverse order while the second modal torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged) and increase in the third mode (when the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engaged in successive order while the third modal torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged).</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="146.13mm" wi="195.92mm" file="US07297085-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="246.72mm" wi="176.53mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="261.20mm" wi="182.03mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="267.38mm" wi="166.03mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00004" num="00004">
<img id="EMI-D00004" he="248.67mm" wi="165.86mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00004.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00005" num="00005">
<img id="EMI-D00005" he="261.96mm" wi="175.43mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00005.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00006" num="00006">
<img id="EMI-D00006" he="251.63mm" wi="175.01mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00006.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00007" num="00007">
<img id="EMI-D00007" he="263.48mm" wi="171.53mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00007.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00008" num="00008">
<img id="EMI-D00008" he="260.77mm" wi="174.67mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00008.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00009" num="00009">
<img id="EMI-D00009" he="257.64mm" wi="180.93mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00009.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00010" num="00010">
<img id="EMI-D00010" he="263.65mm" wi="155.96mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00010.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00011" num="00011">
<img id="EMI-D00011" he="264.50mm" wi="131.91mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00011.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00012" num="00012">
<img id="EMI-D00012" he="243.08mm" wi="176.19mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07297085-20071120-D00012.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">TECHNICAL FIELD</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates to a power transmission having at least two planetary gear sets and three modal torque-transmitting mechanisms successively engagable with other torque-transmitting mechanisms to provide three modes of speed ratios with single transition shifts.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Currently available transmissions for heavy working machinery typically have a multi-speed “input” section driving into either a two-speed high/low ratio “splitter” section or a three speed high/medium/low ratio “splitter” section. By successively engaging torque-transmitting mechanisms in the input section (“input torque-transmitting mechanisms”) with the splitter section torque-transmitting mechanisms a shift sequence is achieved. For instance, if the input section includes torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B, C and the splitter section includes torque-transmitting mechanisms low (L), medium (M) and high (H) then the shift sequence would be AL-BL-CL-AM-BM-CM-AH-BH-CH. This shift sequence has single transition shifting except for two undesirable center shifts, i.e., CL to AM and CM to AH. These are double transition shifts which compromise shift quality, shift time and durability of the internal gears.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">The present invention provides an improved transmission, especially for heavy working machinery, with a high number of ratios, very uniform steps and low internal speeds. The transmission has two “rear” planetary gear sets that are uniquely constructed to provide modal operation as explained herein. A “front” section provides power flow input to the rear planetary gear sets using either a modal torque-transmitting mechanism or an input torque-transmitting mechanism, providing multiple input speed ratios. The rear two planetary gear sets are operatively connected with two other modal torque-transmitting mechanisms and a reverse brake. The transmission provides up to three ratios in a first mode, a first transition speed ratio between the first mode and the second mode, up to three additional speed ratios in the second mode, a second transition speed ratio between the second mode and a third mode, and up to three speed ratios in the third mode. Thus, if three input torque-transmitting mechanisms are provided, potentially eleven speed ratios (or corresponding torque ratios) may be achieved. Up to three reverse ratios may be achieved. The third mode speed ratios may include one or more overdrive ratios or the transmission may operate without overdrive depending on gear tooth counts selected.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">In the transmission, input to the rear planetary gear sets from the multi-speed input torque-transmitting mechanisms increases in the first mode, decreases in the second mode and increases again in the third mode.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Specifically, an automatic transmission is provided that has first and second planetary gear sets (the rear planetary gear sets) each having a first member, a second member and a third member. A first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is selectively engagable to connect one of the members of the first planetary gear set with a stationary member such as the transmission housing. A second modal torque-transmitting mechanism is selectively engagable to establish power flow to a member of the second planetary gear set. A third modal torque-transmitting mechanism is selectively engagable to connect any two members of one of the first and second planetary gear sets. First and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are separately selectively engagable to establish power flow at a different member of one of the first and second planetary gear sets than the member at which power flow is established via engagement of the second modal torque-transmitting mechanism. The speed of the member at which power flow is established by engagement of the first or the second input torque-transmitting mechanism increases, then decreases, then increases, respectively, as the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engaged in successive order while the first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged, in reverse order while the second modal torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged, and in successive order while the third modal torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A plurality of gear members (the front section) include a first gear member continuously connected with the input member, a second gear member continuously connected with the member that increases, then decreases, then increases in speed as described above, and a third gear member continuously connected with the member at which power flow is established via engagement of the second modal torque-transmitting mechanism. As used herein, ‘gear member’ within the claimed plurality of gear members may include a ring gear member, a sun gear member or a pinion gear member and may also include a carrier member which rotatably supports the pinion gear members.</p>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">The transmission has an input member and an output member. Preferably, the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engagable in successive order while the first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged to establish respectively increasing first modal speed ratios between the input member and the output member, in reverse order while the second modal torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged to establish respectively increasing second modal speed ratios between the input member and the output member, and in successive order while the third modal torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged to establish respectively increasing third modal speed ratios between the input member and the output member. Speed ratio, as used herein, is the ratio of the speed of the output member to the speed of the input member. Torque ratio is the ratio of the torque of the output member to the torque of the input member. As torque ratio decreases, speed ratio increases.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">Additionally, the first and second modal torque-transmitting mechanisms may be simultaneously engagable to establish a first transition speed ratio between the input member and the output member, with a single transition shift between the first transition speed ratio and both of said first and second modal speed ratios. The first transition speed ratio has a numerical value greater than the first modal speed ratio and less than the second modal speed ratio. Similarly, the second modal torque-transmitting mechanism and the third modal torque-transmitting mechanism may be simultaneously engaged to establish a second transition speed ratio between the input member and the output member, with a single transition shift between the second transition speed ratio and both of the second and third modal speed ratios. The second transition speed ratio has a numerical value greater than the second modal speed ratio and less than the third modal speed ratio. The ability of the transmission to provide the first and second transition speed ratios eliminates undesirable double transition shifts typically encountered with transmissions having a “splitter” section.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Preferably a third input torque-transmitting mechanism is provided that is selectively engagable to establish power flow at the same gear member at which the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms establish power flow. The third input torque-transmitting mechanism is engagable with the first modal torque-transmitting mechanism, with the second modal torque-transmitting mechanism and with the third modal torque-transmitting mechanism to establish another first modal speed ratio, another second modal speed ratio and another third modal speed ratio, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">Preferably, a reverse torque-transmitting mechanism is provided that is selectively engagable to connect one of the members of the second planetary gear set with the stationary member. The first, second and the third input torque-transmitting mechanisms are successively engagable while the reverse torque-transmitting mechanism is engaged to establish different reverse speed ratios between the input member and the output member.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">The reverse torque-transmitting mechanism enables an unique lock-out feature. Specifically, engagement of the reverse torque-transmitting mechanism with the first modal torque-transmitting mechanism prevents rotation of the output member to prevent rolling on steep grades.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">The input torque-transmitting mechanisms may be operatively connected to additional planetary gear sets or to gears in a counter-shaft layout located between the input member and the first and second planetary gear sets. If three input torque-transmitting mechanisms are provided, up to eleven speed ratios may be achieved, although as few as seven may be utilized depending on the step and ratios desired. For instance, a direct, single overdrive or dual overdrive top ratio may be utilized. The rear planetary gear sets (i.e., the first and second planetary gear sets) have two separate interconnected pairs of members. Additionally, the first modal torque-transmitting mechanism connects one of the members of the first planetary gear set with the stationary member. The transmission provides very deep start ratios.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">The above features and advantages and other features and advantages of the present invention are readily apparent from the following detailed description of the best modes for carrying out the invention when taken in connection with the accompanying drawings.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a schematic block diagram representation of a powertrain including the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is a schematic representation of a powertrain including one embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a chart depicting some of the operating characteristics of a powertrain shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>:</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a chart showing the speed of one of the sun gear members of the transmission of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> versus the transmission torque ratio of the transmission of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> at different torque ratios established by engagement of selected ones of modal torque-transmitting mechanisms and input torque-transmitting mechanisms included in the transmission;</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is a schematic representation of a powertrain having a second embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> is a chart depicting some of the operating characteristics of the powertrain shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> is a schematic representation of a powertrain having a third embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> is a chart depicting some of the operating characteristics of the powertrain shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is a schematic representation of a powertrain having a fourth embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> is a chart depicting some of the operating characteristics of the powertrain shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> is a schematic representation of a powertrain incorporating a fifth embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> is chart depicting some of the operating characteristics of the powertrain shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is a schematic representation of a powertrain incorporating a sixth embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> is a chart depicting some of the operating characteristics of the powertrain shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> is a schematic representation of a powertrain incorporating a seventh embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> is a chart depicting some of the operating characteristics of the powertrain shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> is a schematic representation of a powertrain incorporating an eighth embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref> is a chart depicting some of the operating characteristics of the powertrain shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref> is a schematic representation of two rear planetary gear sets of a ninth embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 20</figref> is a schematic representation of two rear planetary gear sets of a transmission depicting a tenth embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 21</figref> is a schematic representation of two rear planetary gear sets of an eleventh embodiment of the transmission of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 22</figref> is a schematic representation of two rear planetary gear sets of a transmission depicting a twelfth embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref> is a schematic representation of a powertrain incorporating a thirteenth embodiment of the transmission of the present invention; and</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 24</figref> is a chart depicting some of the operating characteristics of the powertrain shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="h-0006" num="0000">Schematic Block Diagram of the Transmission</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">Referring to the drawings, wherein like reference numbers represent the same or corresponding parts through out the several views, a powertrain <b>10</b> shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> in block diagram form, is representative of each of the specific transmission embodiments described below. The powertrain <b>10</b> has an engine <b>12</b> and torque converter <b>13</b>, a transmission <b>14</b> and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>14</b> includes an input member or shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected with the engine <b>12</b>, (either directly or through the torque converter <b>13</b>) and an output member of shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with a final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The planetary transmission <b>14</b> includes a front section <b>11</b> (also referred to as an input section) configured to establish power flow to a rear section <b>15</b> (also referred to as an output section) to establish various speed ratios between the input member <b>17</b> and the output member <b>19</b>. The front section <b>11</b> may be comprised of planetary gear sets or may be a countershaft gear arrangement. The rear section <b>15</b> includes first and second planetary gear sets which may be referred to herein as modal planetary gear sets. The front section <b>11</b> includes multiple input section torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B, and C, as well as a second mode clutch (MII). The rear section <b>15</b> includes a first mode brake (MI) engagable to ground a member of one of the modal planetary gear sets to the transmission housing. The rear section <b>15</b> also includes a reverse brake (REV) selectively engagable to ground different members of the modal planetary gear sets to the transmission housing. Additionally, a third mode clutch (MIII) is selectively engagable to connect any two members of one of the modal planetary gear sets. When only one of the input section torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B or C is engaged and clutch MIl is not engaged, power flow is established between the front section <b>11</b> and the rear section <b>15</b> only along power flow path D. If the MII clutch is engaged and none of the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B, C are engaged, power flow is established between the front section <b>11</b> and the rear section <b>15</b> only along the power flow path E. If clutch MII is engaged along with one of the input torque-transmitting mechanisms, A, B or C, power flow is established between the front section <b>11</b> and the rear section <b>15</b> is along both power flow paths D and E.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">Eleven potential forward speed ratios may be achieved in the transmission <b>14</b> by the following engagement schedule:</p>
<p id="h-0007" num="0000">A, MI; B, MI; C, MI-MI, MII-MII, C; MII, B; MII, A-MII, MIII-MIII, A; MIII, B; MIII, C</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">Three reverse speed ratios are achieved by engaging REV and A, REV and B, and REV and C. The first three forward speed ratios, established by engaging A and MI, B and MI and C and MI, establish a first mode, Mode I; the fifth sixth, and seventh ratios established by engaging C and MII, B and MII, and A and MII establish a second mode, Mode II. The ninth, tenth and eleventh speed ratios established by engaging A and MIII, B and MIII, and C and MIII, establish a third mode, MIII. The fourth speed ratio established by engagement of the brake MI and the clutch MII is a first transition speed ratio with a numerical value greater than the Mode I ratios and less than the Mode II ratios. The eighth speed ratio established by engaging the clutch MII and the clutch MIII establishes a second transition mode speed ratio with a numerical value greater than the second mode speed ratios and less than the third mode speed ratios. The modal nature of the engagement schedule allows for the single transition shifts utilized. Under this engagement schedule, the member of the modal planetary gear set which receives power flow from the front section <b>11</b> along power flow path D increases in speed during Mode I, decrease in speed during Mode II and increases in speed again during Mode III. The modal nature of the transmission <b>14</b> is also present in each of the transmission embodiments depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2-24</figref>, as described below.</p>
<heading id="h-0008" level="1">First Transmission Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, a powertrain <b>100</b> has an engine <b>12</b>, a torque converter <b>13</b>, a transmission <b>114</b> and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>114</b> may be characterized by front section <b>11</b> and rear section <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">The transmission <b>114</b> includes an input shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected to the engine <b>12</b> either through the torque converter <b>13</b> or by engagement of a torque converter lock-up clutch <b>18</b> which effectively bypasses the torque converter <b>13</b>. The output shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>114</b> includes five planetary gear sets <b>20</b>, <b>30</b>, <b>40</b>, <b>50</b> and <b>60</b>. The planetary gear set <b>20</b> is referred to in the claims as the first planetary gear set and the planetary gear set <b>30</b> is referred to in the claims as the second planetary gear set. The planetary gear sets <b>20</b> and <b>30</b> are part of the rear section <b>15</b> and the planetary gear sets <b>40</b>, <b>50</b> and <b>60</b> are considered part of the front section <b>11</b> and are referred to in the claims as a plurality of gear members.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The planetary gear set <b>20</b> includes a sun gear member <b>22</b>, a ring gear member <b>24</b> and a carrier member <b>29</b> on which a plurality of pinion gears <b>27</b> are rotatably supported and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>22</b> and the ring gear member <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The planetary gear set <b>30</b> includes a sun gear member <b>32</b>, a ring gear member <b>34</b> and a carrier member <b>39</b> on which a plurality of pinion gears <b>37</b> are rotatably supported and disposed in meshing relationship with the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the ring gear member <b>34</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">The planetary gear set <b>40</b> includes a sun gear member <b>42</b>, a ring gear member <b>44</b> and a carrier member <b>49</b> on which a plurality of pinion gear <b>47</b> are rotatably supported in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>42</b> and the ring gear member <b>44</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The planetary gear set <b>50</b> includes a sun gear member <b>52</b>, a ring gear member <b>54</b>, and a carrier member <b>59</b> which rotatably supports a plurality of pinion gears <b>57</b> that are disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>52</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">The planetary gear set <b>60</b> includes a sun gear member <b>62</b>, ring gear member <b>64</b> and a carrier member <b>69</b> which rotatably supports a plurality of pinion gears <b>67</b> that are disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>62</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The input shaft <b>17</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>69</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>54</b> through an interconnecting member <b>70</b>. The ring gear member <b>64</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>32</b> as well as the sun gear member <b>22</b> through an interconnecting member <b>72</b>. The interconnecting member <b>72</b>, as with all other interconnecting members, may be one component or separate components. The carrier member <b>59</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>44</b> though an interconnecting member <b>74</b>. The carrier member <b>49</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>39</b> through an interconnecting member <b>76</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>29</b> through an interconnecting member <b>78</b>. The sun gear member <b>32</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>22</b> through the interconnecting member <b>72</b>. The sun gear member <b>52</b> is continuously connected with the transmission housing <b>80</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">The ring gear member <b>64</b> and the sun gear members <b>22</b> and <b>32</b> are selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>59</b> and the ring gear member <b>44</b> through an input torque-transmitting mechanism clutch A. The sun gear member <b>62</b> is selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>69</b> and with the ring gear member <b>54</b> through the input torque-transmitting mechanism clutch B. The sun gear member <b>62</b> is selectively grounded to the transmission housing <b>80</b> (a stationary member) through the input torque-transmitting mechanism brake C.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">A first modal torque-transmitting mechanism, brake MI, selectively connects the ring gear member <b>24</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. A second modal torque-transmitting mechanism, brake MII, selectively connects the sun gear member <b>42</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. A third modal torque-transmitting mechanism, clutch MIII, selectively connects the sun gear member <b>32</b> (and the sun gear member <b>22</b>) with carrier member <b>39</b> (and with carrier member <b>49</b> via interconnecting member <b>76</b>). A reverse torque-transmitting mechanism, brake REV, selectively connects the carrier member <b>39</b> (and therefore also carrier member <b>49</b> via interconnecting member <b>76</b>) with the transmission housing <b>80</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">As shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the torque-transmitting mechanisms are selectively engaged in combinations of two to provide nine forward speed ratios and three reverse ratios. (Torque ratios are listed; those skilled in the art will readily understand the relationship between torque ratio and speed ratio (i.e., as torque ratios successively decrease, speed ratios successively increase). The torque-transmitting mechanisms are preferably multiple disk-type, fluid actuated friction drive establishing devices which are commonly used in planetary gear transmissions.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The third reverse speed ratio, R<b>3</b>, is established with the engagement of the brake C and the brake REV. The brake C connects the sun gear member <b>62</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>, and the brake REV connects the carrier members <b>39</b> and <b>49</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b> rotate at the same speed as the input shaft <b>17</b>. The sun gear member <b>62</b>, sun gear member <b>52</b>, carrier member <b>49</b>, and carrier member <b>39</b> do not rotate. Ring gear member <b>64</b> rotates at the same speed as sun gear member <b>32</b> and sun gear member <b>22</b>. Ring gear member <b>64</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the carrier <b>69</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>60</b>. Ring gear member <b>34</b> and carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. Ring gear member <b>34</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>30</b>. The numerical value of the third reverse (R<b>3</b>) speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the planetary gear sets <b>30</b> and <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">The second reverse speed ratio (R<b>2</b>) is established with the engagement of the clutch B and the brake REV. The clutch B connects the carrier member <b>69</b> with the sun gear member <b>62</b>, and the brake REV connects the carrier member <b>39</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. The planetary gear set <b>60</b>, the ring gear member <b>54</b>, the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the sun gear member <b>22</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The sun gear member <b>52</b> and the carrier members <b>49</b> and <b>39</b> do not rotate. The ring gear member <b>34</b> and the carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>30</b>. The numerical value of the second reverse (R<b>2</b>) speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0055" num="0054">The first reverse speed ratio (R<b>1</b>) is established with the engagement of the clutch A and the brake REV. The clutch A connects the ring gear member <b>44</b> with the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the brake REV connects the carrier member <b>39</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The ring gear member <b>64</b> rotates at the same speed as the sun gear member <b>32</b>, the sun gear member <b>22</b>, the carrier member <b>59</b> and the ring gear member <b>44</b>. The sun gear member <b>52</b> and the carrier members <b>49</b> and <b>39</b> do not rotate. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at a speed determined from the ring gear member <b>54</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>50</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b> and the carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>30</b>. The numerical value of the first reverse (R<b>1</b>) speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the planetary gear sets <b>30</b> and <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0056" num="0055">The first forward speed ratio is established with the engagement of the clutch A and the brake MI. The clutch A connects the ring gear member <b>44</b> with the sun gear member <b>32</b> (and the sun gear member <b>22</b>), and the brake MI connects the ring gear member <b>24</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at the same speed as the ring gear member <b>44</b>, the sun gear members <b>22</b> and <b>32</b>, and the ring gear member <b>64</b>. The sun gear member <b>52</b> and the ring gear member <b>24</b> do not rotate. The carrier member <b>59</b> and sun gear member <b>22</b> rotate at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>54</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>50</b>. The carrier member <b>29</b> rotates at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The carrier member <b>29</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the sun gear member <b>22</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>20</b>. The numerical value of the first forward speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the planetary gear sets <b>20</b> and <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0057" num="0056">The second forward-speed ratio is established with the engagement of the clutch B and the brake MI. The clutch B connects the carrier member <b>69</b> with the sun gear member <b>62</b>, and the brake MI connects the ring gear member <b>24</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. The planetary gear set <b>60</b>, the ring gear member <b>54</b> and the sun gear members <b>22</b> and <b>32</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The sun gear member <b>52</b> and the ring gear member <b>24</b> do not rotate. The carrier member <b>49</b> rotates at the same speed as the carrier member <b>39</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b> and the carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The carrier member <b>39</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>34</b>, the speed of the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>30</b>. The carrier member <b>29</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the sun gear member <b>22</b> (driven the same speed as input member <b>17</b>) and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>20</b>. The numerical value of the second forward speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0058" num="0057">The third forward speed ratio is established with the engagement of the brake C and the brake MI. The brake C connects the sun gear member <b>62</b> with transmission housing <b>80</b>, and the brake MI connects the ring gear member <b>24</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The ring gear member <b>64</b> rotates at the same speed as the sun gear member <b>22</b> and the sun gear member <b>32</b>. The sun gear members <b>52</b> and <b>62</b> and the ring gear member <b>24</b> do not rotate. The ring gear member <b>64</b> rotates at a speed determined from the carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>60</b>. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at the same speed as the ring gear member <b>44</b>. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>54</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>50</b>. The carrier member <b>49</b> rotates at the same speed as the carrier member <b>39</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b> and the carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The carrier member <b>39</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>34</b>, the speed of the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>30</b>. The carrier member <b>29</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the sun gear member <b>22</b> (which is the same as the speed of the ring gear member <b>64</b>) and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>20</b>. The numerical value of the third forward speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the planetary gear sets <b>20</b> and <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0059" num="0058">The fourth forward speed ratio is established with the engagement of the brakes MI and MII. The brake MI connects the ring gear member <b>24</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>, and the brake MII connects the sun gear member <b>42</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The sun gear members <b>42</b> and <b>52</b> and the ring gear member <b>24</b> do not rotate. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at the same speed as the ring gear member <b>44</b>. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>54</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>50</b>. The carrier member <b>49</b> rotates at the same speed as the carrier member <b>39</b>. The carrier member <b>49</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>44</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>40</b>. The sun gear member <b>22</b> and the sun gear member <b>32</b> rotate at the same speed as the ring gear member <b>64</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b> and the carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the carrier member <b>39</b>, the speed of the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>30</b>. The carrier member <b>29</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the sun gear member <b>22</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>20</b>. The numerical value of the fourth forward speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the planetary gear sets <b>20</b>, <b>30</b>, <b>40</b> and <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0060" num="0059">The fifth forward speed ratio is established with the engagement of the brake C and the brake MII. The brake C connects the sun gear member <b>62</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>, and the brake MII connects the sun gear member <b>42</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The sun gear members <b>42</b>, <b>52</b> and <b>62</b> do not rotate. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at the same speed as the ring gear member <b>44</b>. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>54</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>50</b>. The carrier member <b>49</b> rotates at the same speed as the carrier member <b>39</b>. The carrier member <b>49</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>44</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>40</b>. The sun gear members <b>22</b> and <b>32</b> rotate at the same speed as the ring gear member <b>64</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b> and the carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The ring gear member <b>34</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the carrier member <b>39</b>, the speed of the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>30</b>. The numerical value of the fifth forward speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the planetary gear sets <b>30</b>, <b>40</b>, <b>50</b> and <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0061" num="0060">The sixth forward speed ratio is established with the engagement of the brake MII and the clutch MIII. The brake MII connects the sun gear member <b>42</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>, and the clutch MIII connects the carrier member <b>39</b> with the sun gear member <b>32</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at the same speed as the ring gear member <b>44</b>. The sun gear members <b>42</b> and <b>52</b> do not rotate. The carrier member <b>59</b> rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>54</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>50</b>. The carrier member <b>49</b>, the planetary gear set <b>30</b>, the sun gear member <b>22</b> and the ring gear member <b>64</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The carrier member <b>49</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>44</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>40</b>. The numerical value of the sixth forward speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the planetary gear sets <b>40</b> and <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0062" num="0061">The seventh forward speed ratio is established with the engagement of the clutch A and the clutch MIII. The clutch A connects the ring gear member <b>44</b> with the sun gear member <b>32</b> and the clutch MIII connects the carrier member <b>39</b> with the sun gear member <b>32</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The carrier member <b>59</b>, the ring gear member <b>44</b>, the carrier member <b>49</b>, the planetary gear set <b>30</b>, the sun gear member <b>22</b> and the carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The sun gear member <b>52</b> does not rotate. The carrier member <b>59</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the ring gear member <b>54</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>50</b>. The numerical value of the seventh forward speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>50</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0063" num="0062">The eighth forward speed ratio is established with the engagement of the clutch MIII and the clutch B. The clutch B connects the carrier member <b>69</b> with the sun gear member <b>62</b>, and the clutch MIII connects the carrier member <b>39</b> with the sun gear member <b>32</b>. The planetary gear set <b>60</b>, the planetary gear set <b>30</b>, the sun gear member <b>22</b> and the carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. Because the carrier member <b>29</b> also rotates at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>, the input member <b>17</b> rotates at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b> in this configuration, providing a direct drive ratio.</p>
<p id="p-0064" num="0063">The ninth forward speed ratio is established with the engagement of the brake C and the clutch MIII. The brake C connects the sun gear member <b>62</b> with the transmission housing <b>80</b>, and the clutch MIII connects the carrier member <b>39</b> with the sun gear member <b>32</b>. The carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear member <b>54</b> rotate at the same speed as the input member <b>17</b>. The ring gear member <b>64</b>, the planetary gear set <b>30</b>, the sun gear member <b>22</b> and the carrier member <b>29</b> rotate at the same speed as the output member <b>19</b>. The ring gear member <b>64</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b>, rotates at a speed determined from the speed of the carrier member <b>69</b> and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>60</b>. The numerical value of the ninth forward speed ratio is determined utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>60</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0065" num="0064">The engagement schedule for the torque-transmitting mechanisms in the transmission <b>114</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is shown in the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>. Chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> also provides an example of torque ratios that are available utilizing the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios as follows: the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>20</b> is 3.96; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>30</b> is 4.65; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>40</b> is 3.26; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>50</b> is 3.26; and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>60</b> is 3.57.</p>
<p id="p-0066" num="0065">Also, the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> describes the ratio steps that are obtained utilizing the tooth ratio values listed above. For example, the step ratio between the first and second forward torque ratio is 1.31, while the step ratio between the second and third forward torque ratio is 1.28. It is apparent from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> that the first three forward speed ratios are established with the engagement of the first mode brake MI while the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C are engaged in succeeding order. The fourth, fifth and sixth speed ratios are attained with the engagement of the second mode brake MII. The fourth forward speed ratio is a transition speed ratio in which the brake MI and the clutch MII are engaged, while the sixth forward speed ratio is a transition ratio in which the clutch MII and the brake MIII are engaged. The seventh, eighth and ninth forward speed ratios establish the third mode in which the clutch MIII is engaged while the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C are engaged in succeeding order. Only the ninth forward speed ratio is an overdrive ratio. Accordingly, as most of the forward speed ratios are underdrive ratios, lower internal speeds are maintained. Alternatively, the highest speed ratio could be an overdrive ratio, or two overdrive ratios could be provided, depending on engine speeds, vehicle speeds, axles available, and internal design considerations. Single transition shifts are employed in the forward speed ratios as well as the reverse speed ratios as is evident from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0067" num="0066">The transmission <b>114</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is able to “lock” the output member <b>19</b> by engaging the brake REV and the brake MI. If a vehicle having transmission <b>114</b> is parked on a grade, wheels interconnected with the output member <b>19</b> will transfer a gravity-induced torque to the output member <b>19</b>, which may attempt to rotate the carrier member <b>29</b>. If the output member <b>19</b> attempts to rotate in a clockwise direction, the carrier member <b>29</b> and the ring gear member <b>34</b>, interconnected by interconnecting member <b>78</b>, will attempt to also rotate in a clockwise direction. Because the ring gear member <b>24</b> is braked by brake MI, this will cause the sun gear member <b>22</b> to attempt to rotate in a clockwise direction as well. With the ring gear member <b>34</b> attempting to rotate in a clockwise direction, because the carrier member <b>39</b> is braked by brake REV, the pinion gears <b>37</b> will attempt to rotate in a clockwise direction, causing the sun gear member <b>32</b> to attempt to rotate in a counter-clockwise direction. Because the interconnecting member <b>79</b> connects the sun gear member <b>22</b> with the sun gear member <b>32</b>, with the sun gear member <b>22</b> attempting to rotate in a clockwise direction, and the sun gear member <b>32</b> attempting to rotate in a counter-clockwise direction, rotation is prevented.</p>
<p id="p-0068" num="0067">It is apparent from the above descriptions of the respective torque ratios listed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> that the engagement of any of the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B or C affects power flow to and therefore the speed of the sun gear member <b>32</b>. The power flow to the sun gear member <b>32</b> is along the interconnecting member <b>72</b> which is comparable to the torque flow path D of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. When the brake MII is engaged, power flow from the front section <b>11</b> to the rear section <b>15</b> is affected through the interconnecting member <b>76</b> as the planetary gear set <b>40</b> is made active. Interconnecting member <b>76</b> is comparable to the power flow path E of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. With respect to the claims, carrier member <b>69</b> is the first gear member, ring gear member <b>64</b> is the second gear member and carrier member <b>49</b> is the third gear member.</p>
<p id="p-0069" num="0068">Referring now to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, the ratio of the speed of the sun gear member <b>22</b> to the speed of the input member <b>17</b> in the transmission <b>114</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is plotted versus torque ratio (i.e., the torque of the output member <b>19</b> with respect to the torque of the input member <b>17</b>). Each of the nine forward speed ratios (corresponding to torque ratios indicated in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) is plotted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> as follows: point F represents the first speed ratio, point G represents the second speed ratio, point H represents the third speed ratio, point I represent the fourth speed ratio, point J represents the fifth speed ratio, point K represents the sixth speed ratio, point L represents the seventh speed ratio, point M represents the eighth speed ratio and point N represents the ninth speed ratio. Thus, points F, G and H represent the first modal speed ratios (establishing the first mode) while point I represents the first transition speed ratio, the fourth speed ratio. Point J represents a second modal speed ratio (establishing the second mode) while point K represents the second transition speed ratio, the sixth forward speed ratio. Points L, M and N represent third modal speed ratios (establishing the third mode). It is evident from the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> that the ratio of the speed of the sun gear member <b>32</b> to the speed of the input member <b>17</b> increases in the first mode, reaches a maximum at the first transition speed ratio, decreases in the second mode, reaches a minimum at the second transition speed ratio and increases again during the third mode.</p>
<heading id="h-0009" level="1">Second Transmission Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0070" num="0069">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>, another embodiment of a powertrain <b>200</b> having an engine <b>12</b>, a planetary transmission <b>214</b> and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b> is depicted. A torque converter <b>13</b> with lock-up clutch <b>18</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> may also be employed between the engine <b>12</b> and the input shaft <b>17</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0071" num="0070">The planetary transmission <b>214</b> includes the input shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected with engine <b>12</b> and an output shaft <b>19</b> continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>214</b> includes a first planetary gear set <b>220</b> and a second planetary gear set <b>230</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>220</b> and <b>230</b> are within and partially define a rear section <b>15</b> of the transmission <b>214</b>. A front section <b>11</b> of the transmission <b>214</b> includes a plurality of gears <b>221</b>, as described below.</p>
<p id="p-0072" num="0071">The planetary gear set <b>220</b> includes a sun gear member <b>222</b>, a ring gear member <b>224</b>, and a carrier member <b>229</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>227</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>229</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>222</b> and the ring gear member <b>224</b>. The planetary gear set <b>220</b> is referred to in the claims as the first planetary gear set.</p>
<p id="p-0073" num="0072">The planetary gear set <b>230</b> includes a sun gear member <b>232</b>, a ring gear member <b>234</b>, and a carrier member <b>239</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>237</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>239</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>232</b> and the ring gear member <b>234</b>. The planetary gear set <b>230</b> is referred to in the claims as the second planetary gear set.</p>
<p id="p-0074" num="0073">The plurality of gear members <b>221</b> includes a headset comprised of gear <b>261</b>, gear <b>263</b> and gear <b>265</b>. Gear <b>263</b> is connected for common rotation with the input shaft <b>17</b>. Gear <b>261</b> intermeshes with gear <b>263</b> and is connected for common rotation with a countershaft <b>270</b>. Gear <b>265</b> intermeshes with gear <b>263</b> and is connected for common rotation with a countershaft <b>272</b>. Gear <b>263</b> is referred to in the claims as the first gear member of the plurality of gear members <b>221</b>. The plurality of gear members <b>221</b> further includes gear <b>266</b> which rotates about countershaft <b>270</b> on sleeve shaft <b>268</b>. Gear <b>266</b> intermeshes with gear <b>267</b> which is connected for common rotation with interconnecting member or shaft <b>274</b>. Connecting shaft <b>274</b> may be one component or separate components and also interconnects with sun gear members <b>222</b> and <b>232</b>. The plurality of gear members <b>221</b> also includes gear <b>251</b> which is connected for common rotation with connecting shaft <b>274</b>. The plurality of gear members <b>221</b> further includes gear <b>253</b> which is connected for common rotation with sleeve shaft <b>255</b> and rotates about countershaft <b>272</b>. Furthermore, the plurality of gear members <b>221</b> includes gears <b>241</b> and <b>243</b>. Gear <b>241</b> is connected for common rotation with the countershaft <b>270</b> and intermeshes with gear <b>243</b> which is connected for common rotation with sleeve shaft <b>245</b>. Sleeve shaft <b>245</b> rotates about and is concentric with the connecting shaft <b>274</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0075" num="0074">The input shaft <b>17</b> is continuously connected with the gear <b>263</b>. The output shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>229</b>. The interconnecting member <b>278</b> continuously connects the ring gear member <b>234</b> with the carrier member <b>229</b>. The connecting shaft <b>274</b> continuously connects the sun gear members <b>222</b> and <b>232</b>. Gear <b>261</b> is continuously connected with gear <b>241</b> via the countershaft <b>270</b>. Gear <b>267</b> is continuously connected with gear <b>251</b> via the connecting shaft <b>274</b>. Gear <b>266</b> is intermeshed with gear <b>267</b>, gear <b>241</b> is intermeshed with gear <b>243</b>, and gear <b>253</b> is intermeshed with gear <b>251</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0076" num="0075">Gear <b>265</b> is selectively connectable with gear <b>253</b> by the engagement of the clutch A which interconnects the countershaft <b>272</b> with the sleeve shaft <b>255</b>. The input member <b>17</b> is selectively connectable with the connecting shaft <b>274</b> via engagement of the clutch B. Gear <b>261</b> is selectively connectable with gear <b>266</b> via engagement of clutch C which interconnects the countershaft <b>270</b> with the sleeve shaft <b>268</b>. Ring gear member <b>224</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>280</b> via engagement of the brake MI. Gear <b>243</b> is selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>239</b> via engagement of the clutch MII. The sun gear member <b>222</b> is selectively connectable with carrier member <b>229</b> via engagement of the clutch MIII which also interconnects the sun gear member <b>222</b> with the output member <b>19</b>. The carrier member <b>239</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>280</b> via engagement of the brake REV.</p>
<p id="p-0077" num="0076">As shown in the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>, the torque-transmitting mechanisms of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> (i.e., clutches A, B, C, clutch MII, clutch MIII and brakes MI and REV) are selectively engaged in combinations of two to provide nine forward speed ratios and three reverse speed ratios (corresponding torque ratios are listed). The engagement schedule for torque-transmitting mechanisms of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> is shown in the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> also provides an example of torque ratios that are available using the follow gear tooth counts and ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>: gears <b>261</b>, <b>263</b> and <b>265</b> each have 100 teeth, gear <b>266</b> has 112 teeth, gear <b>267</b> has 88 teeth, gear <b>251</b> has 113 teeth, gear <b>253</b> has 87 teeth, gear <b>241</b> has 74 teeth, gear <b>243</b> has 126 teeth; the planetary gear set <b>220</b> has a ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of 3.96, and the planetary gear set <b>230</b> has a ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of 4.84.</p>
<p id="p-0078" num="0077">The first three forward speed ratios of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> are first modal speed ratios (because the brake MI is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C) establishing a first mode. The fourth forward speed ratio is a first transition speed ratio (corresponding with the torque ratio of 2.86). The fifth forward speed ratio is a second modal speed ratio (because the clutch MII is engaged with clutch C) establishing a second mode. The sixth forward speed ratio is a second transition speed ratio (corresponding with the torque ratio of 1.70). The seventh, eighth and ninth forward speed ratios are third modal speed ratios (because the clutch MIII is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C) establishing a third mode. The first through seventh forward speed ratios are underdrive ratios, the eighth forward speed ratio is a direct drive ratio and the ninth forward speed is an overdrive speed ratio, as determined by the gear ratio selections of each component. Each of the forward speed ratios as well as the three reverse speed ratios involve single transition shifts, are characterized by close ratio steps (listed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref>) and the first forward speed ratio as well as the first reverse speed ratio (R<b>1</b>) are deep start ratios.</p>
<p id="p-0079" num="0078">The transmission <b>214</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref> provides a locked output feature by engaging both the brake REV and the brake MI simultaneously while on an incline. As the output shaft <b>19</b> attempts to rotate in one direction (for instance, clockwise) the carrier member <b>229</b> as well as the ring gear member <b>234</b> will also attempt to rotate clockwise. This will force the sun gear member <b>222</b> to attempt to rotate clockwise while the sun gear member <b>232</b> attempts to rotate counter-clockwise, thus effectively preventing rotation of the output shaft <b>19</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0080" num="0079">With respect to the claims, the gear <b>263</b> is the first gear member of the plurality of gear members, gear <b>251</b> is the second gear member of the plurality of gear members and gear <b>243</b> is the third gear member of the plurality of gear members. Accordingly, the speed of the sun gear member <b>232</b> increases during the first mode, decreases during the second mode and increases again during the third mode. The connecting shaft <b>274</b> is comparable to power flow path D, and the sleeve shaft <b>245</b> and gear <b>243</b> is comparable to power flow path E.</p>
<p id="p-0081" num="0080">As shown and described above for the transmission of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, those skilled in the art will understand from the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 6</figref> how the torque ratios shown are established through the planetary gear sets <b>220</b> and <b>230</b> as well as the plurality of gear members <b>221</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0010" level="1">Third Transmission Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0082" num="0081"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> shown a powertrain <b>300</b> having an engine <b>12</b>, a transmission <b>314</b> and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>314</b> may be characterized by a front section <b>11</b> and a rear section <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0083" num="0082">The transmission <b>314</b> includes an input shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected with the engine <b>12</b> either through a torque converter <b>13</b> or via engagement of a torque converter lock-up clutch <b>18</b> which effectively bypasses the torque converter <b>13</b>. The transmission <b>314</b> also includes an output shaft <b>19</b> continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>314</b> includes four planetary gear sets <b>320</b>, <b>330</b>, <b>340</b> and <b>350</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>340</b> and <b>350</b> partially define the front section <b>11</b> and the planetary gear sets <b>320</b> and <b>330</b> partially define the rear section <b>15</b>. Planetary gear set <b>320</b> is referred to in the claims as the first planetary gear set, and the planetary gear set <b>330</b> is referred to in the claims as the second planetary gear set. The planetary gear sets <b>340</b> and <b>350</b> are referred to in the claims as a plurality of gear members.</p>
<p id="p-0084" num="0083">Planetary gear set <b>320</b> includes a sun gear member <b>322</b>, a ring gear member <b>324</b> and carrier member <b>329</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>327</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>329</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>322</b> and the ring gear member <b>324</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0085" num="0084">Planetary gear set <b>330</b> includes a sun gear member <b>332</b>, a ring gear member <b>334</b> and a carrier member <b>339</b>. A plurality of pinion gear <b>337</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>339</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>332</b> and the ring gear member <b>334</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0086" num="0085">Planetary gear set <b>340</b> includes a sun gear member <b>342</b>, a ring gear member <b>344</b> and a carrier member <b>349</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>347</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>349</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>342</b> and the ring gear member <b>344</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0087" num="0086">The planetary gear set <b>350</b> includes a sun gear member <b>352</b>, a ring gear member <b>354</b> and a carrier member <b>359</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>357</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>359</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>352</b> and the ring gear member <b>354</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0088" num="0087">The input shaft <b>17</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>359</b> and therefore also to the ring gear member <b>344</b> via interconnecting member <b>370</b> which connects the carrier member <b>359</b> with the ring gear member <b>344</b>. The output shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>329</b> and therefore also with the ring gear member <b>334</b> which is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>329</b> via interconnecting member <b>378</b>. The ring gear member <b>354</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>332</b> and also with the sun gear member <b>322</b> via an interconnecting member <b>372</b> which may be one component or separate components. The carrier member <b>349</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>339</b> via interconnecting member <b>376</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>340</b> and <b>350</b> are referred to as a plurality of gear members within the claims.</p>
<p id="p-0089" num="0088">With respect to the claims, the first gear member of the plurality of gear members is carrier member <b>359</b>, the second gear member of the plurality of gear members is ring gear member <b>354</b>, and the third gear member of the plurality of gear members is carrier member <b>349</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0090" num="0089">The sun gear member <b>352</b> is selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>359</b> and the ring gear member <b>344</b> via engagement of the clutch B. The sun gear member <b>352</b> is selectively connectable to transmission housing <b>380</b> via engagement of the brake C. The clutch B and brake C are referred to herein as input torque-transmitting mechanisms. The ring gear member <b>324</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>380</b> via engagement of the first modal torque-transmitting mechanism, brake MI. The sun gear member <b>342</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>380</b> via engagement of the second modal torque-transmitting mechanism, brake MII. The carrier member <b>339</b> is selectively connectable with the sun gear member <b>332</b> (and also the sun gear member <b>322</b> and ring gear member <b>354</b> via the interconnecting member <b>372</b>) via engagement of the third modal torque-transmitting mechanism, clutch MII. The carrier member <b>339</b> (and also the carrier member <b>349</b> via the interconnecting member <b>376</b>) is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>380</b> via engagement of the brake REV.</p>
<p id="p-0091" num="0090">Referring to the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>, the engagement schedule for the torque-transmitting mechanisms of the transmission <b>314</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref> to achieve seven forward speed ratios and two reverse speed ratios is provided. Torque ratios as well as ratio steps associated with the speed ratios are listed. A corresponding numerical speed ratio is associated with each of numbers 1-7, R<b>2</b> and R<b>1</b>. The first and second forward speed ratios are first modal speed ratios (because brake MI is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms B and C) and establish a first mode. The third forward speed ratio establishes a first transition speed ratio. The fourth forward speed ratio is a second modal speed ratio (because brake MII is engaged with brake C) and establishes a second mode. The fifth forward speed ratio establishes a second transition mode. The sixth and seventh forward speed ratios are third modal speed ratios (because brake MIII is engage with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms B and C) and establish a third mode. The engagement schedule depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref> involves single transition shifts. Additionally, the first forward speed ratio as well as the reverse ratio R<b>1</b> provides a deep start ratio. The transmission <b>314</b> is designed to provide the close ratio steps listed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 8</figref>. The listed torque ratios and ratio steps result from the following ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the transmission <b>314</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 7</figref>: the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of planetary gear set <b>320</b> is 3.00; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>330</b> is 3.80; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>340</b> is 2.88; and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>350</b> is 2.88.</p>
<p id="p-0092" num="0091">Application of the brake REV and the brake MI provides a lockout feature to prevent rotation of the output member <b>19</b> on steep grades. The lockout feature performs in the same manner as that described with respect to the lockout feature of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<heading id="h-0011" level="1">Fourth Transmission Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0093" num="0092">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>, another embodiment of a powertrain <b>400</b> having engine <b>12</b>, a planetary transmission <b>414</b> and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b> is depicted. The transmission <b>414</b> may be characterized by a front section <b>11</b> and a rear section <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0094" num="0093">The transmission <b>414</b> includes an input shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected with the engine <b>12</b> either through a torque converter <b>13</b> or via engagement of a torque converter lockup clutch <b>18</b> which effectively bypasses the torque converter <b>13</b>. The transmission <b>414</b> also includes an output shaft <b>19</b> continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>414</b> includes a first planetary gear set <b>420</b> and a second planetary gear set <b>430</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>420</b> and <b>430</b> are within and partially define the rear section <b>15</b> of the transmission <b>414</b>. The front section <b>11</b> of the transmission <b>414</b> includes a plurality of gear members <b>421</b>, as described below.</p>
<p id="p-0095" num="0094">The planetary gear set <b>420</b> includes a sun gear member <b>422</b>, a ring gear member <b>424</b>, and a carrier member <b>429</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>427</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>429</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>422</b> and the ring gear member <b>424</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0096" num="0095">The planetary gear set <b>430</b> includes a sun gear member <b>432</b>, a ring gear member <b>434</b>, and a carrier member <b>439</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>437</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>439</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>432</b> and the ring gear member <b>434</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0097" num="0096">The plurality of gear members <b>421</b> includes a head set comprised of gear <b>461</b>, gear <b>463</b> and gear <b>465</b>. Gear <b>463</b> has a hub portion <b>469</b> and is connected for common rotation with the input shaft <b>17</b>. Gear <b>461</b> intermeshes with gear <b>463</b> and is connected for common rotation with the countershaft <b>470</b>. Gear <b>465</b> intermeshes with gear <b>463</b> and is connected for common rotation with the countershaft <b>471</b>. Gear <b>463</b> is referred to in the claims as the first gear of the plurality of gear members <b>421</b>. The plurality of gear members <b>421</b> further includes gear <b>441</b> which rotates about countershaft <b>470</b> on sleeve shaft <b>468</b>. Gear <b>441</b> intermeshes with gear <b>467</b> which is connected for common rotation with connecting member or shaft <b>472</b>. Connecting shaft <b>472</b> may be one component or separate components and also interconnects the sun gear members <b>422</b> and <b>432</b>. The plurality of gear members <b>421</b> further include gear <b>453</b> which is connected for common rotation with the sleeve shaft <b>455</b> and rotates about countershaft <b>471</b>. Furthermore, the plurality of gear members <b>421</b> includes gear <b>443</b>, intermeshed with gear <b>453</b> and is connected for common rotation with sleeve shaft <b>445</b> and carrier <b>439</b>. Sleeve shaft <b>445</b> rotates about in a concentric with the connecting shaft <b>471</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0098" num="0097">The input shaft <b>17</b> is continuously connected with gear <b>463</b>. The output shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>429</b>. The interconnecting member <b>478</b> continuously connects the ring gear member <b>434</b> with the carrier member <b>429</b>. The connecting shaft or interconnecting member <b>472</b> continuously connects the sun gear members <b>422</b> and <b>432</b>. Gear <b>467</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear members <b>422</b> and <b>432</b> via the interconnecting member or connecting shaft <b>472</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0099" num="0098">The input member <b>17</b> is selectively connectable with gear <b>467</b>, and therefore with the connecting shaft <b>472</b>, via engagement of the clutch B which also connects gear <b>463</b> (via its hub portion <b>469</b>) to gear <b>467</b>. Gear <b>461</b> is selectively connectable with gear <b>441</b> via engagement of clutch C which interconnects the countershaft <b>470</b> with the sleeve shaft <b>468</b>. Ring gear member <b>424</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>480</b> via engagement of the brake MI. Gear <b>465</b> is selectively connectable with gear <b>453</b> via engagement of clutch MII which interconnects countershaft <b>471</b> with the sleeve shaft <b>455</b>. The carrier member <b>429</b> is selectively connectable with sun gear member <b>422</b> via engagement of the clutch MIII, which also interconnects with sun gear member <b>422</b> with the output member <b>19</b>. The carrier member <b>429</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>480</b> via engagement of the brake REV.</p>
<p id="p-0100" num="0099">As shown in the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>, the torque-transmitting mechanisms of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> (i.e., clutches B and C, clutch MII, clutch MIII and brakes MI and REV) are selectively engaged in combinations of two to provide seven forward speed ratios and two reverse speed ratios. The engagement schedule for the torque-transmitting mechanisms of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> is shown in the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> also provides an example of the torque ratios that are available using the following gear tooth counts and ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref>: gear <b>441</b> has 101 teeth, gear <b>467</b> has 75 teeth, gear <b>443</b> has 101 teeth, gear <b>453</b> has 75 teeth; planetary gear set <b>420</b> has a ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of 3.00 and the planetary gear set <b>430</b> has a ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of 3.80. The headset (gears <b>461</b> to <b>463</b> and <b>465</b> to <b>463</b>) has a 1.0 ratio.</p>
<p id="p-0101" num="0100">The first two forward speed ratios (corresponding with the first two listed forward torque ratios of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>) are first modal speed ratios (because the brake MI is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms B and C) establishing a first mode. The third forward speed ratio is a first transition speed ratio, (corresponding with a torque ratio of 2.188). The fourth forward speed ratio is a second modal speed ratio (because the clutch MII is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanism C) establishing a second mode. The fifth forward speed ratio is a second transition speed ratio (corresponding with a torque ratio of 1.347). The sixth and seventh forward speed ratios are third modal speed ratios (because the clutch MIII is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms B and C) establishing a third mode. The first through fifth forward speed ratios are underdrive ratios, the sixth forward speed ratio is a direct drive ratio and the seventh forward speed ratio is an overdrive ratio. Each of the forward speed ratios as well as the two reverse speed ratios involve singe transition shifts, are characterized by close ratio steps (listed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref>) and the first forward speed ratio as well as the first reverse speed ratio (corresponding with the torque ratio listed for R<b>1</b>) are deep start ratios.</p>
<p id="p-0102" num="0101">The transmission <b>414</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 9</figref> provides a lockout feature by engaging both the brake REV and the brake MI while on an incline. The lockout feature functions as described with respect to the transmission <b>214</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 5</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0103" num="0102">With respect to the claims, gear <b>463</b> is the first gear member, gear <b>468</b> is the second gear member, and gear <b>443</b> is the third gear member. Accordingly, the speed of the sun gear member <b>432</b> increases during the first mode, decreases during the second mode and increases again during the third mode. The connecting shaft or interconnecting member <b>472</b> is comparable to power flow path D, and the sleeve shaft <b>445</b> and gear <b>443</b> are comparable to power flow path E.</p>
<p id="p-0104" num="0103">As shown and described above for the transmission of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, those skilled in the art will understand from the chart from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 10</figref> how the torque ratios shown are established through the planetary gear sets <b>420</b> and <b>430</b> as well as the plurality of gear members <b>421</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0012" level="1">Fifth Transmission Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0105" num="0104"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> shows a powertrain <b>500</b> having an engine <b>12</b>, a transmission <b>514</b>, and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>514</b> may be characterized by a front section <b>11</b> and a rear section <b>15</b>. Transmission <b>514</b> includes an input shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected with the engine <b>12</b> via a torque converter <b>13</b> or via engagement of the torque converter lockup clutch <b>18</b> which effectively bypasses the torque converter <b>13</b>. The transmission <b>514</b> also includes an output shaft <b>19</b> continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. Transmission <b>514</b> includes four planetary gear sets, <b>520</b>, <b>530</b>, <b>540</b> and <b>550</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>540</b> and <b>550</b> partially define the front section <b>11</b> and the planetary gear sets <b>520</b> and <b>530</b> partially define the rear section <b>15</b>. Planetary gear set <b>520</b> is referred to in the claims as the first planetary gear set, and the planetary gear set <b>530</b> is referred to in the claims as the second planetary gear set. The planetary gear sets <b>540</b> and <b>550</b> are referred to in the claims as a plurality of gear members.</p>
<p id="p-0106" num="0105">Planetary gear set <b>520</b> includes a sun gear member <b>522</b>, a ring gear member <b>524</b> and carrier member <b>529</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>527</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>529</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>522</b> and the ring gear member <b>524</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0107" num="0106">Planetary gear set <b>530</b> includes a sun gear member <b>532</b>, a ring gear member <b>534</b> and a carrier member <b>539</b>. A plurality of pinion gear <b>537</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>539</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>532</b> and the ring gear member <b>534</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0108" num="0107">Planetary gear set <b>540</b> includes a sun gear member <b>542</b>, a ring gear member <b>544</b> and a carrier member <b>549</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>547</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>549</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>542</b> and the ring gear member <b>544</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0109" num="0108">The planetary gear set <b>550</b> includes a sun gear member <b>552</b>, a ring gear member <b>554</b> and a carrier member <b>559</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>557</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>559</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>552</b> and the ring gear member <b>554</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0110" num="0109">The input shaft <b>17</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>559</b> and therefore also to the ring gear member <b>544</b> via interconnecting member <b>570</b> which connects the carrier member <b>559</b> with the ring gear member <b>544</b>. The output shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>529</b> and therefore also with the ring gear member <b>534</b> which is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>529</b> via interconnecting member <b>578</b>. The ring gear member <b>554</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>532</b> and the sun gear member <b>522</b> via an interconnecting member <b>572</b> which may be one component or several components. The planetary gear sets <b>540</b> and <b>550</b> are referred to as a plurality of gear members within the claims. With respect to the claims, the first gear member of the plurality of gear members is carrier member <b>559</b>, the second gear member of the plurality of gear members is ring gear member <b>554</b>, and the third gear member of the plurality of gear members is carrier member <b>549</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0111" num="0110">The ring gear member <b>554</b> is selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>549</b> via engagement of the clutch A. The sun gear member <b>552</b> is selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>559</b>, and also with the ring gear member <b>554</b> via the interconnecting member <b>579</b>, via engagement of the clutch B. The sun gear member <b>552</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>580</b> via engagement of the brake C. The clutches A and B and the brake C are referred to herein as input torque-transmitting mechanisms. The ring gear member <b>524</b> is selectively connectable to the transmission housing <b>580</b> via engagement of the first modal torque-transmitting mechanism, brake MI. The carrier member <b>549</b> is selectively connectable with carrier member <b>539</b> via engagement of the second modal torque-transmitting mechanism, clutch MII. The carrier member <b>529</b> is selectively connectable with the sun gear member <b>522</b> via engagement of the third modal torque-transmitting mechanism, clutch MIII, and thereby also with the sun gear member <b>532</b> and the ring gear member <b>554</b> via the interconnecting member <b>572</b>. The carrier member <b>539</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>580</b> via engagement of the brake REV.</p>
<p id="p-0112" num="0111">Referring to the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>, the engagement schedule of the torque-transmitting mechanisms of the transmission <b>514</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref> to achieve eight forward speed ratios and three reverse speed ratios is provided. Torque ratios as well as ratio steps associated with the speed ratios are provided. A corresponding speed ratio is associated with each of numbers 1-8, R<b>1</b>, R<b>2</b> and R<b>3</b>. The first, second and third forward speed ratios are first modal speed ratios (because brake MI is engaged with the torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C) and establish a first mode. The fourth forward speed ratio is a first transition speed ratio. The fifth forward speed ratio is a second modal speed ratio because clutch MII is engaged with brake C and establishes a second mode. The sixth forward speed ratio is a second transition speed ratio. The seventh and eighth forward speed ratios are third modal speed ratios because clutch MIII is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms B and C to establish a third mode. The engagement schedule as pictured in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref> involves single transition shifts. Additionally, the first forward speed ratio as well as the reverse ratio R<b>1</b> provides a deep start ratio. The transmission <b>514</b> is designed to provide the close ratio steps listed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 12</figref>. The listed torque ratios and ratio steps result from the following ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the transmission <b>514</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 11</figref>: the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>520</b> is 3.0; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>530</b> is 3.8; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>540</b> is 2.88; and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>550</b> is 2.88. Application of the brake REV and the brake MI provides a lockout feature to prevent rotation of the output member <b>19</b> on steep grades. The lockout feature performs in the same manner as that described with respect to lockout feature of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<heading id="h-0013" level="1">Sixth Transmission Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0113" num="0112">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref>, another embodiment of a powertrain <b>600</b> having an engine <b>12</b>, a planetary transmission <b>614</b> and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b> is depicted. The transmission <b>614</b> includes an input shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected with the engine <b>12</b> either through a torque converter <b>13</b> or via engagement of a torque converter lockup clutch <b>18</b> with effectively bypasses the torque converter <b>13</b>. The transmission <b>614</b> further includes an output shaft <b>19</b> continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>614</b> includes a first planetary gear set <b>620</b> and a second planetary gear set <b>630</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>620</b> and <b>630</b> are within and partially define a rear section <b>15</b> of the transmission <b>614</b>. A front section <b>11</b> of the transmission <b>614</b> includes a plurality of gear members <b>621</b> as described below.</p>
<p id="p-0114" num="0113">The planetary gear set <b>620</b> includes a sun gear member <b>622</b>, a ring gear member <b>624</b> and a carrier member <b>629</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>627</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>629</b> and are disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>622</b> and the ring gear member <b>624</b>. The planetary gear set <b>620</b> is referred to in the claims as the first planetary gear set.</p>
<p id="p-0115" num="0114">The planetary gear set <b>630</b> includes a sun gear member <b>632</b>, a ring gear member <b>634</b> and a carrier member <b>639</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>637</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>639</b> and are disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>632</b> and the ring gear member <b>634</b>. The planetary gear set <b>630</b> is referred to in the claims as the second planetary gear set.</p>
<p id="p-0116" num="0115">The plurality of gear members <b>621</b> includes a head set comprised of gear <b>661</b>, gear <b>663</b> and gear <b>665</b>. The gear <b>663</b> has a hub portion <b>669</b> and is connected for common rotation with the input shaft <b>17</b>. Gear <b>661</b> intermeshes with gear <b>663</b> and is connected for common rotation with the countershaft <b>671</b>. Gear <b>665</b> intermeshes with gear <b>663</b> and is connected for common rotation with the countershaft <b>671</b>. Gear <b>663</b> is referred to in the claims as the first gear member of the plurality of gear members <b>621</b>. The plurality of gear members <b>621</b> further includes gear <b>641</b> which rotates about countershaft <b>670</b> on sleeve shaft <b>668</b>. Gear <b>641</b> intermeshes with gear <b>667</b> which is connected for common rotation with interconnecting member or shaft <b>672</b>. Connecting shaft <b>672</b> may be one component or separate components and also interconnects the sun gear members <b>622</b> and <b>632</b>. The plurality of gear members <b>621</b> also includes gear <b>653</b> which is connected for common rotation with countershaft <b>671</b>. Gear <b>653</b> intermeshes with gear <b>643</b>. The plurality of gear members <b>621</b> further includes <b>643</b> which intermeshes with gear <b>653</b> and is connected for common rotation with sleeve shaft <b>645</b>. Sleeve shaft <b>645</b> and gear <b>643</b> rotate about countershaft <b>672</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0117" num="0116">The input shaft <b>17</b> is continuously connected with gear <b>663</b>. The output shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>629</b>. The interconnecting member <b>678</b> continuously connects the ring gear member <b>634</b> with the carrier member <b>629</b>. The interconnecting member or connecting shaft <b>672</b> continuously connects the sun gear members <b>622</b> and <b>632</b> as well as the gear <b>667</b>. Gear <b>665</b> is connected for common rotation with gear <b>653</b> via the countershaft <b>671</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0118" num="0117">Gear <b>643</b> is selectively connectable with the sun gear members <b>622</b> and <b>632</b> via engagement of the clutch A which interconnects the interconnecting member or connecting shaft <b>672</b> with the sleeve shaft <b>645</b>. The input member <b>17</b> and gear <b>663</b> are selectively connectable with gear <b>667</b> via engagement of the clutch B which also connects gear <b>663</b> (via its hub portion <b>669</b>) to gear <b>667</b>. Gear <b>661</b> is selectively connectable with gear <b>641</b> via engagement of clutch C which interconnects the countershaft <b>670</b> with the sleeve shaft <b>668</b>. The ring gear member <b>624</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>680</b> via engagement of the brake MI. Gear <b>643</b> is selectively connectable with carrier member <b>639</b> via engagement of the clutch MII. The carrier member <b>629</b> is selectively connectable with the sun gear member <b>622</b> and thereby also with the sun gear member <b>632</b> and the gear <b>667</b>, via engagement of the clutch MIII. The carrier member <b>639</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>680</b> via engagement of the brake REV.</p>
<p id="p-0119" num="0118">As shown in the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>, the torque-transmitting mechanisms of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> (i.e., clutches A, B, C, clutches MII and MIII and brakes MI and REV) are selectively engagable in combinations of two to provide eight forward speed ratios and three reverse speed ratios (corresponding with the listed torque ratios). The engagement schedule for torque-transmitting mechanisms of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> is shown in the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> also provides an example of torque ratios using the following gear tooth counts and ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>: gear <b>653</b> has 75 teeth, gear <b>643</b> has 101 teeth, gear <b>667</b> has 75 teeth and gear <b>641</b> has 101 teeth; the planetary gear set <b>620</b> has a ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of 3.0 and the planetary gear set <b>630</b> has a ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of 3.8. The headset (gears <b>661</b>, <b>663</b> and <b>665</b>) has a 1.0 ratio.</p>
<p id="p-0120" num="0119">The first three forward speed ratios (corresponding with the first three forward torque ratios of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>) are first modal speed ratios (because brake MI is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C, in that order) establishing a first mode. The fourth forward speed ratio is the first transition speed ratio (corresponding with the torque ratio of 2.188). The fifth forward speed ratio is a second modal speed ratios (because the clutch MII is engaged with the clutch C) establishing a second mode. The sixth forward speed ratio is a second transition speed ratio (corresponding with a torque ratio 1.347). The seventh and eighth forward speed ratios are third modal speed ratios (because the clutch MIII is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms B and C, in that order) establishing a third mode. The first through sixth forward speed ratios are underdrive speed ratios, the seventh forward speed ratio is a direct drive ratio and the eighth forward speed ratio is an overdrive speed ratio. Each of the forward speed ratios as well as the three reverse speed ratios involve single transition shifts, are characterized by close ratio steps (listed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref>) and the first forward speed ratio as well the first reverse speed ratio (corresponding with the torque ratio listed at R<b>1</b>) are deep start ratios. The transmission <b>614</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 13</figref> provides a lockout feature by engaging both brake REV and brake MI while on an incline. The lockout feature (i.e., prevention of rotation of output shaft <b>19</b> by application of the brakes REV and MI) functions in the same manner as that described with respect to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0121" num="0120">With respect to the claims, the gear <b>663</b> is the first gear member of the plurality of gear members, gear <b>667</b> is the second gear member of the plurality of gear members, and gear <b>643</b> is the third gear member of the plurality of gear members. Accordingly, the speed of the sun gear member <b>632</b> increases during the first mode, decreases during the second mode, and increases again during the third mode. The interconnecting member <b>672</b> is comparable to power flow path D of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> and sleeve shaft <b>645</b> and gear <b>643</b> are comparable to power flow path E of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>.</p>
<p id="p-0122" num="0121">As shown and described above for the transmission of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, those skilled in the art will understand from the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 14</figref> how the torque ratios shown are established through the planetary gear sets <b>620</b> and <b>630</b> as well as the plurality of gear members <b>621</b>.</p>
<heading id="h-0014" level="1">Seventh Transmission Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0123" num="0122">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> shows a powertrain <b>700</b> having an engine <b>12</b>, a transmission <b>714</b> and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>714</b> may be characterized by a front section <b>11</b> and a rear section <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0124" num="0123">The transmission <b>714</b> includes an input shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected to the engine <b>12</b> either through a torque converter <b>13</b> or via engagement of the torque converter lockup clutch <b>18</b> which effectively bypasses the torque converter <b>13</b>. The transmission <b>714</b> also includes an output shaft <b>19</b> continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>714</b> includes five planetary gear sets <b>720</b>, <b>730</b>, <b>740</b>, <b>750</b> and <b>760</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>740</b>, <b>750</b> and <b>760</b> partially define the front section <b>11</b> and the planetary gear sets <b>720</b> and <b>730</b> partially define the rear section <b>15</b>. Planetary gear set <b>720</b> is referred to in the claims as the first planetary gear set, and the planetary gear set <b>730</b> is referred to in the claims as the second planetary gear set. The planetary gear sets <b>740</b>, <b>750</b> and <b>760</b> are referred to in the claims as a plurality of gear members.</p>
<p id="p-0125" num="0124">Planetary gear set <b>720</b> includes a sun gear member <b>722</b>, a ring gear member <b>724</b> and carrier member <b>729</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>727</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>729</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>722</b> and the ring gear member <b>724</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0126" num="0125">Planetary gear set <b>730</b> includes a sun gear member <b>732</b>, a ring gear member <b>734</b> and a carrier member <b>739</b>. A plurality of pinion gear <b>737</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>739</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>732</b> and the ring gear member <b>734</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0127" num="0126">Planetary gear set <b>740</b> includes a sun gear member <b>742</b>, a ring gear member <b>744</b> and a carrier member <b>749</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>747</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>749</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>742</b> and the ring gear member <b>744</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0128" num="0127">The planetary gear set <b>750</b> includes a sun gear member <b>752</b>, a ring gear member <b>754</b> and a carrier member <b>759</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>757</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>759</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>752</b> and the ring gear member <b>754</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0129" num="0128">The planetary gear set <b>760</b> includes a sun gear member <b>762</b>, a ring gear member <b>764</b> and a carrier member <b>769</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>767</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>769</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>762</b> and the ring gear member <b>764</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0130" num="0129">The input shaft <b>17</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>769</b> and therefore also with the ring gear member <b>754</b> via the interconnecting member <b>770</b>. The output shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>729</b> and therefore also with the carrier member <b>739</b> via the interconnecting member <b>768</b> which interconnects carrier member <b>739</b> with carrier member <b>729</b>. Ring gear member <b>764</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>722</b> via the interconnecting member <b>772</b> which may be one component or several components. The carrier member <b>759</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>744</b> via interconnecting member <b>774</b>. Carrier member <b>749</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>734</b> via the interconnecting member <b>776</b> which may be one component or several components. Sun gear member <b>732</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>724</b> via the interconnecting member <b>769</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>740</b>, <b>750</b> and <b>760</b> are referred to as a plurality of gear members within the claims.</p>
<p id="p-0131" num="0130">With respect to the claims, the first gear member of the plurality of gear members is carrier member <b>769</b>, the second gear member of the plurality of gear members is ring gear member <b>764</b>, and the third gear member of the plurality of gear members is carrier member <b>749</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0132" num="0131">The ring gear member <b>764</b> is selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>759</b> and the ring gear member <b>744</b> via the clutch A. The carrier member <b>769</b> is selectively connectable with the sun gear member <b>762</b> via engagement of the clutch B. The sun gear member <b>762</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>780</b> via engagement of the brake C. The ring gear member <b>724</b>, as well as the sun gear member <b>732</b> via the interconnecting member <b>769</b>, is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>780</b> via engagement of the brake MI. The sun gear member <b>742</b> is selectively connectable to the transmission housing <b>780</b> via engagement of the brake MII. The sun gear member <b>722</b> is selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>729</b> and therefore with the output member <b>19</b> via engagement of the clutch MIII. The ring gear member <b>734</b> is also selectively connectable to the transmission housing <b>780</b> via the brake REV.</p>
<p id="p-0133" num="0132">Referring to the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref>, the engagement schedule provided for the torque-transmitting mechanisms of the transmission <b>714</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> achieves nine forward speed ratios and three reverse speed ratios. Torque ratios as well as ratio steps associated with the speed ratios are listed. Speed ratios corresponding with the torque ratios are indicated by numbers 1-9, R<b>3</b>, R<b>2</b>, and R<b>1</b>. The first, second and third forward speed ratios are first modal speed ratios (because brake MI is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C) establishing a first mode. The fourth forward speed ratio establishes a first transition speed ratio. The fifth forward speed ratio is the second modal speed ratio (because brake MII is engaged with clutch C) to establish a second mode. The sixth forward speed ratio is the second transition speed ratio. The seventh, eighth and ninth forward speed ratios are the third modal speed ratios (because clutch MIII is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C) to establish a third mode. The engagement schedule depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref> involves single transition shifts. Additionally, the first forward speed ratio as well as the reverse speed ratio R<b>1</b> provide deep start ratios. The transmission <b>714</b> is designed to provide the close ratio steps listed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 16</figref>. Listed torque ratios and ratio steps result from the following ring gear/sun gear tooth ratios of the planetary transmission <b>714</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref>: the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>720</b> is 3.96; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>730</b> is 1.52; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>740</b> is 3.26; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>750</b> is 3.26; and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>760</b> is 2.88.</p>
<p id="p-0134" num="0133">Application of the brake REV and the brake MI provides a lockout feature to prevent rotation of the output member <b>19</b> on steep grades. Application of brake MI and brake REV ground both the ring gear member <b>734</b> and the sun gear member <b>732</b> of the planetary gear set <b>730</b> to the transmission housing <b>780</b>. This causes the entire planetary gear set <b>720</b> and planetary gear set <b>730</b> to be grounded.</p>
<heading id="h-0015" level="1">Eighth Transmission Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0135" num="0134"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> shows a powertrain <b>800</b> having an engine <b>12</b>, a transmission <b>814</b> and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>814</b> may be characterized by a front section <b>11</b> and a rear section <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0136" num="0135">The transmission <b>814</b> includes an input shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected with the engine <b>12</b> either through a torque converter <b>13</b> or via engagement of a torque converter lockup clutch <b>18</b> which effectively bypasses the torque converter <b>13</b>. The transmission <b>814</b> also includes an output shaft <b>19</b> continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>814</b> includes five planetary gear sets <b>820</b>, <b>830</b>, <b>840</b>, <b>850</b> and <b>860</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>840</b>, <b>850</b> and <b>860</b> partially define the front section <b>11</b> and the planetary gear sets <b>820</b> and <b>830</b> partially define the rear section <b>15</b>. The planetary gear set <b>820</b> is referred to in the claims as the first planetary gear set and the planetary gear set <b>830</b> is referred to in the claims as the second planetary gear set. The planetary gear sets <b>840</b>, <b>850</b> and <b>860</b> are referred to in the claims as a plurality of gear members.</p>
<p id="p-0137" num="0136">Planetary gear set <b>820</b> includes a sun gear member <b>822</b>, a ring gear member <b>824</b> and carrier member <b>829</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>827</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>829</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>822</b> and the ring gear member <b>824</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0138" num="0137">Planetary gear set <b>830</b> includes a sun gear member <b>832</b>, a ring gear member <b>834</b> and a carrier member <b>839</b>. A plurality of pinion gear <b>837</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>839</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>832</b> and the ring gear member <b>834</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0139" num="0138">Planetary gear set <b>840</b> includes a sun gear member <b>842</b>, a ring gear member <b>844</b> and a carrier member <b>849</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>847</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>849</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>842</b> and the ring gear member <b>844</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0140" num="0139">The planetary gear set <b>850</b> includes a sun gear member <b>852</b>, a ring gear member <b>854</b> and a carrier member <b>859</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>857</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>859</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>852</b> and the ring gear member <b>854</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0141" num="0140">The planetary gear set <b>860</b> includes a sun gear member <b>862</b>, a ring gear member <b>864</b> and a carrier member <b>869</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>867</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>869</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>862</b> and the ring gear member <b>864</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0142" num="0141">The input shaft <b>17</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>869</b> (and therefore also with the ring gear member <b>854</b> via the interconnecting member <b>870</b> which connects the carrier member <b>869</b> and the ring gear member <b>854</b>). The output shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>829</b>. The ring gear member <b>864</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>832</b> via the interconnecting member <b>872</b> which may be one component or separate components. The carrier member <b>859</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>844</b> via the interconnecting member <b>874</b>. The sun gear <b>852</b> is continuously connected to the housing <b>880</b>. The carrier member <b>849</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>839</b> via the interconnecting member <b>876</b>. The ring gear member <b>834</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>822</b> via the interconnecting member <b>878</b>. The carrier member <b>839</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>824</b> via the interconnecting member <b>879</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>840</b>, <b>850</b> and <b>860</b> are referred to as a plurality of gear members within the claims.</p>
<p id="p-0143" num="0142">With respect to the claims, the first gear member of the plurality of gear members is the carrier member <b>869</b>, the second gear member of the plurality of gear members is the ring gear member <b>864</b>, and the third gear member of the plurality of gear members is the carrier member <b>849</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0144" num="0143">The ring gear member <b>864</b> is selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>859</b> via the engagement of the clutch A. The sun gear member <b>862</b> is selectively connectable with the carrier member <b>869</b> via engagement of the clutch B. The sun gear member <b>862</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>880</b> via engagement of the brake C. The ring gear member <b>834</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>880</b> via engagement of the brake MI. The sun gear member <b>842</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>880</b> via engagement of the brake MII. The carrier member <b>849</b> is selectively connectable with the sun gear member <b>832</b> via engagement of the clutch MIII. The clutch MIII also connects the carrier member <b>839</b> with the sun gear member <b>832</b>. The carrier member <b>839</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>880</b> via engagement of the brake REV. This also connects the carrier member <b>849</b> and the ring gear member <b>824</b> with the transmission housing <b>880</b> via the interconnecting members <b>876</b> and <b>879</b>, respectively.</p>
<p id="p-0145" num="0144">Referring to the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref>, the engagement schedule for the torque-transmitting mechanisms of the transmission <b>814</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> to achieve nine forward speed ratios and three reverse speed ratios is provided. Torque ratios as well as ratio steps associated with the speed ratios are listed. Speed ratios corresponding with the torque ratios are indicated by the numbers 1-9, R<b>3</b>, R<b>2</b>, and R<b>1</b>. The first, second and third forward speed ratios are first modal speed ratios (because the brake MI is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C) to establish a first mode. The fourth forward speed ratio is a first transition speed ratio. The fifth forward speed ratio is a second modal speed ratio because brake MII is engaged with brake C thereby establishing a second mode. The sixth forward speed ratio is a second transition speed ratio. The seven, eighth and ninth forward speed ratios are third modal speed ratios (because the clutch MIII is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C) to establish the third mode. The engagement schedule depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref> involves single transition shifts. Additionally, the first forward ratio as well as the first reverse speed ratio provide a deep start ratio. Transmission <b>814</b> is designed to provide the close ratio steps listed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 18</figref>. The listed torque ratios and ratio steps result from the following ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the transmission <b>814</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>: the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>820</b> is 1.46; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>830</b> is 2.06; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>840</b> is 3.26; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>850</b> is 3.26; and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>860</b> is 3.26.</p>
<p id="p-0146" num="0145">In the transmission <b>814</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref>, application of the brake REV and the brake MI provides a lockout feature to prevent rotation of the output member <b>19</b> on steep grades. Application of the brake MI prevents rotation of the ring gear member <b>834</b> and the sun gear member <b>822</b>. Application of the brake REV grounds the carrier member <b>839</b>, the ring gear member <b>834</b> and the carrier member <b>849</b> to the transmission housing <b>880</b>. Because two members of planetary gear set <b>830</b> are held stationary, and these members interconnect with two different member of the planetary gear set <b>820</b>, the entire planetary gear set <b>820</b> and the entire planetary gear set <b>830</b> are held stationary. Thus, when both the brake MI and REV are applied, the entire planetary gear sets <b>820</b> and <b>830</b> are held stationary, which prevents rotation of the output member <b>19</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0147" num="0146"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 2</figref>, <b>5</b>, <b>7</b>, <b>9</b>, <b>11</b>, <b>13</b>, <b>17</b> and <b>23</b> involve a similar output section <b>15</b> referred to as a first output version. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 15</figref> depicts a rear section <b>15</b> referred to as a second output version. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 17</figref> depicts a rear section <b>15</b> arranged as a third output version. <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref> depicts a fourth output version, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 20</figref> depicts a fifth output version, <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 21</figref> depicts a sixth output version and <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 22</figref> depicts a sixth output version.</p>
<heading id="h-0016" level="1">Fourth Output Section Embodiment (Ninth Transmission Embodiment)</heading>
<p id="p-0148" num="0147">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref>, another embodiment of an output or rear section <b>15</b> of a transmission within the scope of the invention is depicted. The rear section <b>15</b> includes a first planetary gear set <b>920</b> and a second planetary gear set <b>930</b>. The first planetary gear set <b>920</b> includes a sun gear member <b>922</b>, ring gear member <b>924</b> and a carrier member <b>929</b> that rotatably supports a plurality of pinion gear members <b>927</b> that are disposed in meshing engagement with both the sun gear member <b>922</b> and the ring gear member <b>924</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0149" num="0148">The planetary gear set <b>930</b> includes a sun gear member <b>932</b>, a ring gear member <b>934</b> and a carrier member <b>939</b> that rotatably supports a plurality of pinion gears <b>937</b> that are disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>932</b> and the ring gear member <b>934</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0150" num="0149">The carrier member <b>929</b> is continuously connected with the output member <b>19</b> which is continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The sun gear member <b>932</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>922</b> via the interconnecting member <b>972</b>. The carrier member <b>939</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>924</b> via the interconnecting member <b>978</b>. Various input torque-transmitting mechanisms including clutches A, B and C in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of embodiments described herein are selectively engagable to provide power flow at the ring gear member <b>934</b>. Power flow to the ring gear member <b>934</b> is along path D of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. Similarly, a second modal torque-transmitting mechanism, clutch MII in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of the embodiments described herein is selectively engagable to provide power flow to the carrier member <b>939</b> and also to the ring gear member <b>924</b> via the interconnecting member <b>978</b>. Power flow to the carrier member <b>939</b> is along path E of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A first modal torque-transmitting mechanism, the brake MI, is selectively engagable to connect the sun gear members <b>922</b> and <b>932</b> to the transmission housing <b>980</b>. A third modal torque-transmitting mechanism, clutch MIII, is selectively engagable to connect the carrier member <b>929</b> with the ring gear member <b>924</b>. A brake REV is selectively engagable to connect carrier member <b>939</b> with the transmission housing <b>980</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0151" num="0150">Application of both the brake MI and the brake REV provides a lockout feature to prevent the output member <b>19</b> from rotating on steep grades. By holding the sun gear member <b>922</b> stationary via application of the brake MI and by holding the ring gear member <b>924</b> stationary via application of the brake REV, the entire planetary gear set <b>920</b> is held stationary including the carrier member <b>929</b>, thereby holding the output member <b>19</b> stationary as well.</p>
<heading id="h-0017" level="1">Fifth Output Section Embodiment (Tenth Transmission Embodiment)</heading>
<p id="p-0152" num="0151">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 19</figref>, another embodiment of an output or rear section <b>15</b> for a transmission within the scope of the invention is illustrated. The rear section <b>15</b> includes both a first planetary gear set <b>1020</b> and a second planetary gear set <b>1030</b>. The first planetary gear set <b>1020</b> includes a sun gear member <b>1022</b>, a ring gear member <b>1024</b> and a carrier member <b>1029</b> rotatably supporting a plurality of pinion gear members <b>1027</b> disposed in meshing relationship with both sun gear member <b>1022</b> and ring gear member <b>1024</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0153" num="0152">The planetary gear set <b>1030</b> includes sun gear member <b>1032</b>, a ring gear member <b>1034</b>, and a carrier member <b>1039</b> rotatably supporting a plurality of pinion gears <b>1037</b> disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>1032</b> and the ring gear member <b>1034</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0154" num="0153">The carrier member <b>1029</b> is continuously connected with the output member <b>19</b> which is continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The sun gear member <b>1022</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>1032</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1072</b>. The ring gear member <b>1024</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>1034</b> via an interconnecting member <b>1078</b>. Input torque-transmitting mechanisms A, B and C (or at least two thereof) in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of embodiments described herein are selectively engagable to establish power flow at the sun gear member <b>1032</b> (and therefore the sun gear member <b>1022</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1072</b>). Power flow to the sun gear member <b>1032</b> is along path D of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A second modal torque-transmitting mechanism, clutch MII in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of the embodiments described herein, is selectively engagable to establish power flow at the carrier member <b>1039</b>. Power flow to the carrier member <b>1039</b> is along path E of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A first modal torque-transmitting mechanism, the brake MI is selectively engagable to connect the ring gear members <b>1024</b> and <b>1034</b> with a transmission housing <b>1080</b>. A third modal torque-transmitting mechanism MIII is selectively engagable to connect the carrier member <b>1029</b> with the sun gear member <b>1022</b>. Engagement of both the brake MI and reverse brake REV prevents rotation of the output member <b>19</b> to provide a lockout feature on steep grades. The brake MI prevents rotation of both of the ring gear members <b>1024</b> and <b>1034</b>. The brake REV prevents rotation of the carrier member <b>1039</b>. Because neither the ring gear member <b>1034</b> nor the carrier member <b>1039</b> rotate, the sun gear member <b>1032</b> is also held stationary. The interconnecting member <b>1072</b> thus ensures that the sun gear member <b>1022</b> is held stationary. Because both the sun gear member <b>1022</b> and the ring gear member <b>1024</b> are stationary, the carrier member <b>1029</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b> are stationary.</p>
<heading id="h-0018" level="1">Sixth Output Section Embodiment (Eleventh Transmission Embodiment)</heading>
<p id="p-0155" num="0154">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 21</figref>, another embodiment of an output or rear section <b>15</b> for a transmission within the scope of the invention is illustrated. The rear section <b>15</b> includes both a first planetary gear set <b>1120</b> and a second planetary gear set <b>1130</b>. The first planetary gear set <b>1120</b> includes a sun gear member <b>1122</b>, a ring gear member <b>1124</b> and a carrier member <b>1129</b> rotatably supporting a plurality of pinion gear members <b>1127</b> disposed in meshing relationship with both sun gear member <b>1122</b> and ring gear member <b>1124</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0156" num="0155">The planetary gear set <b>1130</b> includes sun gear member <b>1132</b>, a ring gear member <b>1134</b>, and a carrier member <b>1139</b> rotatably supporting a plurality of pinion gears <b>1137</b> disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>1132</b> and the ring gear member <b>1134</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0157" num="0156">The ring gear member <b>1124</b> is continuously connected with the output member <b>19</b> which is continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The carrier member <b>1139</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>1129</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1172</b>. The sun gear member <b>1122</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>1132</b> via an interconnecting member <b>1178</b>. Input torque-transmitting mechanism B in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of embodiments discussed herein is selectively engagable to establish power flow at the carrier member <b>1129</b> (and therefore the carrier member <b>1139</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1172</b>). Input torque-transmitting mechanism C in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of embodiments discussed herein is selectively engagable to establish power flow at the sun gear member <b>1132</b> (and therefore the sun gear member <b>1122</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1178</b>). Power flow to the carrier member <b>1129</b> or to the sun gear member <b>1132</b> is along the path D of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A second modal torque-transmitting mechanism, MII in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of the embodiments discussed herein, is selectively engagable to establish power flow at the carrier member <b>1139</b>. Power flow to the carrier member <b>1139</b> is along path E of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A first modal torque-transmitting mechanism, the brake MI is selectively engagable to connect the ring gear member <b>1134</b> with a transmission housing <b>1180</b>. A third modal torque-transmitting mechanism MIII is selectively engagable to connect the carrier member <b>1129</b> with the ring gear member <b>1124</b>. Engagement of both the brake MI and reverse brake REV prevents rotation of the output member <b>19</b> to provide a lockout feature on steep grades. The brake MI prevents rotation of ring gear members <b>1134</b>. The brake REV prevents rotation of the carrier member <b>1139</b>. Because neither the ring gear member <b>1134</b> nor the carrier member <b>1139</b> rotate, the sun gear member <b>1132</b> is also held stationary. The interconnecting members <b>1172</b> and <b>1178</b> thus ensure that the sun gear member <b>1122</b> and the carrier member <b>1129</b> are held stationary. Because both the sun gear member <b>1122</b> and the carrier member <b>1129</b> are stationary, the ring gear member <b>1124</b>, and therefore the output member <b>19</b> are stationary.</p>
<heading id="h-0019" level="1">Seventh Output Section Embodiment (Twelfth Transmission Embodiment)</heading>
<p id="p-0158" num="0157">Referring to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 22</figref>, another embodiment of an output or rear section <b>15</b> for a transmission within the scope of the invention is illustrated. The rear section <b>15</b> includes both a first planetary gear set <b>1220</b> and a second planetary gear set <b>1230</b>. The first planetary gear set <b>1220</b> includes a sun gear member <b>1222</b>, a ring gear member <b>1224</b> and a carrier member <b>1229</b> rotatably supporting a plurality of pinion gear members <b>1227</b> disposed in meshing relationship with both sun gear member <b>1222</b> and ring gear member <b>1224</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0159" num="0158">The planetary gear set <b>1230</b> includes sun gear member <b>1232</b>, a ring gear member <b>1234</b>, and a carrier member <b>1239</b> rotatably supporting a plurality of pinion gears <b>1237</b> disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>1232</b> and the ring gear member <b>1234</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0160" num="0159">The ring gear member <b>1224</b> is continuously connected with the output member <b>19</b> which is continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The ring gear member <b>1234</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>1229</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1272</b>. The carrier member <b>1239</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>1224</b> via an interconnecting member <b>1278</b>. Input torque-transmitting mechanism B in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of embodiments described herein is selectively engagable to establish power flow at the carrier member <b>1229</b> (and therefore the ring gear member <b>1234</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1272</b>). Input torque-transmitting mechanism C in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of embodiments discussed herein is selectively engagable to establish power flow at the sun gear member <b>1222</b>. Power flow to the carrier member <b>1229</b> or to the sun gear member <b>1222</b> is along path D of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A second modal torque-transmitting mechanism, MII is in any of the input sections <b>11</b> of the embodiments described herein, is selectively engagable to establish power flow at the carrier member <b>1229</b> and therefore the ring gear member <b>1234</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1272</b>. Power flow from the MII input to the carrier member <b>1229</b> is along path E of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>. A first modal torque-transmitting mechanism, the brake MI is selectively engagable to connect the sun gear member <b>1232</b> with a transmission housing <b>1280</b>. A third modal torque-transmitting mechanism MIII is selectively engagable to connect the carrier member <b>1229</b> with the ring gear member <b>1224</b>. Engagement of both the brake MI and reverse brake REV prevents rotation of the output member <b>19</b> to provide a lockout feature on steep grades. The brake MI prevents rotation of the sun gear member <b>1232</b>. The brake REV prevents rotation of both the carrier member <b>1229</b> and the ring gear members <b>1234</b> and <b>1224</b>. Therefore, the output member <b>19</b> is stationary.</p>
<heading id="h-0020" level="1">Thirteenth Transmission Embodiment</heading>
<p id="p-0161" num="0160"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref> shows a powertrain <b>1300</b> having an engine <b>12</b>, a transmission <b>1314</b> and a final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>1314</b> may be characterized by a front section <b>11</b> and a rear section <b>15</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0162" num="0161">The transmission <b>1314</b> includes an input shaft <b>17</b> continuously connected with the engine <b>12</b> either through a torque converter <b>13</b> or via engagement of a torque converter lockup clutch <b>18</b> which effectively bypasses the torque converter <b>13</b>. The transmission <b>1314</b> also includes an output shaft <b>19</b> continuously connected with the final drive mechanism <b>16</b>. The transmission <b>1314</b> includes four planetary gear sets <b>1320</b>, <b>1330</b>, <b>1340</b>, and <b>1350</b>. The planetary gear sets <b>1340</b> and <b>1350</b> partially define the front section <b>11</b> and the planetary gear sets <b>1320</b> and <b>1330</b> partially define the rear section <b>15</b>. The planetary gear set <b>1320</b> is referred to in the claims as the first planetary gear set and the planetary gear set <b>1330</b> is referred to in the claims as the second planetary gear set. The planetary gear sets <b>1340</b> and <b>1350</b> are referred to in the claims as a plurality of gear members.</p>
<p id="p-0163" num="0162">Planetary gear set <b>1320</b> includes a sun gear member <b>1322</b>, a ring gear member <b>1324</b> and carrier member <b>1329</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>1327</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>1329</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>1322</b> and the ring gear member <b>1324</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0164" num="0163">Planetary gear set <b>1330</b> includes a sun gear member <b>1332</b>, a ring gear member <b>1334</b> and a carrier member <b>1339</b>. A plurality of pinion gear <b>1337</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>1339</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>1332</b> and the ring gear member <b>1334</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0165" num="0164">Planetary gear set <b>1340</b> includes a sun gear member <b>1342</b>, a ring gear member <b>1344</b> and a carrier member <b>1349</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>1347</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>1349</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>1342</b> and the ring gear member <b>1344</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0166" num="0165">The planetary gear set <b>1350</b> includes a sun gear member <b>1352</b>, a ring gear member <b>1354</b> and a carrier member <b>1359</b>. A plurality of pinion gears <b>1357</b> are rotatably supported on the carrier member <b>1359</b> and disposed in meshing relationship with both the sun gear member <b>1352</b> and the ring gear member <b>1354</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0167" num="0166">The input shaft <b>17</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>1354</b>. The output shaft <b>19</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>1329</b> and therefore also with the ring gear member <b>1334</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1378</b>. The carrier member <b>1359</b> is continuously connected with the ring gear member <b>1344</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1370</b>. The sun gear <b>1352</b> is continuously connected to the housing <b>1380</b>. The carrier member <b>1349</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>1339</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1376</b>. The ring gear member <b>1334</b> is continuously connected with the carrier member <b>1329</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1378</b>. The sun gear member <b>1332</b> is continuously connected with the sun gear member <b>1322</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1379</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0168" num="0167">With respect to the claims, the first gear member of the plurality of gear members is the ring gear member <b>1354</b>, the second gear member of the plurality of gear members is the carrier member <b>1349</b>, and the third gear member of the plurality of gear members is the ring gear member <b>1344</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0169" num="0168">The carrier member <b>1359</b> and the ring gear member <b>1344</b> are selectively connectable with the sun gear members <b>1322</b> and <b>1332</b> via engagement of the clutch B. The ring gear member <b>1354</b> is selectively connectable with the sun gear members <b>1322</b> and <b>1332</b> via engagement of the clutch C. The ring gear member <b>1324</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>1380</b> via engagement of the brake MI. The sun gear member <b>1342</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>1380</b> via engagement of the brake MII. The carrier member <b>1349</b> is selectively connectable with the sun gear members <b>1322</b> and <b>1332</b> as well as the carrier member <b>1339</b> via engagement of the clutch MIII. The carrier member <b>1339</b> is selectively connectable with the transmission housing <b>1380</b> via engagement of the brake REV. This also connects the carrier member <b>1349</b> with the transmission housing <b>1380</b> via the interconnecting member <b>1376</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0170" num="0169">Referring to the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 24</figref>, the engagement schedule for the torque-transmitting mechanisms of the transmission <b>1314</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref> to achieve seven forward speed ratios and two reverse speed ratios is provided. Torque ratios as well as ratio steps associated with the speed ratios are listed. Speed ratios are indicated by the numbers 1-7, R<b>2</b> and R<b>1</b>. The first and second forward speed ratios are first modal speed ratios (because the brake MI is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms B and C, respectively) to establish a first mode. The third forward speed ratio is a first transition speed ratio. The fourth forward speed ratio is a second modal speed ratio because brake MII is engaged with clutch C thereby establishing a second mode. The fifth forward speed ratio is a second transition speed ratio. The sixth and seventh forward speed ratios are third modal speed ratios (because the clutch MIII is engaged with the input torque-transmitting mechanisms B and C, respectively) to establish the third mode. The engagement schedule depicted in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref> involves single transition shifts. Additionally, the first forward ratio as well as the first reverse speed ratio provide a deep start ratio. Also, the highest speed ratio (indicated at <b>7</b> in the chart of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 24</figref>) is a direct ratio. Thus, seven forward speed ratios are provided with low internal speeds, as there are no overdrive ratios. Transmission <b>1314</b> is designed to provide the close ratio steps listed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 24</figref>. The listed torque ratios and ratio steps result from the following ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the transmission <b>1314</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref>: the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>1320</b> is 3.0; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>1330</b> is 3.8; the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>1340</b> is 2.88; and the ring gear/sun gear tooth ratio of the planetary gear set <b>1350</b> is 2.88.</p>
<p id="p-0171" num="0170">In the transmission <b>1314</b> of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 23</figref>, application of the brake REV and the brake MI provides a lockout feature to prevent rotation of the output member <b>19</b> on steep grades. The lockout feature functions in the same manner as that described with respect to the lockout feature of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref></p>
<p id="p-0172" num="0171">While the best modes for carrying out the invention have been described in detail, those familiar with the art to which this invention relates will recognize various alternative designs and embodiments for practicing the invention within the scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. An automatic transmission comprising:
<claim-text>first and second planetary gear sets each having a first member, a second member and a third member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first modal torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect one of said members of said first planetary gear set with a stationary member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second modal torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to establish power flow to a member of said second planetary gear set;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third modal torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect any two members of one of said first and second planetary gear sets; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first and a second input torque-transmitting mechanism separately selectively engagable to establish power flow at a different member of one of said first and second planetary gear sets than said member of said second planetary gear set at which power flow is established via engagement of said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a speed of said different member (i) increases as said first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engaged in successive order while said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged, (ii) then decreases as at least one of the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms is engaged while said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged, and (iii) then increases as the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engaged in successive order while said third modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged, respectively.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said first member of said first planetary gear set is continuously connected with said first member of said second planetary gear set, wherein said second member of said first planetary gear set is continuously connected with said second member of said second planetary gear set; and
<claim-text>wherein said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is selectively engagable to connect one of said second and third members of said first planetary gear set with said stationary member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a reverse torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect one of said members of said second planetary gear set with said stationary member;
<claim-text>wherein said first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engagable in successive order while said reverse torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish different reverse speed ratios between an input member and a output member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein engagement of both said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism and said reverse torque-transmitting mechanism prevents rotation of said output member, thus preventing rolling on steep grades.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>an input member; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engagable in successive order while said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish respectively increasing first modal speed ratios between said input member and said output member, in reverse order while said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish respectively increasing second modal speed ratios between said input member and said output member, and in successive order while said third modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish respectively increasing third modal speed ratios between said input member and said output member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said first and said second modal torque-transmitting mechanisms are simultaneously engagable to establish a first transition speed ratio between said input member and said output member, with a single transition shift between said first transition speed ratio and both of said first and second modal speed ratios, said first transition speed ratio having a numerical value greater than said first modal speed ratios and less than said second modal speed ratios.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism and said third modal torque-transmitting mechanism are simultaneously engagable to establish a second transition speed ratio between said input member and said output member, with a single transition shift between said second transition speed ratio and both of said second and third modal speed ratios, said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism having a numerical value greater than said second modal speed ratios and less than said third modal speed ratios.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a third input torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to establish power flow at said different member of one of said first and second planetary gear sets;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said third input torque-transmitting mechanism is engagable with said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism to establish another first modal speed ratio, with said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism to establish another second modal speed ratio and with said third modal torque-transmitting mechanism to establish another third modal speed ratio; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said another first modal speed ratio is less than all of said second modal speed ratios and said another second modal speed ratio is less than all of said third modal speed ratios.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. An automatic transmission comprising:
<claim-text>an input member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>an output member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>first and second planetary gear sets each having a first member, a second member and a third member; wherein one of said members of said first planetary gear set is continuously connected with said output member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a plurality of gear members including a first gear member continuously connected with said input member, a second gear member continuously connected with one of said members of one of said first and second planetary gear sets, and a third gear member continuously connected or selectively connectable with a different one of said members of one of said first and second planetary gear sets;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first modal torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect one of said members of said first planetary gear set with a stationary member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second modal torque-transmitting mechanism;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third modal torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect any two of said members of one of said first and said second planetary gear sets; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first and a second input torque-transmitting mechanism each separately selectively engagable to connect a respective different one of said plurality of gear members with another one of said plurality of gear members, with said input shaft or with a stationary member, said first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms being engagable in successive order while said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish respectively increasing first modal speed ratios between said input member and said output member, one of which is engagable while said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish a second modal speed ratio, or both of which are engagable in reverse order while said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish respectively increasing second modal speed ratios between said input member and said output member, and being engagable in successive order while said third modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish respectively increasing third modal speed ratios between said input member and said output member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein a speed of said member of one of said first and second planetary gear sets continuously connected with said second gear member increases during successive first modal speed ratios, decreases during successive second modal speed ratios and increases during successive third modal speed ratios.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said first and said second modal torque-transmitting mechanisms are simultaneously engagable to establish a first transition speed ratio between said input member and said output member, with a single transition shift between said first transition speed ratio and both of said first and second modal speed ratios, and having a numerical value greater than said first modal speed ratios and less than said second modal speed ratios.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism and said third modal torque-transmitting mechanism are simultaneously engagable to establish a second transition speed ratio between said input member and said output member, with a single transition shift between said second transition speed ratio and both of said second and third modal speed ratios, and having a numerical value greater than said second modal speed ratios and less than said third modal speed ratios.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said first member of said first planetary gear set is continuously connected with said first member of said second planetary gear set, wherein said second member of said first planetary gear set is continuously connected with said second member of said second planetary gear set; and
<claim-text>wherein said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is selectively engagable to connect one of said second and third members of said first planetary gear set with said stationary member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a third input torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect a respective different one of said plurality of gears members than that connected via engagement of said first or said second torque-transmitting mechanism with another one of said plurality of gear members, with said input shaft or with said stationary member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said third input torque-transmitting mechanism is engagable with said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism to establish another first modal ratio, with said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism to establish another second modal speed ratio and with said third modal torque-transmitting mechanism to establish another third modal speed ratio; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said another first modal speed ratio is less than all of said second modal speed ratios, and wherein said another second modal speed ratio is less than all of said third modal speed ratios.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>a reverse torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect one of said members of said second planetary gear set with said stationary member; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engagable in successive order while said reverse torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish different reverse speed ratios between said input member and said output member.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00015">claim 15</claim-ref>, wherein engagement of both of said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism and said reverse torque-transmitting mechanism prevents rotation of said output member, thus preventing rolling on steep grades.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00017" num="00017">
<claim-text>17. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein said plurality of gear members include at least two additional planetary gear sets.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00018" num="00018">
<claim-text>18. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, further comprising:
<claim-text>at least one countershaft offset from said input and output members, wherein at least some of said plurality of gear members are connected for common rotation with said countershaft.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00019" num="00019">
<claim-text>19. The transmission of <claim-ref idref="CLM-00009">claim 9</claim-ref>, wherein a highest of said third modal speed ratios is a direct drive ratio.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00020" num="00020">
<claim-text>20. An automatic transmission comprising:
<claim-text>first and second planetary gear sets each having a first member, a second member and a third member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first modal torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect one of said members of said first planetary gear set with a stationary member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a second modal torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to establish power flow to a member of said second planetary gear set;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a third modal torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect any two members of one of said first and second planetary gear sets;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a first and a second input torque-transmitting mechanism separately selectively engagable to establish power flow at a different member of one of said first and second planetary gear sets than said member of said second planetary gear set at which power flow is established via engagement of said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a reverse torque-transmitting mechanism selectively engagable to connect one of said members of said second planetary gear set with said stationary member;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein a speed of said different member (i) increases as said first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engaged in successive order while said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged, (ii) then decreases as at least one of the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms is engaged while said second modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged, and (iii) then increases as the first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engaged in successive order while said third modal torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged, respectively;</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein said first and second input torque-transmitting mechanisms are engagable in successive order while said reverse torque-transmitting mechanism is also engaged to establish different reverse speed ratios between said input member and said output member; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein engagement of both said first modal torque-transmitting mechanism and said reverse torque-transmitting mechanism prevents rotation of said output member, thus preventing rolling on steep grades.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
