<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07296643-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07296643</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>10501993</doc-number>
<date>20030122</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>10</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>SE</country>
<doc-number>0200201</doc-number>
<date>20020122</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<us-term-of-grant>
<us-term-extension>182</us-term-extension>
</us-term-of-grant>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>B</section>
<class>60</class>
<subclass>K</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>02</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 651</main-classification>
<further-classification>280  658</further-classification>
<further-classification>280 21</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e71">Drive unit, and a powered vehicle</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3404746</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Slay</name>
<date>19681000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>3912037</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Krieg</name>
<date>19751000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4044853</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Melke</name>
<date>19770800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4221273</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Finden</name>
<date>19800900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180  648</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4463821</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Falamak</name>
<date>19840800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180168</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4529052</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Imai et al.</name>
<date>19850700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180  648</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00007">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4533998</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Falamak</name>
<date>19850800</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>701 50</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00008">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>4733737</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Falamak</name>
<date>19880300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180  71</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00009">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5379842</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Terry</name>
<date>19950100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180 21</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00010">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5432416</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Tae-Sig</name>
<date>19950700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00011">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5456332</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Borenstein</name>
<date>19951000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00012">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5823884</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Ager</name>
<date>19981000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>472 77</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00013">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>5924512</doc-number>
<kind>A</kind>
<name>Wada</name>
<date>19990700</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00014">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6948576</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Angeles</name>
<date>20050900</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>180 23</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>16</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180167</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 62</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180  658</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 651</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 21</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 22</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180 23</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>180908</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>2</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>3</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050061560</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20050324</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Philipson</last-name>
<first-name>Niklas</first-name>
<address>
<city>Stockholm</city>
<country>SE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>SE</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>SE</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Nison &amp; Vanderhye P.C.</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Visual Act Scandinavia AB</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Saltsjo-Boo</city>
<country>SE</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Ellis</last-name>
<first-name>Christopher P.</first-name>
<department>3618</department>
</primary-examiner>
<assistant-examiner>
<last-name>Swenson</last-name>
<first-name>Brian</first-name>
</assistant-examiner>
</examiners>
<pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>PCT/SE03/00109</doc-number>
<kind>00</kind>
<date>20030122</date>
</document-id>
<us-371c124-date>
<date>20041123</date>
</us-371c124-date>
</pct-or-regional-filing-data>
<pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
<document-id>
<country>WO</country>
<doc-number>WO03/062007</doc-number>
<kind>A </kind>
<date>20030731</date>
</document-id>
</pct-or-regional-publishing-data>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">The present invention relates to a drive unit (<b>10</b>) comprising a rolling means (<b>12</b>) intended to be infrictional engagement with a surface over which said drive unit (<b>10</b>) is intended to move. The drive unit (<b>10</b>) also comprises a first driving means (<b>14</b>) and a second driving means (<b>16</b>), co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit (<b>10</b>) while eliminating slippage between said rolling means (<b>12</b>) and said surface. The first driving means (<b>14</b>) is arranged on a rotatable support means (<b>18</b>) rotatable about a center axis (c.a.) and is operable to rotate said rolling (<b>12</b>) about a roling axis. rolling means (<b>12</b>) is displaced a predetermined distance from said center axis (c.a.), and the second driving means (<b>16</b>) is operable rotate the support means (<b>18</b>) about said center axis (c.a.).</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="123.61mm" wi="307.76mm" file="US07296643-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="220.73mm" wi="161.88mm" file="US07296643-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="240.96mm" wi="164.93mm" orientation="landscape" file="US07296643-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">This application is the US national phase of international application PCT/SE03/00109 filed 22 Jan. 2003, which designated the US and claims priority to SE Application No. 0200201-2, filed 22 Jan. 2002. The entire contents of these applications are incorporated herein by reference.</p>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">The present invention relates in a first aspect to a drive unit.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">In a second aspect the present invention relates to a powered vehicle.</p>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">DESCRIPTION OF THE RELATED ART</heading>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The theatre has automated much of the equipment used for the movement of scenery and lighting. Most of stage activity involves simply moving scenery about the stage. Automated systems for doing this have been limited by poor radio communication, lack of accuracy and navigation, high noise and high costs.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">The document U.S. Pat. No. 5,823,884 discloses a powered stage wagon comprising a chassis to which there is mounted a plurality of rolling support means, each of which is located at a respective corner of the chassis. The powered stage wagon also comprises a first and a second drive means, both mounted on the chassis in engagement with the surface over which the stage wagon is to move and are mutually spaced. The two drive means both comprise a wheel which is mounted for rotation about a drive shaft. At the end of the drive shaft remote from the wheel there is provided both a gear-box and a motor, so the motor drives the drive shaft via the gear-box so as to cause a rotation of the wheel. The entire assembly comprising the wheel, the drive shaft, the gear-box and the motor is mounted on a circular support member which is itself mounted for rotation about an axis perpendicular to the drive shaft. By actuating a second motor it is possible to cause the rotation of the circular support member and thereby alter the relative orientation of the wheel with respect to the surface over which the stage wagon is to move. By actuating the first motor it is possible to control the speed with which the stage wagon moves in the direction determined by the second motor.</p>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">One main disadvantage with the stage wagon according to the document U.S. Pat. No. 5,823,884 is that it causes damage to the floor surface caused by slippage, due to rotation of the drive wheel at slow speeds or at standstill. One way of trying to eliminate this problem is the use of special floor materials or require the wagon to move in order to rotate the wheel, limiting the types of movement the wagon can make. Another way of trying to eliminate this problem is to separate the functions of locomotion and steering, limiting the types of movement the wagon can make. However, these solutions result in other problems as is clear from the statements made above.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007">It is an object of the present invention to solve the above mentioned problems.</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008">According to the present invention there is provided in a first aspect a drive unit comprising a rolling means intended to be in frictional engagement with a surface over which said drive unit is intended to move. The drive unit also comprises a first driving means and a second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit while eliminating slippage between said rolling means and said surface. The first drive means is arranged on a rotatable support means rotatable about a center axis and operable to rotate said rolling means about a rolling axis, wherein said rolling means is displaced a predetermined distance from said center axis. The second driving means is operable to rotate said support means about said center axis. This drive unit eliminates the slippage between the rolling means and said surface. This is achieved without the use of any special floor materials or without limiting the types of movement the drive unit can make.</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009">Another advantage with this drive unit is that it is scalable, i.e. it is adaptable to be used in small, lightweight vehicles or for vehicles carrying extremely heavy loads.</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010">A further advantage in this context is achieved if said rolling axis is perpendicular to said center axis.</p>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said support means on its circumference is provided with a sprocket means driven by said second driving means by way of a transmission means.</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012">A further advantage in this context if said transmission means is a chain which is engaged with said sprocket means and a toothed wheel driven by said second driving means.</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said drive unit also comprises a tension wheel which is engaged with said chain.</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014">A further advantage in this context is achieved if said transmission means is a toothed wheel driven by said second driving means, wherein said toothed wheel is engaged with said sprocket means.</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said drive unit also comprises a planetary gear-box mounted on said first driving means, and in connection with said rolling means.</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016">A further advantage in this context is achieved if said rotatable support means is supported by a ball bearing means.</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said first and second driving means, each is a servomotor.</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018">A further advantage in this context is achieved if said rolling means is a wheel.</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said support means is a round plate.</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020">A further advantage in this context is achieved if said drive unit also comprises a rotation limiter arranged in the vicinity of said rotatable support means.</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021">Furthermore, it is an advantage in this context if said drive unit also comprises a sensor means arranged in the vicinity of said rotatable support means, which sensor means is operable to detect the position of said rotatable support means.</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022">Another object of the invention is to provide a powered vehicle comprising a chassis, at least three rolling means mounted on said chassis for engagement with a surface over which said vehicle is to move. At least two of said rolling means is a drive unit according to the present invention. This vehicle eliminates the slippage between said rolling means and said surface. This is achieved without the use of any special floor materials or without limiting the types of movement the vehicle can make.</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023">Another advantage is that this powered vehicle is scalable that is, it is adaptable to be a small, lightweight vehicle or a vehicle for carrying extremely heavy loads.</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024">Another advantage is that the vehicle comprises reusable components, which e.g. means that the drive unit easily can be moved from one vehicle to another.</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">A further advantage in this context is achieved if said powered vehicle comprises four rolling means, each situated at a corner of said chassis, and in that two of said four rolling means are drive units, each arranged at two diagonally arranged corners of said powered vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">Furthermore, it is an advantage in the context if said powered vehicle also comprises a wireless communication means for receiving control signals from a remote computer system to control said drive units.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">It should be emphasized that the term “comprise/comprising” when used in this specification is taken to specify the presence of stated features, steps or components but does not preclude the presence of one or more other features, integers, steps, components or groups thereof.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">Embodiments of the invention will now be described with a reference to the accompanying drawings, in which:</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a side view from above of a drive unit according to the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> shows a side view, partly in cross section, of a drive unit according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, mounted on a vehicle; and</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> shows a schematic diagram of a powered vehicle according to the present invention.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF EMBODIMENTS</heading>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> shows a side view from above of a drive unit <b>10</b> according to the present invention. The drive unit <b>10</b> comprises a rolling means <b>12</b> intended to be in frictional engagement with a surface (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>) over which said drive unit <b>10</b> is intended to move. Preferably, said rolling means <b>12</b> is a wheel <b>12</b>. The driving unit <b>10</b> also comprises a first driving means <b>14</b>, and a second driving means <b>16</b>, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit <b>10</b>. The first driving means <b>14</b> is arranged on a rotatable support means <b>18</b> rotatable about a center axis, c.a. The first driving means <b>14</b> is operable to rotate said rolling means <b>12</b> about a rolling axis (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>). The rolling axis is perpendicular to said center axis, c.a. As is apparent from <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the rolling means <b>12</b> is displaced a predetermined distance from the center axis, c.a. The second driving means <b>16</b> is operable to rotate the support means <b>18</b> about said center axis, c.a. In one preferred embodiment of the drive unit <b>10</b>, which is disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the first and second driving means <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>, each is a servomotor <b>14</b>, <b>16</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> also comprises a sprocket means <b>20</b> provided on the circumference of the support means <b>18</b>. The sprocket means <b>20</b> is driven by the second driving means <b>16</b> by way of a transmission means. In the embodiment disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, the transmission means is a chain <b>22</b> which is engaged with said sprocket means <b>20</b> and a toothed wheel <b>24</b> driven by said second driving means <b>16</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> also comprises a tension wheel <b>26</b> which can be in engagement with the chain <b>22</b>. The tension wheel <b>26</b> can be moved along a groove <b>28</b> so as to alter the tension on the chain <b>22</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> also comprises an inductive sensor <b>30</b> arranged in a sensor holder <b>32</b> to detect the position of the sprocket means <b>20</b>, i.e. the orientation of the wheel <b>12</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> also comprises a rotation limiter <b>34</b> arranged in the vicinity of the sprocket means <b>20</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">The rotation limiter <b>34</b> sets a mechanical limit to the rotation of the drive unit <b>10</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> can also be operated manually, in which case some cables are needed for each drive unit <b>10</b>. The rotation limiter <b>34</b> prevents the cables needed for the drive unit <b>10</b> from being damaged under manual operation,. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> there is also disclosed a stop bar and transmitting sensor <b>27</b> which functions in combination with the inductive sensor <b>30</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">Preferably, the drive unit <b>10</b> also comprises a planetary gear-box (not disclosed) mounted on the first driving means <b>14</b>, and in connection with the wheel <b>12</b>. The rotatable support means <b>18</b> is supported by a ball bearing means (not disclosed). The support means <b>18</b> is preferably a plate <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> there is disclosed a side view, partly in cross section, of a drive unit <b>10</b> according to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, mounted on a vehicle (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). The same elements disclosed both in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> are designated with the same reference signs. The only parts of the vehicle (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>), which partly is disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, is the vehicle frame <b>40</b> and the top plate <b>42</b> of the vehicle. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> there is also disclosed the surface <b>44</b> over which said drive unit <b>10</b> is intended to move. In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> there is also disclosed another advantage with the drive unit <b>10</b>, i.e. the relative placement of the servomotors <b>14</b>, <b>16</b> allows the drive unit <b>10</b> to be of a low height-limited only by the diameter of the first servomotor <b>14</b> plus suitable clearances.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">This imply another advantage with the present invention, i.e. the combination of low height and servomotors with high power give rise to both low height and high loading capacity.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">The drive unit <b>10</b> uses two motors <b>14</b>, <b>16</b> that, in combination, provide propulsion and steerage. The first motor <b>14</b> is mounted on a plate <b>18</b> supported by a ball bearing means. The plate <b>18</b> and the first motor <b>14</b> can therefore rotate with respect to the drive unit <b>10</b>, or a vehicle (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>). A planetary gear-box is mounted on the first motor <b>14</b> and a wheel <b>12</b> on the gear-box, in such a way that the wheel is offset to and at a right angle to the plates' <b>18</b> center of rotation, c.a.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">A second motor <b>16</b> is placed on the fixed portion of the drive unit <b>10</b> and can control the position of the rotating plate <b>18</b> by means of the chains <b>22</b>. The motion of the two motors can be controlled by a data system (see <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>) such that rotation of a part of the drive unit <b>10</b> and movement of the wheel <b>12</b> in combination provides propulsion at any angel to the drive unit <b>10</b>, or a vehicle.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">The resulting drive unit <b>10</b> has a number of advantages. It can be used for steering without excess sliding against and resulting damage to the underlying floor surface <b>44</b>. It can be rotated while the vehicle is at standstill, allowing the first movement of the vehicle to be in any direction. Preferably, the wheel is offset to the center of rotation by 100 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The offset of the wheel <b>12</b> will be related to the size of the drive unit <b>10</b> and the diameter of the wheel <b>12</b>. The drive unit <b>10</b> disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIGS. 1 and 2</figref> has a wheel diameter of 180 mm, and the offset is 100 mm.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">Another advantage with the drive unit <b>10</b> is that the wheel <b>12</b> can be placed close to the corner of a vehicle, to allow for a large wheelbase and therefore higher stability and accuracy.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">Another advantage is that the drive system is scalable, that is, it is adaptable to be used in small, lightweight vehicles or for vehicles carrying extremely heavy loads.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">In <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> there is disclosed a schematic diagram of a powered vehicle <b>50</b> according to the present invention. This vehicle <b>50</b> comprises two drive units <b>10</b>, of the same kind disclosed in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, and two passive rolling means <b>52</b>. The two drive units <b>10</b> are arranged in two diagonally arranged corners of the vehicle and the two passive rolling means <b>52</b> are arrange in the two other corners of the vehicle. The vehicle <b>50</b> is e.g. powered by a battery pack <b>54</b>. The vehicle <b>50</b> also comprises a wireless communication means <b>56</b> for communicating with a remote computer system <b>58</b> to control said drive unit <b>10</b>, i.e. the movement and steering of the vehicle <b>50</b>. The vehicle <b>50</b> also comprises a laser navigation unit <b>60</b>, e.g. a laser scanner which makes use of several reflectors mounted along the perimeter of e.g. the stage area. The vehicle <b>50</b> also comprises a central processing unit <b>62</b> which is connected to the laser navigation unit <b>60</b>, the wireless communication means <b>56</b>, the battery pack <b>54</b> and a number of servo amplifiers <b>64</b> which in turn are connected to the drive units <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">Another examples of the transmission means <b>22</b> can be a toothed gear or a belt drive. It is also possible to make use of a planetary gear, an eccentric gear or a spur gear in the dive unit <b>10</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">It is to be noted that the invention does not only relate to a stage wagon, but to a powered vehicle which can be used in many different applications, such as robotics and in material handling.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">The invention is not limited to the embodiments described in the foregoing. It will be obvious that many different modifications are possible within the scope of the following claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>The invention claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A drive unit comprising a rolling means intended to be in frictional engagement with a surface over which said drive unit is intended to move, a first driving means and a second driving means, co-operatively operable to provide both propulsion and steering of said drive unit while eliminating slippage between said rolling means and said surface, wherein said first driving means is arranged on a rotatable support means rotatable about a center axis and is operable to rotate said rolling means about a rolling axis, wherein said rolling means is displaced a predetermined distance from said center axis, wherein said second driving means is operable to rotate said support means about said center axis, allowing said support means and said rolling means to rotate with respect to said drive unit.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said rolling axis is perpendicular to said center axis.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said support means on its circumference is provided with a sprocket means driven by said second driving means by way of a transmission means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said transmission means is a chain which is engaged with said sprocket means and a toothed wheel driven by said second driving means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein said drive unit also comprises a tension wheel which is engaged with said chain.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00003">claim 3</claim-ref>, wherein said transmission means is a toothed wheel driven by said second driving means, wherein said toothed wheel is engaged with said sprocket means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said drive unit also comprises a planetary gear-box mounted on said first driving means, and in connection with said rolling means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said rotatable support means is supported by a ball bearing means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said first and second driving means, each is a servomotor.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said rolling means is a wheel.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said support means is a round plate.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said drive unit also comprises a rotation limiter arranged in the vicinity of said rotatable support means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00013" num="00013">
<claim-text>13. The drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein said drive unit also comprises a sensor means arranged in the vicinity of said rotatable support means, which sensor means is operable to detect the position of said rotatable support means.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00014" num="00014">
<claim-text>14. A powered vehicle comprising a chassis, at least three rolling means mounted on said chassis for engagement with a surface over which said vehicle is to move, wherein at least two of said rolling means each is the drive unit according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00015" num="00015">
<claim-text>15. The powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein said powered vehicle comprises four rolling means, each situated at a corner of said chassis, and in that two of said four rolling means are drive units, each arranged at two diagonally arranged corners of said powered vehicle.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00016" num="00016">
<claim-text>16. The powered vehicle according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00014">claim 14</claim-ref>, wherein said powered vehicle also comprises a wireless communication means for receiving control signals from a remote computer system to control said drive units.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
