<us-patent-grant lang="EN" dtd-version="v4.2 2006-08-23" file="US07298335-20071120.XML" status="PRODUCTION" id="us-patent-grant" country="US" date-produced="20071106" date-publ="20071120">
<us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<publication-reference>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>07298335</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<date>20071120</date>
</document-id>
</publication-reference>
<application-reference appl-type="utility">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>11165909</doc-number>
<date>20050624</date>
</document-id>
</application-reference>
<us-application-series-code>11</us-application-series-code>
<priority-claims>
<priority-claim sequence="01" kind="national">
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2004-186810</doc-number>
<date>20040624</date>
</priority-claim>
</priority-claims>
<classifications-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>Q</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>24</subgroup>
<symbol-position>F</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>H</section>
<class>01</class>
<subclass>Q</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>38</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
<classification-ipcr>
<ipc-version-indicator><date>20060101</date></ipc-version-indicator>
<classification-level>A</classification-level>
<section>G</section>
<class>06</class>
<subclass>F</subclass>
<main-group>1</main-group>
<subgroup>16</subgroup>
<symbol-position>L</symbol-position>
<classification-value>I</classification-value>
<action-date><date>20071120</date></action-date>
<generating-office><country>US</country></generating-office>
<classification-status>B</classification-status>
<classification-data-source>H</classification-data-source>
</classification-ipcr>
</classifications-ipcr>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>343702</main-classification>
<further-classification>343700 MS</further-classification>
<further-classification>361681</further-classification>
</classification-national>
<invention-title id="d0e61">Portable information terminal with communication capabilities</invention-title>
<references-cited>
<citation>
<patcit num="00001">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6654231</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Teshima</name>
<date>20031100</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361681</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00002">
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>6804110</doc-number>
<kind>B2</kind>
<name>Amemiya et al.</name>
<date>20041000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by examiner</category>
<classification-national><country>US</country><main-classification>361683</main-classification></classification-national>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00003">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>08-078931</doc-number>
<date>19960300</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00004">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>08-256009</doc-number>
<date>19961000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00005">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>11-355033</doc-number>
<date>19991200</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
<citation>
<patcit num="00006">
<document-id>
<country>JP</country>
<doc-number>2003-283232</doc-number>
<date>20031000</date>
</document-id>
</patcit>
<category>cited by other</category>
</citation>
</references-cited>
<number-of-claims>12</number-of-claims>
<us-exemplary-claim>1</us-exemplary-claim>
<us-field-of-classification-search>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>343702</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>343700 MS</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>343830</main-classification>
</classification-national>
<classification-national>
<country>US</country>
<main-classification>361681</main-classification>
</classification-national>
</us-field-of-classification-search>
<figures>
<number-of-drawing-sheets>3</number-of-drawing-sheets>
<number-of-figures>4</number-of-figures>
</figures>
<us-related-documents>
<related-publication>
<document-id>
<country>US</country>
<doc-number>20050285804</doc-number>
<kind>A1</kind>
<date>20051229</date>
</document-id>
</related-publication>
</us-related-documents>
<parties>
<applicants>
<applicant sequence="001" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Usui</last-name>
<first-name>Hideyuki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Chigasaki</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
<applicant sequence="002" app-type="applicant-inventor" designation="us-only">
<addressbook>
<last-name>Agata</last-name>
<first-name>Hiroaki</first-name>
<address>
<city>Yokohama</city>
<country>JP</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
<nationality>
<country>JP</country>
</nationality>
<residence>
<country>JP</country>
</residence>
</applicant>
</applicants>
<agents>
<agent sequence="01" rep-type="attorney">
<addressbook>
<orgname>Sawyer Law Group LLP</orgname>
<address>
<country>unknown</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</agent>
</agents>
</parties>
<assignees>
<assignee>
<addressbook>
<orgname>Lenovo (Singapore) Pte. Ltd.</orgname>
<role>03</role>
<address>
<city>Singapore</city>
<country>SG</country>
</address>
</addressbook>
</assignee>
</assignees>
<examiners>
<primary-examiner>
<last-name>Chen</last-name>
<first-name>Shih-Chao</first-name>
<department>2821</department>
</primary-examiner>
</examiners>
</us-bibliographic-data-grant>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p id="p-0001" num="0000">A portable information terminal with communication capabilities according to the present invention comprises a conductive housing, a display, and a planar antenna. The display is attached to the inside of the housing. The planar antenna is attached to the outside of the housing.</p>
</abstract>
<drawings id="DRAWINGS">
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00000" num="00000">
<img id="EMI-D00000" he="162.73mm" wi="127.00mm" file="US07298335-20071120-D00000.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00001" num="00001">
<img id="EMI-D00001" he="143.85mm" wi="132.93mm" file="US07298335-20071120-D00001.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00002" num="00002">
<img id="EMI-D00002" he="214.55mm" wi="131.15mm" file="US07298335-20071120-D00002.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
<figure id="Fig-EMI-D00003" num="00003">
<img id="EMI-D00003" he="96.44mm" wi="129.88mm" file="US07298335-20071120-D00003.TIF" alt="embedded image" img-content="drawing" img-format="tif"/>
</figure>
</drawings>
<description id="description">
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0001" level="1">FIELD OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0002" num="0001">The present invention relates generally to a portable information terminal with communication capabilities, and more specifically, to a portable information terminal comprising a conductive housing and a built-in antenna.</p>
<heading id="h-0002" level="1">BACKGROUND OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0003" num="0002">Some recent notebook type personal computers have a built-in antenna for a wireless local area network (WLAN) or Bluetooth (registered trade mark). A planar inverted F antenna (sometimes called an “F type antenna”) suitable for transmitting and receiving high frequencies is used as this antenna and embedded, for example, at the top of a rear cover or at the top of both sides of the rear cover.</p>
<p id="p-0004" num="0003">Many of today's rear covers are made of a conductive material to prevent electromagnetic radiation generated within the personal computers from leaking out. In order to allow an inverted-F antenna to transmit a radio wave to the outside and receive a radio wave from the outside, an opening is provided in a rear cover in the position where the inverted-F antenna is embedded and the opening is covered with a resin cap.</p>
<p id="p-0005" num="0004">The antenna requires a ground. However, the conventional structure as described above does not allow a large ground area to be provided. Consequently, such conventional antennas have a problem that they tend to be affected by the conductive material surrounding the antenna and therefore do not provide stable transmission and reception.</p>
<p id="p-0006" num="0005">Accordingly, what is needed is a system and method for overcoming the above-identified problems. The present invention addresses such a need.</p>
<heading id="h-0003" level="1">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p-0007" num="0006">A portable information terminal with communication capabilities according to the present invention comprises a conductive housing, a display, and a planar antenna. The display is attached to the inside of the housing. The planar antenna is attached to the outside of the housing.</p>
<?BRFSUM description="Brief Summary" end="tail"?>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="lead"?>
<description-of-drawings>
<heading id="h-0004" level="1">BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF THE DRAWINGS</heading>
<p id="p-0008" num="0007"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref> is a perspective view showing the external configuration of a notebook personal computer according to an embodiment of the present invention;</p>
<p id="p-0009" num="0008"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> is an exploded perspective view showing the configuration of a rear cover of the notebook personal computer shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>;</p>
<p id="p-0010" num="0009"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref> is a partly sectional view of the rear cover and a planar antenna, which are shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>; and</p>
<p id="p-0011" num="0010"><figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref> is a perspective view showing a structure in which coaxial cables are attached to the planar antenna shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>.</p>
</description-of-drawings>
<?brief-description-of-drawings description="Brief Description of Drawings" end="tail"?>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="lead"?>
<heading id="h-0005" level="1">DETAILED DESCRIPTION</heading>
<p id="p-0012" num="0011">[Description of Symbols]</p>
<p id="p-0013" num="0012"><b>10</b> . . . Notebook type personal computer</p>
<p id="p-0014" num="0013"><b>12</b> . . . PC main body</p>
<p id="p-0015" num="0014"><b>16</b> . . . Rear cover</p>
<p id="p-0016" num="0015"><b>22</b> . . . Hinge</p>
<p id="p-0017" num="0016"><b>24</b> . . . Concave</p>
<p id="p-0018" num="0017"><b>26</b> . . . Planar antenna</p>
<p id="p-0019" num="0018"><b>28</b>, <b>30</b>, <b>32</b> . . . Inverted F antennas</p>
<p id="p-0020" num="0019"><b>34</b> . . . Ground portion</p>
<p id="p-0021" num="0020"><b>36</b>, <b>38</b>, <b>40</b> . . . Resonators</p>
<p id="p-0022" num="0021"><b>42</b>, <b>44</b>, <b>46</b> . . . Notches</p>
<p id="p-0023" num="0022"><b>50</b>, <b>52</b>, <b>54</b> . . . Through-holes</p>
<p id="p-0024" num="0023"><b>56</b>, <b>58</b>, <b>60</b> . . . Coaxial cables</p>
<p id="p-0025" num="0024"><b>62</b> . . . Decorative laminate</p>
<p id="p-0026" num="0025">The present invention relates generally to a portable information terminal with communication capabilities, and more specifically, to a portable information terminal comprising a conductive housing and a built-in antenna. The following description is presented to enable one of ordinary skill in the art to make and use the invention and is provided in the context of a patent application and its requirements. Various modifications to the preferred embodiments and the generic principles and features described herein will be readily apparent to those skilled in the art. Thus, the present invention is not intended to be limited to the embodiments shown, but is to be accorded the widest scope consistent with the principles and features described herein.</p>
<p id="p-0027" num="0026">An object of the present invention is to provide a portable information terminal having a built-in antenna capable of providing stable transmission and reception even if its housing is electrically conductive.</p>
<p id="p-0028" num="0027">A portable information terminal with communication capabilities according to the present invention comprises a conductive housing, a display, and a planar antenna. The display is attached to the inside of the housing. The planar antenna is attached to the outside of the housing. The term “portable information terminal” as used herein refers to a notebook type personal computer, a PDA (Personal Digital Assistance), a cellular phone (PHS (Personal Handyphone System)), or the like. For the notebook type personal computer, the term “housing” as used herein corresponds to a rear cover attached to the notebook type personal computer main body so as to be freely opened and closed.</p>
<p id="p-0029" num="0028">The portable information terminal employs the conductive housing in order to block electromagnetic waves generated inside the terminal. However, since the planar antenna is attached to the outside of the housing, the terminal is unlikely to be affected by a display attached to the inside of the housing. As a result, stable transmissions and receptions can be carried out.</p>
<p id="p-0030" num="0029">Preferably, the housing has a concave formed over a predetermined area outside the housing. The planar antenna is attached in the concave. The portable information terminal further comprises a dielectric decorative laminate. The decorative laminate is attached so as to cover the planar antenna.</p>
<p id="p-0031" num="0030">In this case, the planar antenna is attached in the concave of the housing and is further covered with the decorative plate. Accordingly, the planar antenna is formed integrally with the housing. This simplifies the external configuration of the terminal. Moreover, the decorative plate is dielectric, so that radio waves transmitted and received by the planar antenna are not blocked by the decorative plate.</p>
<p id="p-0032" num="0031">Moreover, the planar antenna preferably has a resonator. The housing has a through-hole formed at a position corresponding to the resonator of the planar antenna. The portable information terminal further comprises a cable connected to the planar antenna and passing through the through-hole.</p>
<p id="p-0033" num="0032">In this case, the through-hole is formed at the position corresponding to the resonator of the planar antenna. Consequently, the vibration of the resonator is not prevented. Moreover, the cable connected to the planar antenna passes through the through-hole. This simplifies the wiring structure of the terminal.</p>
<p id="p-0034" num="0033">Preferably, the planar antenna is in electric contact with the housing.</p>
<p id="p-0035" num="0034">In this case, the planar antenna has a larger ground area and can thus carry out more stable transmissions and receptions.</p>
<p id="p-0036" num="0035">Moreover, the housing is preferably molded of carbon fiber reinforced plastics. The planar antenna is in contact with carbon fibers exposed from a surface of the housing.</p>
<p id="p-0037" num="0036">In this case, it is possible to ensure that the planar antenna and the housing are electrically contacted with each other.</p>
<p id="p-0038" num="0037">An embodiment of the present invention will be described below in detail with reference to the drawings. The same or corresponding parts will be denoted by the same reference numerals, and their descriptions will not be repeated.</p>
<p id="p-0039" num="0038">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 1</figref>, a notebook type personal computer <b>10</b> comprises a main body (hereinafter referred to as a “PC main body”) <b>12</b>, a rear cover <b>16</b> attached to the PC main body <b>12</b> via hinges <b>14</b> so as to be freely opened and closed, and a liquid crystal display (LCD) <b>18</b> attached to the inside of the rear cover <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0040" num="0039">A keyboard <b>20</b> and the like are arranged on a top surface of the PC main body <b>12</b>. The PC main body <b>12</b> contains a printed circuit board on which a CPU (Central Processing Unit), a memory, and the like are mounted, a hard disk drive, a flexible disk drive, a CD-ROM (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory) drive, and the like.</p>
<p id="p-0041" num="0040">The rear cover <b>16</b> is formed of carbon-fiber reinforced plastics (CFRP) so as not to allow the leakage of electromagnetic waves generated in the PC main body <b>12</b> or the LCD <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0042" num="0041">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the LCD <b>18</b> is installed inside the rear cover <b>16</b> using fixture such as hinges <b>22</b>. On the other hand, a rectangular concave <b>24</b> is formed over a predetermined area outside the rear cover <b>16</b>. The predetermined area occupies the greater part of, specifically at least half of, preferably 80% of a main surface of the rear cover <b>16</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0043" num="0042">A planar antenna <b>26</b> one size smaller than the concave <b>24</b> in the rear cover <b>16</b> is installed in the concave <b>24</b> parallel to the LCD <b>18</b>. The planar antenna <b>26</b> is formed of metal such as copper, nickel, a copper-nickel alloy, or phosphor bronze, or their plating.</p>
<p id="p-0044" num="0043">The planar antenna <b>26</b> has two WLAN inverted F antennas <b>28</b> and <b>30</b> on its long side and a Bluetooth inverted F antenna <b>32</b> on its short side. The inverted F antennas <b>28</b>, <b>30</b>, and <b>32</b> have resonators <b>36</b>, <b>38</b>, and <b>40</b>, respectively, extending from a ground portion <b>34</b> like a key and notches <b>42</b>, <b>44</b>, and <b>46</b>, respectively, formed between the resonators <b>36</b>, <b>38</b>, and <b>40</b> and the ground portion <b>34</b>. The ground portion <b>34</b>, which is common to the three inverted F antennas <b>28</b>, <b>30</b>, and <b>32</b>, is sufficiently large compared to the resonators <b>36</b>, <b>38</b>, and <b>40</b>. As shown in the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the ground portion <b>34</b> has almost the same size as that of the concave <b>24</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0045" num="0044">The planar antenna <b>26</b> thus has the WLAN inverted F antennas <b>28</b> and <b>30</b> and the Bluetooth inverted F antenna <b>32</b>. Consequently, the notebook type personal computer <b>10</b> can carry out transmissions and receptions using either system. Moreover, since the planar antenna <b>26</b> has the two WLAN inverted F antennas <b>28</b> and <b>30</b>, a diversity system can be realized.</p>
<p id="p-0046" num="0045">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, the planar antenna <b>26</b> is in electric surface contact with the rear cover <b>16</b>. Specifically, as exaggeratedly shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 3</figref>, carbon fibers <b>48</b>, a filler for CFRP, are exposed from a surface of the rear cover <b>16</b>. The carbon fibers <b>48</b> are in contact with the planar antenna <b>26</b> at many points. To realize such an electric contact, insertion molding is carried out when the rear cover <b>16</b> is formed of CFRP; the planar antenna <b>26</b> is inserted into the CFRP and molded integrally with it. Alternatively, compression molding may be used to harden CFRP thermally melted, together with the planar antenna <b>26</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0047" num="0046">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref> again, in the concave <b>24</b> of the rear cover <b>16</b>, rectangular through-holes <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>, and <b>54</b> are formed at positions corresponding to the inverted F antennas <b>28</b>, <b>30</b>, and <b>32</b> so as not to prevent the vibration of the resonators <b>36</b>, <b>38</b>, and <b>40</b>. As shown in the embodiment of <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the rectangular through-holes <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>, and <b>54</b> are formed at positions directly underneath corresponding resonators <b>36</b>. <b>38</b>, and <b>40</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0048" num="0047">With reference to <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 4</figref>, a coaxial cable <b>56</b> is connected to the resonator <b>36</b> and ground portion <b>34</b> of the inverted F antenna <b>28</b> by soldering. The coaxial cable <b>56</b> is connected to a transmission and reception circuit (not shown) in the PC main body <b>12</b> through the through-hole <b>50</b> as shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>. Coaxial cables <b>58</b> and <b>60</b> are similarly connected to the inverted F antennas <b>30</b> and <b>32</b>, respectively. The coaxial cables <b>58</b> and <b>60</b> are connected to the transmission and reception circuit in the PC main body <b>12</b> through the through-holes <b>52</b> and <b>54</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0049" num="0048">The coaxial cables <b>56</b>, <b>58</b>, and <b>60</b> are thus passed through the through-holes <b>50</b>, <b>52</b>, and <b>54</b>, respectively, formed so as not to prevent the vibration of the resonators <b>36</b>, <b>38</b>, and <b>40</b>. This simplifies the wiring structure.</p>
<p id="p-0050" num="0049">Finally, an adhesive decorative laminate <b>62</b> is fitted into and stuck to the concave <b>24</b> of the rear cover <b>16</b> so as to cover the planar antenna <b>26</b>. In the embodiment shown in <figref idref="DRAWINGS">FIG. 2</figref>, the decorative laminate is flat. The decorative laminate <b>62</b> is a rectangle having almost the same size as that of the concave <b>24</b>. The decorative laminate <b>62</b> is formed of a dielectric such as resin. Accordingly, the planar antenna <b>26</b> is formed integrally with the rear cover <b>16</b>, thus simplifying the external configuration. Moreover, radio waves transmitted and received by the planar antenna <b>26</b> are not blocked by the decorative plate <b>62</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0051" num="0050">As described above, according to the embodiment of the present invention, the rear cover <b>16</b> is formed of the CFRP in order to block electromagnetic waves generated in the PC main body <b>12</b> or the LCD <b>18</b>. However, the planar antenna <b>26</b> is attached to the outside of the rear cover <b>16</b> to ensure transmissions and receptions to and from external equipment. Further, the planar antenna <b>26</b> has the sufficiently large ground portion <b>34</b> and is in electric contact with the conductive rear cover <b>16</b>. Consequently, the planar antenna <b>26</b> is unlikely to be affected by the LCD <b>18</b>, the hinges <b>22</b>, or the like. This enables very stable transmissions and receptions. Moreover, the planar antenna <b>26</b> is attached to the outside of the rear cover <b>16</b>. This makes it possible to equally design any forms of notebook type personal computers.</p>
<p id="p-0052" num="0051">In the above embodiment, the rear cover <b>16</b> is formed of the CFRP. Alternatively, the rear cover <b>16</b> may be formed of a conductive material such as aluminum or steel. Further, the concave <b>24</b>, the planar antenna <b>26</b>, and the decorative laminate <b>62</b> need not be rectangular but may be square, circular, elliptical, trapezoidal, or parallelogrammatic. The shapes of these components are not limited. Furthermore, slot antennas having elongated rectangular holes may be used in place of the inverted F antennas <b>28</b>, <b>30</b>, and <b>32</b>. The type of the planar antenna is not limited. Moreover, a plasma display or the like may be used in place of the LCD <b>18</b>.</p>
<p id="p-0053" num="0052">The present invention is applicable not only to the notebook type personal computer but also to a PDA, a cellular phone, and the like. For a PDA or a cellular phone in which the LCD is integrated with the main body, the planar antenna may be attached to the outside of a conductive housing that accommodates the main body and the LCD. For a PDA or a cellular phone in which the LCD is attached to the main body so as to be freely opened or closed, the planar antenna may be attached to the outside of a conductive rear cover (housing) that accommodates the LCD.</p>
<p id="p-0054" num="0053">Although the present invention has been described in accordance with the embodiments shown, one of ordinary skill in the art will readily recognize that there could be variations to the embodiments and those variations would be within the spirit and scope of the present invention. Accordingly, many modifications may be made by one of ordinary skill in the art without departing from the spirit and scope of the appended claims.</p>
<?DETDESC description="Detailed Description" end="tail"?>
</description>
<us-claim-statement>What is claimed is:</us-claim-statement>
<claims id="claims">
<claim id="CLM-00001" num="00001">
<claim-text>1. A portable information terminal with communication capabilities, the portable information terminal comprising:
<claim-text>an electrically conductive housing, the electrically conductive housing having a concave formed over a greater part of a main surface of the electrically conductive housing;</claim-text>
<claim-text>a display attached inside of the electrically conductive housing; and</claim-text>
<claim-text>a planar antenna smaller than the concave formed over the greater part of the main surface of the electrically conductive housing, the planar antenna having a resonator and being installed in the concave of the electrically conductive housing,</claim-text>
<claim-text>wherein the electrically conductive housing includes a through-hole formed directly underneath the resonator of the planar antenna so as to not prevent vibration of the resonator.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00002" num="00002">
<claim-text>2. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, further comprising a dielectric decorative laminate fitted into the concave of the electrically conductive housing so as to cover the planar antenna in the concave of the electrically conductive housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00003" num="00003">
<claim-text>3. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, further comprising a cable connected to the planar antenna and passing through the through-hole of the electrically conductive housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00004" num="00004">
<claim-text>4. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00002">claim 2</claim-ref>, wherein the planar antenna is installed in the concave of the electrically conductive housing parallel to the display.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00005" num="00005">
<claim-text>5. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00004">claim 4</claim-ref>, wherein the planar antenna includes a plurality of WLAN inverted F antennas operable to carry out diversity transmission and diversity reception.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00006" num="00006">
<claim-text>6. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00005">claim 5</claim-ref>, wherein the planar antenna further includes a Bluetooth inverted F antenna.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00007" num="00007">
<claim-text>7. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the planar antenna is in electric contact with the electrically conductive housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00008" num="00008">
<claim-text>8. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein the decorative laminate is flat.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00009" num="00009">
<claim-text>9. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00007">claim 7</claim-ref>, wherein:
<claim-text>the electrically conductive housing is molded of carbon fiber reinforced plastics, and</claim-text>
<claim-text>the planar antenna is in contact with carbon fibers of the carbon fiber reinforced plastics exposed from a surface of the electrically conductive housing.</claim-text>
</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00010" num="00010">
<claim-text>10. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00001">claim 1</claim-ref>, wherein the portable information terminal is one of a personal computer, a personal digital assistant (PDA), of a cellular phone.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00011" num="00011">
<claim-text>11. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00006">claim 6</claim-ref>, wherein the planar antenna has a ground portion common to each of the plurality of WLAN inverted F antennas and the Bluetooth inverted F antenna.</claim-text>
</claim>
<claim id="CLM-00012" num="00012">
<claim-text>12. The portable information terminal according to <claim-ref idref="CLM-00011">claim 11</claim-ref>, wherein the ground portion of the planar antenna is almost a same size as a size of the concave of the electrically conductive housing.</claim-text>
</claim>
</claims>
</us-patent-grant>
